<!--from staging 2016_08_15 -->
<?xml-model href="oxygen:/Exist$84000-AWS/db/84000/schema/84000-ODD.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">གསང་སྔགས་ཆེན་པོ་རྗེས་སུ་འཛིན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānudhāraṇi</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">གསང་སྔགས་ཆེན་པོ་རྗེས་སུ་འཛིན་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa’i
                    mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Sūtra of Upholding the Great Secret
                    Mantra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānudhāraṇisūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation
                    Committee<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the
                    Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translator">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</author>
                <author role="translatorMain">James Gentry</author>
                <author role="translator">Andreas Doctor</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-090-007"/>
                <date>2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <ref>Toh 563</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 90 (rgyud ’bum, pha), folios 150b–156a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śīlendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jñānasiddhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śākyaprabha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bandé Yeshé Dé</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--title style="contentsPage">Contents
        
        <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Summary
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Acknowledgements
                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Introduction
                    
                    <title style="contentsTranslation">THE TRANSLATION
                        <title style="contentsTextTitle">The Sūtra of Upholding the Great Secret Mantra
                            
                            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Bibliography
                                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Notes-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>
                    <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title> is one of five
                    texts that together constitute the Pañcarakṣā scriptural collection, popular for
                    centuries as an important facet of Mahāyāna-Vajrayāna Buddhism’s traditional
                    approach to personal and communal misfortunes of all kinds. It addresses a range
                    of human ailments, as well as misfortunes such as robbery, natural disaster, and
                    criminal punishment, thought to be brought on especially through the animosity
                    of non-human spirit entities. The sūtra stipulates the invocation of these
                    spirit entities, which it separates into hierarchically ordered groups and thus
                    renders subordinate to the command of the Buddha and members of his saṅgha. The
                    Buddha stipulates that just “upholding” or intoning their names and the mantra
                    formula for each will quell the violent interventions of non-human entities and
                    even hasten them to provide for the pragmatic needs of the saṅgha and its
                    surrounding communities. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi
                    Nyima Rinpoche. The translation was produced by James Gentry, who also wrote the
                    introduction. Andreas Doctor compared the translation with the original Tibetan
                    and edited the text.</p>
                <p>This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānudhāraṇi</title>
                        <note place="end">The Sanskrit title in the Degé Kangyur is <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantranudhāraṇisūtra</title>, and the same
                            title (with variations in the diacritical marks) is found in the
                            Lithang, Cone and Lhasa Kangyurs. The Yunglo, Narthang, and Tok Palace
                            Kangyurs, however, have <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantranudhārisūtra</title> (again, with variations in the exact
                            spelling), and this latter alternative was preferred by the compilers of
                            the Tōhoku catalogue. However, the entry in Edgerton’s <title xml:lang="eng">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Dictionary</title> for
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānusāriṇī</title> suggests that
                            this, instead, may be the original Sanskrit name of the goddess
                            concerned.</note>, Toh 563) is the fifth scripture in a series of five;
                        the other four texts are the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsāhasrapramardanī</title> (Toh 558), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyūrīvidyārājñī</title> (Toh 559), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāpratisāravidyārājñī</title> (Toh 561), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāśītavana</title> (Toh 562). Together these five texts have been
                        apotheosized in the Mahāyāna tradition as five goddesses known collectively
                        as the Pañcarakṣā, or the “Five Protectresses.” In the Tibetan tradition
                        this collection is known by the moniker <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs chen grwa lnga</foreign>, the “Fivefold Great
                        Dhāraṇī.” In the Degé Kangyur collection these texts constitute 60, 49, 43,
                        25, and 12 folios, respectively, making a total of 189 folios. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Tibetan redactors of Kangyur collections have catalogued this set of five
                        texts together within the final Action (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kriyā</foreign>) tantras section of the “tantra collection”
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyud ’bum</foreign>) division.
                        Indeed, these scriptures do contain elements—powerful incantations, an
                        emphasis on external ritual hygiene and other material details such as
                        auspicious dates, and so forth—that resonate with standard kriyāyoga
                        practice as understood in Tibet. Yet missing from nearly all these texts is
                        any extensive mention of the contemplative visualization exercises,
                        specialized ritual gestures (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mudrā</foreign>), elaborate <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">maṇḍala</foreign> diagrams, and initiation ceremonies so typical of
                        full-blown Buddhist tantra. A close perusal of these five texts might then
                        lead the reader to construe them as standard Mahāyāna texts with a
                        preponderance of elements—magical mantra formulas, ritual prescriptions,
                        pragmatic aims, and so forth—that only later coalesced and developed into a
                        typically tantric practice tradition with its own unique set of view,
                        meditation, and conduct. To complicate things further, the core of the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyūrī</title>, for one, is rooted in
                        Indian Buddhist traditions that predate even the rise of Mahāyāna (Sørensen
                        2006: 90). The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyūrī</title> also appears as a
                        remedy for snakebites in the earlier <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinayavastu</title> (Pathak 1989: 32).<note place="end"> The story comes at the very end of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title> (Toh 1 ch. 6); see Yao,
                            Fumi (tr.). <title xml:lang="eng">On Medicinal Materials</title>. 84000:
                            Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</note> This accords
                        with Gregory Schopen’s general observation, based on inscriptional evidence,
                        that “dhāraṇī texts were publically known much earlier and more widely than
                        texts we think of as ‘classically’ Mahāyāna” (1989: 157). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Regardless of their bibliographical position in the Tibetan canon, the Five
                        Protectresses have been among the most popular texts used for pragmatic
                        purposes throughout the Mahāyāna-Vajrayāna Buddhist world. While it seems
                        certain that these texts each developed independently and were only later
                        combined into a five-text corpus, their popularity is attested by their
                        eventual spread to Nepal, Tibet, Central Asia, China, Mongolia, Korea,
                        Japan, and Indonesia (Hidas 2007: 189). In East Asia, the textual tradition
                        associated with the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Mahāmāyūrī</foreign> in particular was instrumental in integrating
                        Buddhist and indigenous notions of divine kingship (Orzech 2002: 58).
                        Moreover, the tradition of all five goddesses and their texts still occupies
                        a place of central importance today in the Vajrayāna Buddhism practiced by
                        the Newar population of the Kathmandu Valley, Nepal. Newar Buddhist
                        communities of Kathmandu have even translated the texts of the Five
                        Protectresses into the modern vernacular, based on which they continue to
                        stage a number of annual rites for a broad range of pragmatic purposes
                        (Lewis 2000: 119–164). Newars often propitiate the Five Protectresses
                        together by means of a five-section <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">maṇḍala</foreign> and other tantric elements that do not necessarily
                        feature in the scriptures themselves. This tradition reflects a specifically
                        tantric ritual treatment of the texts, which, judging by the presence of
                        tantric <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sādhana</foreign> practices
                        associated with these five texts in the Tibetan Tengyur collections, had
                        already developed by the time the Tibetan translations were executed.
                        Indeed, the Tibetan translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāpratisarā</title> reflects a recension of the Sanskrit text that
                        Gergely Hidas suggests “most likely served the better integration of this
                        text into the Vajrayāna, changing the historical locus of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nidāna</foreign> to a mythical Vajrayānic
                        setting” (2007: 188). This helps account for why the Tibetan redactors
                        construed these five texts as belonging to the category of kriyā tantra, and
                        not to the Dhāraṇī or Sūtra sections. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The designation Five Protectresses denotes the set of five texts, the
                        incantations presented therein, and the five goddesses presiding over each.
                        It is believed that all these texts, specifically their incantations,
                        provide special protection against a wide range of illnesses and misfortunes
                        for those who memorize, recollect, read, copy, teach, wear, or otherwise
                        come into contact with them. Each text promises protection from specific
                        misfortunes, with considerable overlap witnessed between the texts. Despite
                        the pragmatic thrust of these scriptures, each text also contains numerous
                        allusions to doctrinal notions. The range of effects described therein
                        sometimes, though rarely, extends beyond the pragmatic sphere to include the
                        purification of negative karma, deliverance from the lower realms, and even
                        the attainment of buddhahood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title> was
                        translated into Tibetan under Tibetan imperial patronage sometime during the
                        early ninth century by a translation team that included the
                        translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé (ca. late eighth to early ninth century)
                        and the Indian scholars Śīlendrabodhi, Jñānasiddhi, and Śākyaprabha. The
                        sūtra promises protection against a range of threats, from illnesses,
                        natural disasters, and dangers while traveling, to warfare, corporal
                        punishment, and theft. This text frames all of these perils as originating
                        from the animosity and ill will of human beings and spirits. The principal
                        focus is threats posed by the capricious spirit world of “non-humans”
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ma yin</foreign>), who feed
                        off the life force, vitality, flesh, and blood of humans. The negative
                        impact of these non-humans extends beyond the individual to include homes,
                        villages, towns, cities, regions, and entire countries. The text claims to
                        be efficacious by means of “drawing” or demarcating a “boundary” around
                        those in need of protection, sealing them off from the source of harm and
                        thereby restoring health and internal cohesion. It is through “receiving,
                        holding, reciting, preaching, and mastering” this scripture that such a
                        protective boundary is formed. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The narrative of the sūtra begins with an interchange between the Buddha and
                        the god Brahmā. Brahmā, along with his divine retinue, visits the Blessed
                        One at the Jetavana hermitage and requests that he “guard, protect, look
                        after, and bring peace and well-being” to the entire trichiliocosm of a
                        thousand million worlds, just as the god himself does for the chiliocosm of
                        a thousand worlds under his care. The Buddha acquiesces to his request by
                        remaining silent. He subsequently proceeds to teach the scripture’s dhāraṇī
                        formulas and to extol its many benefits. Much as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyūrīvidyārājñī</title>, but with less
                        elaboration, the Buddha prescribes the invocation by name of the spirits
                        responsible for personal and communal misfortunes. These litanies, which the
                        Buddha separates into groups based on the locations and activities of these
                        beings, hierarchically arrange the spirits so that they are all subordinate
                        to the Buddha’s command and to the command of his saṅgha. The Buddha states
                        that just “upholding” or intoning these names along with the mantra formula
                        that accompanies each group will urge them to obey members of the saṅgha so
                        that they desist from causing harm and instead serve the pragmatic needs of
                        the saṅgha and surrounding lay communities. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Owing to the absence of a reliable Sanskrit edition that reflects the Tibetan
                        translations, this English translation is based on the Tibetan Degé edition,
                        in consultation with the Pedurma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe
                            bsdur ma</foreign>) comparative edition. Thus, rather than adjudicate on
                        the many variant readings of the dhāraṇī formulas found in the different
                        Tibetan versions of this text, we have chosen to defer this issue for now
                        and record only the Degé version until a Sanskrit edition is produced that
                        might shed further light on the matter. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation">THE TRANSLATION</head>
                <head type="titleHon">The Sūtra of</head>
                <head type="titleMain">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>
                            <ref cRef="F.150.b"/> Homage to the Three Jewels! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the Buddha! Homage to the Dharma! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the Saṅgha! Homage to the seven perfectly and completely
                            buddhas, along with their śrāvakas—those who have perfectly gone, and
                            those who have perfectly entered! </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Having paid homage to them:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>May these incantations be practiced for a purpose! </l>
                        <l>May these incantations be accomplished!</l>
                        <l>May their purpose—the goal for which they are practiced—</l>
                        <l>Be accomplished!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in the Jetavana,
                        Anāthapiṇḍada’s grove in Śrāvastī. At that time, Brahmā, master of the Sahā
                        world, with the gods of the Brahmā realm; Śakra, lord of the gods, with the
                        gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three; the four great kings, with the gods
                        of their realm; the twenty-eight great yakṣa generals; and Hārītī with her
                        children and retinue of servants went before the Blessed One, bowed their
                        heads to his feet, and stood to one side. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Standing there, Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, bowed toward the Blessed
                        One with palms joined, and said, “Venerable Blessed One, I rule as lord over
                        the realms of the chiliocosm. <ref cRef="F.151.a"/> Venerable Blessed One,
                        when needed I guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to
                        the realms in the chiliocosm. Venerable Bliss-Gone Dharma Sovereign, Blessed
                        One, you rule as lord over the realms of the great trichiliocosm. Blessed
                        One, when you see fit you, too, guard, protect, look after, and bring peace
                        and well-being to the realms of the great trichiliocosm. So, Venerable
                        Blessed One, I request you to guard, protect, look after, and bring peace
                        and well-being to the realms of the trichiliocosm!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One acquiesced by remaining silent. Brahmā, master of the Sahā
                        world, understood that the Buddha had acquiesced by his silence, and at that
                        moment he vanished. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Subsequently, the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, last night I was
                        approached by Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, along with the gods of the
                        Brahmā realm; Śakra, lord of the gods, with the gods of the Heaven of the
                        Thirty-Three; the four great kings, with the gods of the realm of the four
                        great kings; and the twenty-eight great yakṣa generals; and Hārītī with her
                        children and retinue of servants also came. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, said to me, ‘Venerable Blessed One, I rule
                        as lord over the realms of the chiliocosm. Venerable Blessed One, when
                        needed, I guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to the
                        realms in the chiliocosm. <ref cRef="F.151.b"/> Venerable Bliss-Gone Dharma
                        Sovereign, Blessed One, you rule as lord over the realms of the great
                        trichiliocosm. Blessed One, when you see fit, you also guard, protect, look
                        after, and bring peace and well-being to the realms of the great
                        trichiliocosm. So, Venerable Blessed One, I request you to guard, protect,
                        look after, and bring peace and well-being to the realms of the
                        trichiliocosm!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, I acquiesced by not responding to Brahmā, master of the Sahā world.
                        Then Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, knowing that I had acquiesced by
                        remaining silent, disappeared at that moment. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great
                            Secret Mantra</title>, was taught by the perfectly and completely
                        awakened thus-gone arhats of the past. It will be taught by the perfectly
                        and completely awakened thus-gone arhats in the future. And likewise, right
                        now in the present, I will also teach it as an aid for the awakening of
                        buddhahood.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then the Blessed One said to venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, you are to receive,
                        hold, recite, preach, and master this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>! Ānanda, this
                        queen of incantations, Upholding the Great Secret Mantra, will bring
                        welfare, benefit, happiness, and comfort to the four assemblies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <q>
                        <p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">“Tadyathā. Ubuddhe nibuddhe
                                vibuddhe saṁbuddhe viśvaṣṭabuddhe īhabuddhe tattrabuddhe niyaṁgame
                                chavila apula tapula <ref cRef="F.152.a"/> tāle māle maṅgagamaṅga
                                manana imam vidyā hudume huhume pūrvaprahare.</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, this strong and powerful secret mantra, which has been practiced for
                        a long time, was taught by the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone
                        arhats of the past. It will be taught by the perfectly and completely
                        awakened thus-gone arhats in the future. And such is also the case at
                        present, as I now teach it to aid in the awakening of buddhahood. With this
                        queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret
                            Mantra</title>, I will protect and form a boundary around the person
                        named such-and-such. I will form a boundary one league to the east. I will
                        form a boundary one league in all the cardinal and intermediate directions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <q>
                        <p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">“Tadyathā. Samuca vimuca
                                palamuca jagadhara madasṭhala nalakamaga samuḥśvavāti vimukti yoga
                                hinasagama aradamula vihaṁgami idiciri vitalākhayo makhayo
                                lagabhidharaṇi pratiprāyogi aḥcakrapati samasraḥvati ilāya milāya
                                bahusaddhya anatama arthavati garavati tikhinitive akanati sakanati
                                samidima vasuvaṭe aṭe aṭe taṭṭa kharusmin kharusmin lahataṁ lahutaṁ
                                sambhara sambhara vatiranataṁ nirutaṁ ila taila saraphala bahuphala
                                satamata daṁṣṭrimata. </foreign>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, this strong and powerful secret mantra, which has been practiced for
                        a long time, was taught by the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone
                        arhats of the past. It will be taught by the perfectly and completely
                        awakened thus-gone arhats in the future. And such is also the case at
                        present, for I too teach it. Brahmā, lord of the Sahā world, teaches it.
                        Śakra, lord of the gods, also teaches it. The four great kings also teach
                        it. The twenty-eight great yakṣa generals also teach it. <ref cRef="F.152.b"/> And Hārītī, with her children and retinue of servants, also teaches it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, any monk, nun, layman, or laywoman who receives this queen of
                        incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret
                            Mantra</title>, and understands, sees, or performs it, precisely as it
                        has been taught and mastered, will be guarded, protected, looked after, and
                        brought peace and well-being for as long as he or she shall live. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, by the command of the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone
                        arhats of the past, future, and present, this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, shall guard,
                        protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to the person named
                        such-and-such. It will form a boundary. It will form a boundary one league
                        to the east. Likewise, it will form a boundary one league to the west. It
                        will form a boundary one league to the south. It will form a boundary one
                        league to the north. It will form a boundary one league in all the cardinal
                        and intermediate directions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, there are four who dwell on and off the path of the four great
                            kings.<note place="end">The commentary (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang
                                sngags chen mo rjes su ’dzin ma’i mdo’i ’bum ’grel</title>,
                            263b–264a) reads: “The ‘path of the four great kings’ is the four great
                            kings themselves…and those guarded by the four great kings. ‘Those not
                            on the path” refers to the sons of the great kings. These four entities
                            garner petty lords and retinues, enacting violence against beings. Who
                            are they? They cause harm in the east, south, west, and north, such that
                            the 80,000 types of obstructers are also included within these
                            four.”</note> Who are they? They are Auspicious, Friend to All,
                        Complete, and Glory of Joy. Whoever knows their names and families will not
                        be in danger of the great kings, nor will he be in danger of robbers, fire,
                        water, humans, or non-humans. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, Vajrapāṇi’s older brother called Swift Hand resides in the city
                        known as Cakravālapur. Whoever knows his name and family will be guarded,
                        protected, looked after, pardoned, <ref cRef="F.153.a"/> and brought peace
                        and well-being by him. On behalf of the person named such-and-such, I
                        beseech and supplicate Vajrapāṇi’s older brother Swift Hand! By the command
                        of the blessed buddhas of the past, future, and present, all yakṣas,
                        rākṣasas, pretas, piśācas, kumbhaṇḍas, pūtanas, and kaṭapūtanas who seek an
                        occasion and look for an opportunity to harm the person named such-and-such
                        will not find any such opportunity, nor will they be able to quarrel with
                        him! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, there are fourteen great rākṣasīs. They protected the Bodhisattva
                        while he was in his mother’s womb. They also protected him during his birth,
                        as a newborn, and while he was being reared. Who are they? They are
                        Powerful, Stainless, Tumult, Supple, Terrifying Lady, Voice of Jambu,
                        Supreme Seizer, Master, Renowned Female, Amazing Renown, Conflict Lover,
                        Playful Lady, Earth Supporter, and Conflict Engager. Whoever knows their
                        names and families will be guarded, protected, looked after, and brought
                        peace and well-being by them! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, there are eight rākṣasīs who steal the vitality of men or women
                        regardless of whether they are asleep or not. Who are they? They are Horn,
                        Unassailable, Instigator of Evil, Slanderous, Red Female Servant, Greatest,
                        Excellent Eyes, and Terrifying. Whoever knows their names and families will
                        be guarded, protected, looked after, and brought peace and well-being by
                        them! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, there are seven rākṣasīs who travel as far as one hundred miles when
                        they smell the scent of blood. Who are they? They are Excellent Splendor,
                        Layered Joy, Giver of Various Things, <ref cRef="F.153.b"/> Excellent White
                        Female Servant, Desiring Engagement, Surrounding City, and Mountain
                        Protector. Whoever knows their names and families will be guarded,
                        protected, looked after, brought peace and well-being, and granted pardon! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, there is a rākṣasī called Mahākālī with one thousand sons who lives
                        at the seashore and travels 80,000 miles in a single night. Whoever knows
                        her name and family will be guarded, protected, looked after, brought peace
                        and well-being, and granted pardon by her! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, there are five rākṣasīs who, along with 7,700,000 yakṣas, guard and
                        protect the humans in the Jambu continent. Who are they? They are Always
                        Insane, Further Insane, Bloated with Power, Bamboo Stick, and Wealthy.
                        Whoever knows their names and families will be guarded, protected, looked
                        after, brought peace and well-being, and granted pardon by them! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Therefore, on behalf of the person named such-and-such, I beseech and
                        supplicate those five rākṣasīs, along with the 7,700,000 yakṣas! By the
                        command of the blessed buddhas of the past, future, and present, may the
                        person named such-and-such be guarded, protected, looked after, brought
                        peace and well-being, and granted pardon! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <q>
                        <p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">“Tadyathā. Vīmude vītide
                                picarite pigarite karaṭi karavīra swāri madhuraghoṣe śatahanita
                                bhaṣitaghe akke nakke vika ḍitā vikuṭite viraje
                                vighaṣṭavāte.</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, nowhere in the worlds of gods, demons, Brahmā, mendicants, priests,
                        humans, kiṃnaras, and mahoragas have I seen anyone—whether human, non-human,
                        yakṣa, rākṣasa, asura, gandharva, nāga, garuḍa, guhyaka, preta, piśāca,
                        vetāla, kākhorda, kṛtya, pūtana, kaṭapūtana, unmada, or apasmāra—<ref cRef="F.154.a"/> who, seeking an opportunity to hurt and looking for
                        conflict, was ever able to harm a person guarded, shielded, protected,
                        looked after, brought peace and well-being, and granted pardon by this queen
                        of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret
                            Mantra</title>—unless, that is, the ripening of their karma precludes
                        it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Therefore, by the command of the blessed buddhas of the past, future, and
                        present, I will use this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, to guard the person named
                        such-and-such from humans, non-humans, yakṣas, rākṣasas, piśācas, asuras,
                        gandharvas, nāgas, garuḍas, guhyakas, pretas, vetālas, kākhordas, kṛtyas,
                        pūtanas, kaṭapūtanas, unmadas, and apasmāras. He will be protected,
                        shielded, brought peace and well-being, granted pardon, and purged of
                        poison. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“This queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the Great Secret
                            Mantra</title>, will intoxicate all those with hostile intentions, ill
                        will, animosity, and rage, as well as all demons, <ref cRef="F.154.b"/> trail
                        guards, fort guards, and customs guards. It will intoxicate them, cause
                        paralysis and stupefaction, and seize their hands, feet, minds, and tongues.
                        Through this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="eng">Upholding the
                            Great Secret Mantra</title>, the person will escape on each and every
                        occasion. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“Oh wonder! Brahmin! You transcended anguish,</l>
                        <l>Crossed over existence within the world,</l>
                        <l>And finally, after so long,</l>
                        <l>Saw the transcendence of all resentment and fear!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“Patience is the supreme austerity;</l>
                        <l>Patience is the supreme nirvāṇa—so proclaims the Buddha.</l>
                        <l>As for the ordained who harm others,</l>
                        <l>One who is violent toward others is not a proper renunciant.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“On the other hand, just as those with eyesight</l>
                        <l>Also have capabilities,</l>
                        <l>The wise, in this world of the living,</l>
                        <l>Avoid misdeeds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“To all the buddhas</l>
                        <l>Of present, future, and past</l>
                        <l>I pay homage!</l>
                        <l>To all of them I go for refuge!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“Since in the world it is the bliss-gone arhats</l>
                        <l>To whom the moon goes for refuge,</l>
                        <l>Buddhas, with compassion for the world,</l>
                        <l>Free the moon from Rāhu!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“‘Rāhu! The moon dispels darkness.</l>
                        <l>Illuminating the sky, </l>
                        <l>It shines with white </l>
                        <l>And pristine light. </l>
                        <l>Instead of seizing it in the sky,</l>
                        <l>Instantly release the lantern of creatures!’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“Then, suddenly,</l>
                        <l>Rāhu, with his body trembling and in a sweat</l>
                        <l>Like a sick person, </l>
                        <l>Abruptly released the moon.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“‘Rāhu, why did you,</l>
                        <l>Trembling and in a sweat</l>
                        <l>Like a sick person, </l>
                        <l>Suddenly release the moon?’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“‘If, upon uttering these verses of the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>The moon were not released,</l>
                        <l>My head would crack into seven pieces,</l>
                        <l>And even while alive, I would be unhappy.<note place="end">The commentary
                                    (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen mo rjes su ’dzin
                                    ma’i mdo’i ’bum ’grel</title>, 274a7) explains this in terms of
                                the next life. It states: “Even after dying, one will be reborn in
                                the hell of Endless Torment.”</note>’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“Oh wonder! Amazing is the emergence of buddhas</l>
                        <l>Who see the truth!</l>
                        <l>If one recites these verses,</l>
                        <l>Rāhu will release the moon.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: <ref cRef="F.155.a"/> one who is
                        unforgettable to beings appearing in the world is a ‘thus-gone one;’ that he
                        speaks by speaking truly means he speaks by speaking truly at the
                        appropriate time. Furthermore, Ānanda, those verses were spoken by the
                        Thus-Gone One to assist in the observation of pure conduct. And what is
                        more, Ānanda, the following words will secure the purpose, as well as
                        further assist and ease, whatever function those verses are set to perform: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <q>
                        <p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">“Syād. Athedana svasti mati
                                vilumati praharati kaśumadchi nanda mati vihagrahe vidumati edakṛta
                                ārtha sudṛśabuddhi bodhimati suhudume alakhūme alamite higaraśara
                                āśuha pragaśini. </foreign>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, the ten roots of seeds and the ten root words of seeds have been
                        spoken by the Thus-Gone One. Ānanda, these words will be spoken by Thus-Gone
                        Ones, and will be taught by them; so if people who dwell in their teaching
                        utter them, yakṣas and rākṣasas will perform activities for them like
                        slaves. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: true words at the irreversible
                        level are called the ‘words that are supreme in the world.’ Those who, of
                        all renunciants, are ‘the most joyful renunciants,’ the perfectly and
                        completely awakened, thus-gone arhats, who have neither fear nor terror,
                        who, neither cowering nor fleeing, lack fear, and who, having abandoned fear
                        and its impetus, are called ‘free of anything that causes one to cry out in
                        hair-raising panic’—these are what is meant by ‘those who speak by speaking
                        truly, those who speak by speaking truly at the appropriate time.’ By their
                        truth and those true words, may the person person named such-and-such have
                        well-being! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: of all those who observe ethical
                        discipline, controlled conduct, austerities, or pure conduct, those who are
                        known as ‘supreme in the discipline that pleases the noble ones’—by their
                        truth and their true words, may the person named such-and-such have
                        well-being! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Of the elders, Ājñātakauṇḍinya, like the eldest of a king’s sons, foremost
                        among those practicing pure conduct, <ref cRef="F.155.b"/> for a long time
                        has passed since his ordination; Mahākāśyapa, supreme among those with few
                        desires who adhere to the qualities from training and have contentment;
                        Śāradvatīputra, supreme among those with great wisdom and eloquence;
                        Mahāmaudgalyāyana, supreme among those with great miraculous powers and
                        great magical abilities; Aniruddha, supreme among those with the divine eye;
                        Ānanda, supreme among the learned; Upālī, supreme among holders of
                        discipline; Pūrṇamaitrāyaṇīputra, supreme among Dharma preachers; Rāhula,
                        supreme among those with respect for the trainings; Vasumallaputra, supreme
                        among those who distribute bedding and cushions; Piṇḍola Bhāradvāja, supreme
                        among those who proclaim the lion’s roar; Kālodāyin, supreme among those who
                        inspire householders; and Sudarśana, supreme among those who are venerated
                        by gods and men—by the truth and true words of these elders, may the person
                        named such-and-such be guarded, protected, looked after, brought peace and
                        well-being, and granted pardon. He shall be protected from kings, ministers,
                        robbers, fire, water, enemies, and adversaries, and when traveling, lost,
                        asleep, drunk, or careless! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: among all possible beings—those
                        without feet, with two feet, with four feet, or with many feet; those with
                        form or without form; those with perception, without perception, or neither
                        with nor without perception—the Thus-Gone One is called ‘supreme.’ By his
                        truth and his true words, may the person person named such-and-such be
                        guarded, protected, looked after, brought peace and well-being, and granted
                        pardon! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: in the entire range of conditioned
                        and unconditioned phenomena, freedom from attachment is called ‘supreme.’ By
                        that truth and those true words, <ref cRef="F.156.a"/> may the person person
                        named such-and-such be guarded, protected, embraced, brought peace and
                        well-being, and granted pardon. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: of all kinds of assemblies,
                        gatherings, multitudes, and retinues, the saṅgha of the Thus-Gone One’s
                        śrāvakas is called ‘supreme.’ By their truth and their true words, may
                        countries, regions, cities, towns, villages, houses, abodes, fields, and
                        this sick patient be guarded, protected, looked after, and brought peace and
                        well-being. Boundaries will be formed around them. All bhūtas will be turned
                        back. Those who steal vitality will be turned back. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“By such truth and true words, as follows: in order that I—a blessed,
                        perfectly and completely awakened, thus-gone arhat—may end this person’s
                        desire, anger, and ignorance, by the truth and true words of the teaching,
                        explanation, and enunciation of the 84,000 sections of teachings, may the
                        404 sicknesses of the person named such-and-such come to an end! May they be
                        eliminated! May they cease! May they cease completely!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p><!--modularPassage type=concludingPraise-->When the Blessed One had spoken,
                        the world, including venerable Ānanda, Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, and
                        all gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised what the
                        Blessed One had said.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p> This completes <title xml:lang="eng">The Sūtra of Upholding the Great Secret
                            Mantra</title>.</p>
                    <p>This was translated and edited by the Indian scholars Śīlendrabodhi,
                        Jñānasiddhi, and Śākyaprabha, along with the translator-editor Bandé Yeshé
                        Dé, who then revised it according to the new lexicon and finalized it. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Tibetan and Sanskrit Texts</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa’i mdo</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānudhāraṇisūtra</title>). Toh 563,
                        Degé Kangyur vol. 90 (rgyud ’bum, pha), folios 150b–156a. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa’i mdo</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānudhāraṇisūtra</title>). bka’ ’gyur
                        (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa
                        zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
                        Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing
                        House), 2006–2009, vol. 90, pp. 457–476. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen mo rjes su ’dzin ma’i mdo’i ’bum
                            ’grel</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmantrānudhāraṇīsūtraśatasahasraṭīkā</title>). Toh 2692, Degé
                        Tengyur vol. 72 (rgyud, du), folios 241b–282b. </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl>Hidas, Gergely (2012). <title xml:lang="eng">Mahāpratisarā-Mahāvidyārājñī,
                            The Great Amulet, Great Queen of Spells: Introduction, Critical Editions
                            and Annotated Translation.</title> Sata-pitaka Series: Indo-Asian
                        Literatures Vol. 636. New Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture and
                        Aditya Prakashan, 2012. </bibl>
                    <bibl>——— (2010). “<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāpratisarāvidyāvidhi</title>: The
                        Spell-Manual of the Great Amulet.” <title xml:lang="eng">Acta
                            Orientalia Academiae Scientiarum Hung</title>, vol. 63(4) (2010):
                        473–484. </bibl>
                    <bibl>——— (2007). “Remarks on the Use of the Dhāraṇīs and Mantras of the
                        Mahāpratisarā-Mahāvidyārājñī.” <title xml:lang="eng">In Indian
                            Languages and Texts Through the Ages: Essays of Hungarian Indologists in
                            Honour of Prof. Csaba Töttössy</title>. Edited by Csaba Dezsö, pp.
                        185–208. New Delhi: Manohar Publishers and Distributors, 2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lewis, Todd. <title xml:lang="eng">Popular Buddhist Texts from Nepal:
                            Narratives and Rituals of Newar Buddhism</title>. Albany: SUNY Press,
                        2000. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Orzech, Charles D. “Metaphor, Translation, and the Construction of
                        Kingship in the Scripture for Humane Kings and the Mahāmāyūrī Vidyārājñī
                        Sūtra.” <title xml:lang="fr">Cahiers d’Extreme-Asie</title>, vol. 13 (2002):
                        55–83. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pathak, Suniti K. “A Dharani-mantra in the Vinaya-vastu.” <title xml:lang="eng">Bulletin of Tibetology</title>, vol. 25, no. 2
                        (1989). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory. “A Verse from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadracaripranidhana</title> in a 10th Century Inscription found at
                        Nalanda.” <title xml:lang="eng">Journal of the International
                            Association of Buddhist Studies</title>, 12(1) (1989): 149–57. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Sørensen, Henrik H. “The Spell of the Great, Golden Peacock Queen: The
                        Origin, Practices, and Lore of an Early Esoteric Buddhist Tradition in
                        China.” <title xml:lang="eng">Pacific World Journal</title>, Fall
                        (8) (2006): 89–123. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te1">apasmāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brjed byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apasmāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te2">asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te3">bhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te4">gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te5">garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te6">guhyaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang ba pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">guhyaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te7">kākhorda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byad stems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kākhorda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te8">kaṭapūtana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus srul po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kaṭapūtana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te9">kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te10">kṛtya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshed byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṛtya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te11">kumbhaṇḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grul bum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumbhaṇḍa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te12">league</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyang grags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krośa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A measure of distance, one quarter of a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojana</foreign>; supposedly the
                                distance within which a cry can be heard.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te13">mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te14">nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te15">piśāca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">piśāca</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te16">preta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te17">pūtana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srul po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūtana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te18">rākṣasa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srin po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rākṣasa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te19">rākṣasī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srin mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rākṣasī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te20">unmāda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smyo byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">unmāda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te21">vetāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ro langs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vetāla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-te22">yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe1">Always Insane</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtag tu myos </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe2">Amazing Renown</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rmad grags </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe3">Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe4">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe5">Aniruddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ’gags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aniruddha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe6">Auspicious</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkra shis ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svastika</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe7">Bamboo Stick</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">od ma sbubs </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe8">Bloated with Power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs kyis rgyags </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe9">Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe10">Complete</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe11">Conflict Engager</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thab ’jug </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe12">Conflict Lover</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thab dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalahapriya?</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe13">Desiring Engagement</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">jug ’dod </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe14">Earth Supporter</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhūmidhāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe15">Excellent Eyes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig bzang </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe16">Excellent Splendor</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi brjid mchog </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe17">Excellent White Female
                                Servant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bren mo dkar mo bzang </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe18">Friend to All</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun bshes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viśvamitra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe19">Further Insane</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rjes su myos </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe20">Giver of Various Things</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sna tshog sbyin sbong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Citra?</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe21">Glory of Joy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīharṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe22">Greatest</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab chen </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe23">Hārītī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phrog ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hārītī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe24">Horn</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rwa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe25">Instigator of Evil</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan slob </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe26">Kālodāyin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag po ’char ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālodāyin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe27">Ājñātakauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun shes kauN+Din+ya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ājñātakauṇḍinya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe28">Layered Joy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ brtsegs </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe29">Mahākālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag mo chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākālī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe30">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe31">Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe32">Master</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prabhu, Guru</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe33">Mountain Protector</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri srung </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe34">Piṇḍola Bhāradvāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bha ra dwa dza bsod snyoms len </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Piṇḍola Bhāradvāja</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe35">Playful Lady</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtsed mo </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe36">Powerful</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Balī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe37">Pūrṇamaitrāyaṇīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams ma’i bu gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇamaitrāyaṇīputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe38">Rāhu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe39">Rāhula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan zin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhula</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe40">Red Female Servant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bran mo dmar mo </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe41">Renowned Female</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grags ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kīrtī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe42">Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe43">Śākyaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya pra bha va </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyaprabha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe44">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ra dwa t’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe45">Śīlendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shrI lendra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śīlendrabodhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe46">Slanderous</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phra ma can </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe47">Stainless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe48">Sudarśana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs mthong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sudarśana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe49">Supple</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab mnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pramṛdū</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe50">Supreme Seizer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog len </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramalabhā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe51">Surrounding City</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grong khyer ’khor yug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakravālapur</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe52">Swift Hand</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag myur </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laghupāṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe53">Terrifying</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">jigs byed </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe54">Terrifying Lady</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">jigs byed ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhairavā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe55">Tumult</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ghoṣā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe56">Unassailable</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thub med </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe57">Upālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar ’khor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upālī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe58">Vasumallaputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gyad bu nor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasumallaputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe59">Voice of Jambū</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzam bu’i mgrin </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe60">Wealthy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byor ldan </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pe61">Jñānasiddhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dznyA na siddhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānasiddhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pl1">great trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasramahāsāhasralokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest universe spoken of in Buddhist
                                cosmology, consisting of one billion smaller world systems.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pl2">Sahā world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sahā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A name for the “world” in which we live.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pl3">Jetavana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jetavana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pl4">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvastī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pl5">chiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gi ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sāhasralokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A universe in Buddhist cosmology consisting of
                                one thousand smaller world systems.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-090-007-pl6">Cakravālapur</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grong khyer khor yug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravālapur</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>