<!--Checked and edited by Simeon & marked Ready for Parser as of 5/5/16 -->
<!-- copied from staging 2016_08_15-->
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/84000-ODD.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyaparipṛcchā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་བྱམས་པས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba
                    theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Question of
                    Maitreya”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryamaitreyaparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain">Translated by Karen Liljenberg<lb/> under the
                    patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
                    Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translatorEng">Karen Liljenberg</author>
                <author role="translatorEng">Dr. Ulrich Pagel </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-044-005"/>
                <date>2016</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <ref>Toh 85</ref>, <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios
                        104b–116b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra </author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>In <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya</title>, the Bodhisattva
                    Maitreya asks the Buddha what qualities a bodhisattva needs to attain
                    enlightenment quickly. The Buddha outlines several sets of qualities, foremost
                    among them the altruistic intention of perfect bodhicitta. The Buddha then
                    recounts to Ānanda how, in a former life, Maitreya revered a previous Buddha
                    and, wishing to become just like him, at once realized that all phenomena are
                    unproduced. Ānanda asks why Maitreya did not become a buddha sooner, and in
                    answer the Buddha compares Maitreya’s bodhisattva career with his own, listing
                    further sets of qualities that differentiate them and recounting examples of the
                    hardships he himself faced in previous lives. Maitreya, on the other hand, has
                    followed the easy bodhisattva vehicle using its skillful means, such as the
                    seven branch practice and the training in the six perfections; the aspirations
                    he thus made are set out in the famous “Prayer of Maitreya” for which this sūtra
                    is perhaps best known. The Buddha declares that Maitreya will become enlightened
                    when sentient beings have less negative emotions, in contrast to the ignorant
                    and turbulent beings he himself vowed to help. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>This sūtra was translated from Tibetan into English by Dr. Karen Liljenberg, with
                    Dr. Ulrich Pagel acting as consultant. </p>
                <p>This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyaparipṛcchā</title>),<note place="end"> In the
                            Degé Kangyur this title, included within the text, is preceded by the
                            introductory sentence “From The Noble Great Heap of Jewels Dharma
                            discourse in one hundred thousand sections, section 41: The Noble
                            Elucidation of the Question of Maitreya in one fascicle.” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dkon mchog brtsegs pa chen po’i chos kyi
                                rnam grangs le’u stong phrag brgya pa las le’u bzhi bcu rtsa gcig pa
                                ste</foreign>/ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus
                                pa lung bstan pa/ bam po gcig pa</foreign>).</note> like most of the
                        sūtras that comprise the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>
                        collection, was translated into Tibetan from a Sanskrit original that is now
                        lost, but that may have dated back as far as the 1st or 2nd centuries CE,
                        i.e. several centuries before the collection itself was compiled. Apart from
                        the Tibetan Kangyur version, translated in the 9th century, and a fragment
                        in Sanskrit found in Central Asia,<note place="end">A fragment of the Stein
                            collection, published in 1911 by Louis de La Vallée Poussin, was
                            identified as part of this sūtra (corresponding to folios 108.b – 110.a
                            of the Degé edition) by Hisashi Matsumura in 1993 (see
                            bibliography).</note> the sūtra is extant only in an earlier Chinese
                        translation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Both the work translated here, sūtra number 41 in the Tibetan version of the
                        collection, and the work that follows, <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of
                            Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>, sūtra number 42, focus on the
                        important figure of the bodhisattva Maitreya, who is generally accepted as
                        destined to be the future Buddha of this world-system.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>In <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya</title>, the Buddha
                        predicts that Maitreya will attain enlightenment due to having applied the
                        skillful means of the bodhisattva vehicle (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvayāna</foreign>), a synonym for the
                        Mahāyāna. This vehicle, its entry, and its path are described as “easy,” in
                        contrast to the difficulties encountered by the Buddha himself. His hardship
                        is detailed in a passage that is unusual for its portrayal of the harsh
                        rejection of the Buddha and his teachings by some of his contemporaries.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The sūtra’s stories of the Buddha’s great sacrifices in three of his former
                        lives derive from earlier Jātaka literature. Although influential to some
                        extent in forming the ideal of the bodhisattva, such supreme heroic acts
                        were doubtless too daunting for most people. The reader is led to infer that
                        by following the example of Maitreya future bodhisattvas will be able to
                        attain enlightenment with relative ease. Thus, the sūtra implicitly promotes
                        the Mahāyāna, without devaluing earlier Buddhist traditions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The sūtra is probably best known for an aspiration prayer in verse that, the
                        Buddha tells Ānanda, was used by Maitreya six times daily as he was training
                        on the bodhisattva path (F.114.a – F.115.a, see milestones 1.66 - 1.89).
                        This prayer is widely known as <title xml:lang="eng">The Prayer of
                            Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam</title>)
                        or <title xml:lang="eng">The Sovereign Prayer of Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyapraṇidhanarāja</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam gyi rgyal po</title>); at least in
                        Tibetan Buddhism, its importance as a general Mahāyāna aspiration prayer is
                        perhaps second only to Samantabhadra’s <title xml:lang="eng">Prayer of Good
                            Action</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang spyod smon lam</title>,
                        from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūhasūtra</title>), and it is
                        recited daily in many monasteries. The verses are also found as an
                        independent text (but with this sūtra mentioned in the colophon as their
                        source) both in the Dhāraṇī section of the Kangyur (Toh 1096), and in the
                        Tengyur (Toh 4378). Although no Indian commentaries on this prayer are
                        known, it seems to have been recognized as a distinct feature of the sūtra
                        at least as far back as the early translation period, as evidenced by the
                        sūtra’s description in the Phangthangma catalogue (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>) as “the longer <title xml:lang="eng">Noble [Sūtra] of the Question of Maitreya</title> containing the
                        aspiration” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa chen po
                            smon lam can</title>). The prayer is the topic of several commentaries
                        in the Tibetan literature, notably those of Shākya Chokden (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA kya mchog ldan</foreign>, 1428-1507); Drukpa Pema
                        Karpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’brug pa pad ma dkar po</foreign>,
                        1527-1592); Tāranātha (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tA ra nA tha</foreign>,
                        1575-1634), who adds comments on the significance of the whole sūtra; Cone
                        Trakpa Shedrup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co ne grags pa bshad
                            sgrub</foreign>, 1675-1748); Ngulchu Dharmabhadra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngul chu dhar ma bha dra</foreign>, 1772-1851); and
                        Kyedor Khenpo Ngawang Khedrup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kye rdor mkhan po
                            ngag dbang mkhas grub</foreign>, 1779-1838).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>It is difficult to determine the precise historical relationship of <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya</title> with the much shorter
                        sūtra that follows it, <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya on the
                            Eight Qualities</title>. Their themes are closely linked—in both,
                        Maitreya questions the Buddha about the bodhisattva’s qualities. However,
                        their geographic setting differs—<title xml:lang="eng">The Question of
                            Maitreya</title> is delivered in a relatively obscure location, Mount
                        Śuśumāra in the country of the Bhargas, while <title xml:lang="eng">The
                            Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title> is set on Vulture
                        Peak Mountain near Rājagṛha, like many other <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> sūtras. The two texts also have different
                        colophons—the translation of the longer sūtra is attributed to Jinamitra and
                        Surendrabodhi, under the editorial supervision of Yeshé Dé, which would date
                        its Tibetan translation to the early ninth century. <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>, however, is
                        said to have been translated by Jinamitra and Danaśila, while Yeshé Dé is
                        said to have corrected it using the revised terminology (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skad gsar</foreign>). This may imply a
                        slightly later date for this translation, but could also indicate the
                        existence of an earlier Tibetan translation of <title xml:lang="eng">The
                            Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title> which required
                        updating in its terminology.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Other sūtras in which previous lives of Maitreya are recounted include the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmapuṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyapraṣṭhāna</title> (Toh 198), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Suvarṇaprabhāsa</title> (Toh 556-7). The story of his
                        obtaining the prophecy of his future buddhahood (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vyākaraṇa</foreign>) at the time of the Buddha
                        Ratnaśikhin is told in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinaya</title> (in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>
                        <note place="end">See Yao, Fumi (tr.). On Medicinal Materials. 84000:
                            Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</note>, the sixth
                        chapter of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh 1)—the same
                        account being found in the non-canonical <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title> collection—and in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyavyākaraṇa</title>, a text found in several Sanskrit
                        manuscripts, in a Chinese translation, and in a Tibetan version in the
                        Peking (P 1011) and Narthang Kangyurs, but not included in the Degé
                        Kangyur.</p>
                    <p>These two sūtras in the Ratnakūṭa, which are both often simply called <title xml:lang="eng">The Question of Maitreya</title>, are not to be confused
                        with a third sūtra of the same name in the General Sūtra (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>) section, Toh 149, a short work also
                        set in Rajgṛha in which Maitreya asks a quite different question.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The main Tibetan text used for the present translation was the Degé edition
                        of the Kangyur. Other Tibetan editions were also consulted but no
                        significant variations were found except for the one noted. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain">The Question of Maitreya</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <ref cRef="F.104.b"/>Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <p>Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was staying in the Country of
                        the Bhargas, on Mount Śuśumāra in a fearsome forest of wild animals,
                        together with a great saṅgha of about 500 monks, eminent śrāvaka-elders who
                        possessed clairvoyance. These included the omniscient venerable Kauṇḍinya,
                        and the venerables Aśvajit, Vaṣpa, Mahānaman, Bhadrika, Vimala, Pūrṇa,
                        Gavāṃpati, Mṛgaśiras, Uruvilva Kāśyapa, Nadī Kāśyapa, Gayā Kāśyapa, Jaṅghā
                        Kāśyapa, Mahākāśyapa, Amogharāja, Sumati, Śāriputra, the eminent
                        Maudgalyāyana, Parvatarāja, Nanda, Upananda, Ānanda, Rāhula and so on. <ref cRef="F.105.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Maitreya and 10,000 other bodhisattva mahāsattvas endowed with clairvoyance
                        had also assembled there. These included the bodhisattvas Vardhamānamati,
                        Sumati, Sthiramati, Viśālamati, Pratibhānakūṭa, Avalokiteśvara,
                        Mahāsthāmaprāpta, Kusumaśrī, Mañjuśrī, Abhijñāpuṣpasuparipūrṇa,
                        Anupalambhamanasikāra, Prasādavat, Ratnaketu, Indradeva, Varuṇadeva<note place="end">This inclusion of Indradeva and Varuṇadeva, Vedic deities,
                            among the assembly of attendant bodhisattvas is unusual. It is, however,
                            paralleled in another Ratnakuṭa sūtra, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatacintyaguhyanirdeśa</title> (Toh 47).</note>, Mṛdusvara,
                        Kṣetraviśodhana, Merukūṭa, Pratibhānasaṃpad, Indraśrī, Nimiṃdhara, Scourer
                        of the Hell-dwellers, Abandoner of Unfavorable Rebirths, Ratnakesarin and
                        others. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then the Blessed One, surrounded by this retinue of many hundreds of
                        thousands, surveyed those before him, and taught the Dharma. At that time,
                        the bodhisattva Maitreya was present in that very retinue. He surveyed the
                        great assembly of bodhisattvas, rose from his seat, draped his upper shawl
                        over one shoulder, set his right knee on the ground, and paid homage with
                        palms joined to the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>He asked the Blessed One, “Would the Blessed One, if he has time, please
                        answer certain questions that I would like to put to the Tathāgata, the
                        Arhat, the completely and perfectly enlightened Buddha?” </p>
                    <p>The Blessed One then replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya,
                        “Maitreya, <ref cRef="F.105.b"/> the Tathāgata always has time to answer
                        such questions. Ask whatever you wish, Maitreya. What I shall say in
                        response to your questions will cause you to rejoice.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One,
                        how many qualities does a bodhisattva need to possess in order to abandon
                        all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but
                        swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha?” </p>
                    <p>The Blessed One answered the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Maitreya, you
                        have served the victorious ones of the past, cultivated the roots of virtue,
                        recalled your past lives, acquired eloquence, and for a long time, lived
                        chastely. Maitreya, you work for the benefit of many people, bring happiness
                        to many people, and are compassionate toward the world. You live to bring
                        welfare, benefit, and wellbeing to ordinary beings, gods, and men, and to
                        assist the noble sons and daughters, present and future, who belong to the
                        vehicle of the bodhisattvas. It is indeed good that you have thought of
                        asking the Blessed One a question on this subject. Therefore, Maitreya,
                        listen well and carefully, and retain all that I say in your mind.” </p>
                    <p>The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya assented to the Blessed One, and listened
                        as the Blessed One had instructed. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One said, “Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses one single
                        quality, he will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of
                        sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and
                        become a buddha. What is that single quality? Having the altruistic
                        intention <ref cRef="F.106.a"/> of excellent bodhicitta. Maitreya, if a
                        bodhisattva possesses this single quality, he will abandon all evil rebirths
                        and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses two qualities, he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What two qualities? Thoroughly applying himself in calm abiding and
                        developing skill in insight. If a bodhisattva possesses these two qualities,
                        he will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses three qualities he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What three qualities? Attaining great compassion and having
                        definitive understanding of the teaching of emptiness, yet without being
                        arrogant. Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses these three qualities, he
                        will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses four qualities, he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What four qualities? Observing moral conduct, having no doubt about
                        the whole of the Dharma, delighting in seclusion, and not wavering from the
                        undertaking to which he has committed himself. [Fol. 106.b] Maitreya, if a
                        bodhisattva possesses these four qualities, he will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly
                        realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses five qualities, he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What five qualities? Dwelling in emptiness, not seeking the
                        delusions of others, investigating the self, delighting in the Dharma, and
                        being committed to helping others. Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses
                        these five qualities, he will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into
                        the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses six qualities, he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What six qualities? Being without attachment, aversion, and
                        ignorance; immediately answering questions correctly and properly, being
                        tireless in his ritual observance, and experiencing emptiness. Maitreya, if
                        a bodhisattva possesses these six qualities, he will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly
                        realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses seven qualities, he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What seven qualities? Being learned in mindfulness and <ref cRef="F.107.a"/> in the Dharma. Being diligent in his undertakings,
                        joyful, mentally supple, and skilled in meditative concentration and
                        analysis through wisdom. Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses these seven
                        qualities, he will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches
                        of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and
                        become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses eight qualities<note place="end">These eight, of course, comprise the noble eightfold
                            path.</note>, he will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the
                        clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What eight qualities? Possessing the
                        right view, right thought, right speech, right action, right livelihood,
                        right effort, right mindfulness, and right concentration. Maitreya, if a
                        bodhisattva possesses these eight qualities, he will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly
                        realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses nine qualities, he will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. What nine qualities? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Maitreya, that bodhisattva distances himself from desires and from sinful,
                        non-virtuous things. He investigates, examines, and possesses the joy and
                        happiness that arise from solitude. Thus, he accomplishes the first
                        meditative absorption and maintains it.<note place="end">This section
                            outlines the system of the eight meditative absorptions (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</foreign>; Pali <foreign type="term" xml:lang="pi">jhāna</foreign>), which are progressively
                            deeper states of meditation. The first four are termed “form” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpa</foreign>) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="pi">jhānas</foreign> because the absorption takes place
                            within the fine material sphere (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</foreign>; Pali <foreign type="term" xml:lang="pi">rūpaloka</foreign>). The final four are called
                            “formless” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arūpa</foreign>)
                            because they take place in the formless spheres (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arūpyadhātu</foreign>; Pali <foreign type="term" xml:lang="pi">arūpaloka</foreign>), and are also known
                            as the four attainments (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samāpatti</foreign>). For a presentation of the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="pi">Jhāna</foreign> system followed in the
                            present-day Theravāda, see Gunaratana, “The Jhānas in Theravāda Buddhist
                            Meditation,” pp. 9-20. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“He is free from thinking or examining, and possesses inner serenity. Because
                        his mind stream is one-pointed, he does not think <ref cRef="F.107.b"/> or
                        examine. Endowed with the joy and happiness that arise from meditative
                        concentration, he then accomplishes the second meditative absorption and
                        maintains it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Because he is free from attachment to joy, he maintains equipoise and
                        possesses mindfulness and awareness. He experiences the physical happiness
                        of which the noble ones say, ‘To possess mindfulness and remain in happiness
                        is equanimity<note place="end">This is a citation from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭādaśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title> (<title xml:lang="eng">Perfection of Wisdom in 18,000 Lines</title>), (Toh
                            11, vol. 29, f. 162b). The preceding passage is also found
                        there.</note>.’ Free of joy he then accomplishes the third meditative
                        absorption, and maintains it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“He renounces happiness after already renouncing suffering. Because both
                        mental happiness and mental displeasure decline, there is neither happiness
                        nor suffering. He then accomplishes the fourth meditative absorption and
                        maintains it, with immaculate equipoise and mindfulness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“He transcends conceptions of form in all aspects, and his conceptions of
                        materiality decline. When he does not fabricate conceptions of any kind, he
                        thinks, ‘This is the infinity of space,’ and then accomplishes the sphere of
                        the infinity of space and maintains it. After he has transcended the sphere
                        of the infinity of space in all aspects, he thinks, ‘This is the infinity of
                        consciousness,’ and then accomplishes the sphere of the infinity of
                        consciousness and maintains it. After he has transcended the sphere of the
                        infinity of consciousness in all aspects, he thinks, ‘This is nothingness,’
                        and then accomplishes the sphere of nothingness and maintains it. After he
                        has transcended the sphere of nothingness in all aspects, he then
                        accomplishes the sphere of neither perception nor non-perception and
                        maintains it. After he has transcended the sphere of neither perception nor
                        non-perception in all aspects, he then accomplishes the cessation of
                        perception and feeling and maintains it.<note place="end">This is a fifth
                            accomplishment sometimes added to the four formless absorptions.</note>
                        Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses these nine qualities, he will abandon
                        all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but
                        swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Furthermore, Maitreya, if a bodhisattva <ref cRef="F.108.a"/> possesses ten
                        qualities, he will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches
                        of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and
                        become a buddha. What ten qualities? Having vajra-like meditative
                        concentration, meditative concentration that is assiduous regarding what is
                        correct and incorrect, meditative concentration of going via methods,
                        illuminating meditative concentration, all-illuminating meditative
                        concentration, manifest meditative concentration, precious moon meditative
                        concentration, moon-lamp meditative concentration, meditative concentration
                        without afflictive emotions, and victory-banner finial meditative
                        concentration. Maitreya, if a bodhisattva possesses these ten qualities, he
                        will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was then satisfied and delighted. Joyful
                        and pleased, he rose from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, set
                        his right knee on the ground, and bowed to the Blessed One with joined
                        palms. He praised the Blessed One with these fitting verses: </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya</speaker>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“In former times, you practiced generous giving. </l>
                            <l>Giving away dear sons, food and drink, </l>
                            <l>And even your head and eyes, </l>
                            <l>You perfected the total generosity of a buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“For a long time, like a yak its tail,<note place="end">This odd,
                                    seemingly culturally Himalayan simile does not appear to be due
                                    to any corruption in the text: Narthang and Shol merely offer
                                        <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul ring(s)</foreign>
                                    instead of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yun
                                        ring</foreign>. Indeed, the same simile is found in other
                                    Kangyur texts, again in the context of guarding moral
                                    conduct.</note>
                            </l>
                            <l>You observed unimpaired moral conduct. </l>
                            <l>Peerless in your conduct,</l>
                            <l>You wholly perfected the conduct of a buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“You generated the power of patience,</l>
                            <l>And patiently endured the wrong deeds of ignorant people. <ref cRef="F.108.b"/>
                            </l>
                            <l>Possessing all the powers of patience,</l>
                            <l>You wholly perfected the patience of a buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“You generated the power of diligence,</l>
                            <l>Then found unsurpassed peace and happiness.</l>
                            <l>Powerful due to your diligence,</l>
                            <l>You wholly perfected the diligence of a buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“After burning up all sins, </l>
                            <l>You, great guide and being, took pleasure in your meditation.</l>
                            <l>Powerful due to the power of meditation,</l>
                            <l>You wholly perfected the meditation of a buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Through wisdom that realizes </l>
                            <l>That phenomena are by nature empty</l>
                            <l>And that nothing intrinsically arises, </l>
                            <l>You reached the other shore and wholly perfected the wisdom of a
                                buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Wise One, beneath the Bodhi tree</l>
                            <l>You subdued clawed demons</l>
                            <l>And attained the supreme goal.</l>
                            <l>As the Buddha, you vanquished the evil gathering of demons.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Great being, at Vārāṇasī</l>
                            <l>You turned the wheel of the Dharma.</l>
                            <l>You terrified the assembly of evil unbelievers,</l>
                            <l>And, as the Buddha, vanquished the unbelievers’ gatherings.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Unsurpassed for your vast wisdom,</l>
                            <l>Utterly without compare,</l>
                            <l>You teach the Jewel of the Dharma,</l>
                            <l>O guide and Buddha, you bring about illumination.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“You are peerless in generosity,</l>
                            <l>Strength of moral conduct, patience, and diligence.</l>
                            <l>You have accomplished the perfection of everything.</l>
                            <l>You excel, O Buddha, with your many qualities.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </sp>
                    <p>After the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya had praised the Blessed One in
                        verse with such fitting words, he stood to one side. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The venerable Ānanda then said to the Blessed One, “Lord, Blessed One, it is
                        wonderful that the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya is so supremely eloquent,
                        and that he teaches the Dharma with such words of certainty, that he teaches
                        the Dharma with such matching words and letters, that he teaches the Dharma
                        with such profound words, that he teaches the Dharma with words that explain
                        it so well, <ref cRef="F.109.a"/> and that he teaches the Dharma with such
                        memorable words.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied, “Exactly, Ānanda. It is just as you have said—it is
                        wonderful that the bodhisattva Maitreya is so supremely eloquent, that the
                        bodhisattva Maitreya teaches the Dharma with such words of certainty, and
                        all of what you said, up to his teaching the Dharma with such memorable
                        words. Ānanda, this is not the first time that the bodhisattva Maitreya has
                        praised me with such fitting verses. Why? Formerly, Ānanda, in times gone
                        by, at a time when ten countless ages had passed, there came into the world
                        <!--modularPassage type=tathāgataDescription1-->a tathāgata, arhat,
                        completely and perfectly enlightened buddha, endowed with perfect knowledge
                        and perfect conduct, established in a state of bliss, commanding all worldly
                        knowledge, an unsurpassed guide who converted all beings, a teacher of gods
                        and men<!--/modularPassage-->, the Buddha Arhat named
                            Jyotivikrīḍitābhijñā.<note place="end"> The Sanskrit name of this
                            tathāgata is attested in the Sanskrit fragment mentioned in the
                            Introduction (see also Matsumura 1993). The name is also a component of
                            the names of two of the 35 “tathāgatas of confession,” found in a
                            liturgy much used in the Tibetan tradition and extracted from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayaviniścayopāliparipṛcchā</title> (Toh 68);
                            the Tibetan of the equivalent part of the names in the latter text is
                            slightly different, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer rnam par rol pa
                                mngon par mkhyen pa</foreign> (see Python 1973, pp. 34 and
                            100).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“At that time, there lived a brahmin boy named Bhadraśuddha,
                        <!--modularPassage type=handsomeness-->good-looking, handsome and beautiful
                        to behold, endowed with a supremely good complexion and excellent
                        figure<!--/modularPassage-->. He was going to a pleasure-grove, when between
                        the villages he saw the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the completely and perfectly
                        enlightened Buddha Jyotivikrīḍitābhijñā.
                        <!--modularPassage type=buddhaQualities-->He was handsome and charismatic,
                        controlled in his faculties and in his mind. He had attained excellence in
                        control and calm abiding, and superiority in control and calm abiding. He
                        guarded his faculties, elephant-like in control of his passions, and
                        radiant, unsullied, and clear like a lake. His body was adorned with the
                        thirty-two marks of a great being, and with the eighty minor marks, like the
                        blossoming flower of a royal sal tree, and towering like Mount Meru, the
                        king of mountains. His face was as calm as the sphere of the moon, <ref cRef="F.109.b"/> and radiantly clear and brilliant like the sphere of
                        the sun. His body was proportioned like a nyagrodha tree, blazing with light
                        and great splendor.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Seeing him, Bhadraśuddha developed an attitude of faith towards the Blessed
                        One. With this attitude of faith, he thought, ‘How marvelous! How wondrously
                        this body of the Tathāgata is adorned in its complexion and splendor. It
                        blazes with glory, marks of buddhahood, and clear, brilliant radiance.’ The
                        brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha then spoke out loud, ‘How marvelous! May I also, in
                        the future, come to possess such a body, blazing like this in complexion,
                        magnificence, splendor, marks of buddhahood, with clear, brilliant
                        radiance!’ </p>
                    <p>“After he had prayed thus, he lay on the ground and thought, ‘If I shall come
                        to possess, in the future, such a body, blazing like this in complexion,
                        magnificence, splendor, marks of buddhahood, with clear, brilliant radiance,
                        may the Tathāgata touch me with his foot.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Then, Ānanda, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the completely and perfectly
                        enlightened Buddha Jyotivikrīḍitābhijñā, learning of the noble intention of
                        the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha, approached him and touched him with his foot.
                        As soon as the Tathāgata Jyotivikrīḍitābhijñā had touched the brahmin boy
                        Bhadraśuddha with his foot, at that very moment the boy attained acceptance
                        of the fact that all phenomena are unproduced. Ānanda, the Tathāgata
                        Jyotivikrīḍitābhijñā looked behind him and addressed the monks, ‘Monks, on
                        no account should you tread on the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha with your feet.
                        Why? Because he is <ref cRef="F.110.a"/> a bodhisattva mahāsattva who has
                        accepted the fact that all phenomena are unproduced.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“At that very moment, the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha obtained the knowledge of
                        the divine eye, knowledge of the divine ear, knowledge of the thoughts of
                        others, knowledge recollecting his past lives, and also accomplished
                        miraculous powers. In the presence of the Tathāgata Jyotivikrīḍitābhijñā he
                        spoke the following fitting verses of praise: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Though I roamed and searched in all cardinal and intermediate
                            directions, </l>
                        <l>There is no lord of man such as you in all the worlds. </l>
                        <l>The perfect Buddha is supreme in all realms of existence. </l>
                        <l>O great self-arisen guide, to you I pay homage. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Just as the bright sun in the sky, </l>
                        <l>In all worldly realms of the cardinal and intermediate directions, </l>
                        <l>Illuminates all these worlds with its light, </l>
                        <l>So do your splendid qualities—O Buddha, to you I pay homage. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Just as a lion roaring in the deep forests </l>
                        <l>Subdues the fox and all other ordinary animals, </l>
                        <l>So you, the noblest and most powerful of men, </l>
                        <l>Subdue all the great assemblies of unbelievers. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘The Sugata’s fair ringlet between his eyebrows, </l>
                        <l>Endlessly splendid like a hoard of silver or snow, </l>
                        <l>Illuminates all these worlds. </l>
                        <l>In all the worlds there is nobody who equals you, O Buddha. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Best of beings, you possess celestial wheels </l>
                        <l>Bright and fair, with a thousand spokes and spinning rims, </l>
                        <l>On your feet: these marks cause the earth, with its mountains and
                            forests, to tremble. </l>
                        <l>O Sage, you are unrivalled by ordinary beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Your great knowledge discards afflictive emotions and abandons
                            everything. </l>
                        <l>Noble One, you discovered the path of deliverance, <ref cRef="F.110.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Possessing every wealth, rich in qualities, </l>
                        <l>You array the wealth of a noble one as you please.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘You are comparable to the earth, and without equal as a recipient of
                            offerings. </l>
                        <l> You have obtained mastery of all good qualities, and your moral conduct
                            is pure. </l>
                        <l>Just as hands cannot grasp or capture space, </l>
                        <l>So too, in the worlds you possess no attachment or anger.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Reaching ultimate acceptance,<note place="end">This translation of
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa zad kyis gtugs
                                    pa</foreign> is tentative.</note> you learnt that all objects
                            and phenomena </l>
                        <l>Are without essence, fictitious, and impure. </l>
                        <l>In all those arrogant sentient beings that migrate in saṃsāra, </l>
                        <l>You found no life force or substance.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘Adapting to their dispositions and actions, and knowing their
                            thoughts, </l>
                        <l>You are a wondrous lamp that discerns them. </l>
                        <l>Since you witnessed beings carried away by the great river, </l>
                        <l>You formerly produced the power of firm strength of diligence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘You possess a mind that rejects rebirth and pacifies afflictive
                            emotions, </l>
                        <l>Your vast mind brought birth, old age, and death to an end. </l>
                        <l>Like the sphere of space you are without attachment, </l>
                        <l>Untainted by worldly qualities, you roam the three worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“ ‘O great being, your wisdom brings illumination, </l>
                        <l>Dispelling every darkness that has gathered. </l>
                        <l>You calm the dust of attachment and dispel the darkness </l>
                        <l>Of the various stains of anger and ignorance—to you I pay homage.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, this does not yet exhaust the miraculous displays and supernormal
                        powers of the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha. Ānanda,
                        <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether the brahmin boy
                        Bhadraśuddha was then at that time someone else, or you are of two minds
                        about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why? Because the bodhisattva
                        mahāsattva Maitreya himself was then at that time the brahmin boy
                        Bhadraśuddha<!--/modularPassage-->, <ref cRef="F.111.a"/> who uttered these
                        verses of praise to the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly enlightened
                        Buddha Jyotivikrīḍitābhijña.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The venerable Ānanda replied, “Blessed One, if this bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Maitreya developed acceptance so long ago of the fact that all phenomena are
                        unproduced, why did he not quickly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment
                        and become a buddha?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied to the venerable Ānanda:</p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>The Blessed One</speaker>
                        <p>“Ānanda, the bodhisattvas set in place and protect<note place="end">The
                                terms provisionally translated here as “set in place” and “protect”
                                are <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkod pa</foreign> and
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su gzung
                                    ba</foreign> in Tibetan. </note> two things. What two things?
                            They set in place and protect sentient beings, and they set in place and
                            protect their buddha realms. But of these two, when formerly the
                            bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was engaged in the conduct of a
                            bodhisattva, he set in place, consecrated, and protected his buddha
                            realm. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, when I myself was formerly engaged in the conduct of a
                            bodhisattva, I set in place and protected sentient beings, and I also
                            set in place and protected my buddha realm. Ānanda, I knew through
                            foresight that forty-two eons after the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya
                            entered the path I would first arouse the mind of supreme, perfect
                            enlightenment. Ānanda, with the knowledge that, ninety-four eons after
                            that good eon had passed, I would realize supreme, perfect
                            enlightenment, I applied myself, Ānanda, with burning diligence <ref cRef="F.111.b"/> and quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment
                            and became a buddha. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, it was by means of ten qualities that I quickly accomplished
                            supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. What ten qualities?
                            I abandoned and let go of all doubts, abandoned and let go of my spouse,
                            abandoned and let go of my child, abandoned and let go of my head,
                            abandoned and let go of my eyes, abandoned and let go of my kingdom,
                            abandoned and let go of my wealth, abandoned and let go of my blood,
                            abandoned and let go of my bones and marrow, and abandoned my limbs. By
                            letting go of everything I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                            enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, it was by means of those ten
                            qualities that I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and
                            became a buddha. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, it was also by means of a further ten qualities that I quickly
                            accomplished supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. What
                            ten qualities? Ānanda, I adhered to the teaching of the qualities of
                            moral conduct, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment
                            and became a buddha. Ānanda, I possessed the power of patience, and so I
                            quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha.
                            Ānanda, I applied ardent diligence, and so I quickly realized supreme,
                            perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I adhered to the
                            qualities of meditation, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                            enlightenment and became a buddha. <ref cRef="F.112.a"/> Ānanda, I
                            adhered to the perfection of wisdom, and so I quickly realized supreme,
                            perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I did not abandon any
                            sentient being in any way, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                            enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I was skillful in my means,
                            and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a
                            buddha. Ānanda, I treated all sentient beings equally, and so I quickly
                            realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I
                            realized the teaching of emptiness, and so I quickly realized supreme,
                            perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I realized the
                            teaching of signlessness and wishlessness, and so I quickly realized
                            supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, it was by
                            means of those ten qualities that I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                            enlightenment and became a buddha. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, if you were aware of how harsh and severe were the sensations of
                            suffering by which I realized supreme and completely perfect
                            enlightenment, perfect buddhahood, you, Ānanda, would not be so
                            forthright. The reason, Ānanda, is that formerly in times gone by there
                            lived a prince named Giver of All Wealth, good-looking, handsome, and
                            beautiful to behold, endowed with a supremely good complexion, excellent
                            figure, and with the great wealth and power of a king. He was going to a
                            pleasure grove, when he saw between the villages a man afflicted with
                            suffering and seriously ill. At this sight, he felt compassion,
                            approached the man and said, <ref cRef="F.112.b"/> ‘Man, what are you
                            suffering from?’ </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“He said, ‘Your Highness, I have contracted an illness.’ </p>
                        <p>“He said ‘Man, what will assuage your illness? What shall I give you?’ </p>
                        <p>“The man replied, ‘Your Highness, if I were to drink just enough of the
                            blood from your body to satisfy me, my illness would be assuaged.’ </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Then, Ānanda, Prince Giver of All Wealth took a sharp knife, cut
                            himself, and gave the man the blood that drained from the wound to
                            drink. Ānanda, as soon as the man drank it, his illness was cured.
                            Ānanda, even though Prince Giver of All Wealth cut himself and all his
                            blood drained out, he never had a moment’s regret. Ānanda,
                            <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether Prince Giver
                            of All Wealth was then at that time someone else, or you are of two
                            minds about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why? Because I myself
                            was then, at that time, Prince Giver of All
                            Wealth.<!--/modularPassage--> Ānanda, all the water of the four great
                            oceans can be measured, but the blood that I have given to sentient
                            beings as I sought supreme, completely perfect enlightenment can not. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, formerly in times gone by there lived a prince named Puṣpa,
                            good-looking, handsome and beautiful to behold, endowed with a supremely
                            good complexion, excellent figure, and with the great wealth and power
                            of a king. He was going to the site of a pleasure grove when he saw
                            between the villages a man who had contracted dropsy, afflicted with
                            suffering and seriously ill. </p>
                        <p>“At this sight, he felt compassion and approached the man, and said,
                            ‘Man, what will assuage this illness of yours? What shall I give you?’ </p>
                        <p>“The man replied, <ref cRef="F.113.a"/> ‘Your Majesty, if I were to get
                            just enough of the marrow from your body to satisfy me, my illness would
                            be assuaged.’ </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Prince Puṣpa was satisfied and delighted; he rejoiced, and then pleasure
                            and happiness arose in him. He beat his own body, then gouged out the
                            marrow and smeared it on that man’s body. Ānanda, as soon as he smeared
                            it on him, the man’s illness was cured. Ānanda, even though Prince Puṣpa
                            beat his own body so that the marrow dripped out, he felt no regret in
                            his mind. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether
                            Prince Puṣpa was then at that time someone else, or you are of two minds
                            about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why? Because I myself was
                            then, at that time, Prince Puṣpa.<!--/modularPassage--> Ānanda, all the
                            water of the four great oceans, can be measured, but the marrow that I
                            have given to sentient beings as I sought supreme, completely perfect
                            enlightenment can not. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, formerly in times gone by there lived a king named Candraprabha;
                            good-looking, handsome and beautiful to behold, endowed with a supremely
                            good complexion, excellent figure, and with the great wealth and power
                            of a king. He was going to a pleasure grove, when between villages he
                            saw a poor, eyeless blind man, a destitute beggar. At this sight, he
                            felt compassion. </p>
                        <p>“That man then approached King Candraprabha and said, ‘Your Majesty, you
                            are happy. Your Majesty, you are joyful, but I suffer. I am blind; I
                            have no eyes. I am poor and destitute. I am a beggar without refuge.’ </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Then, Ānanda, King Candraprabha saw the man again, and after listening
                            to his words again he wept, and still in tears, asked him, ‘Man, what do
                            you need? <ref cRef="F.113.b"/> Should I give you food or drink? A
                            riding-mount? Jewelry? Gold, gems, pearls, or various kinds of precious
                            things? Tell me whatever you need.’ </p>
                        <p>“The man replied, ‘I beg you, please give me your eye.’ </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“So, Ānanda, King Candraprabha plucked out his eye and gave it to the
                            man. But, Ānanda, although King Candraprabha had plucked out his eye and
                            given it to the man, he did not become regretful. Ānanda,
                            <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether King
                            Candraprabha was then at that time someone else, or you are of two minds
                            about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why? Because I myself was
                            then, at that time, King Candraprabha.<!--/modularPassage--> Ānanda,
                            Mount Meru, the king of mountains, can be measured, but the eyes that I
                            have given to sentient beings as I sought supreme, completely perfect
                            enlightenment are too great and can not. </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was formerly engaged in
                            the conduct of a bodhisattva, because the vehicle is easy, the entry is
                            easy, and the path is easy,<note place="end">I have not found the phrase
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa bde ba ’jug pa
                                    bde ba lam bde ba</foreign> attested elsewhere.</note> he
                            perfectly accomplished supreme, perfect enlightenment. Ānanda, when the
                            bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was formerly engaged in the conduct of a
                            bodhisattva he did not let go of his arms, legs, or marrow. He did not
                            renounce and let go of his spouse, his child, village, town, city, royal
                            palace, or retinue. But, Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                            Maitreya was formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, because
                            he fully embraced skillful means, through the easy vehicle, the easy
                            entry, and the easy path, <ref cRef="F.114.a"/> he accomplished supreme,
                            perfect enlightenment.” </p>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then the venerable Ānanda asked, “Blessed One, what were the skillful means
                        to which the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya adhered, thus accomplishing
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment?” </p>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, when formerly the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Maitreya engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, he would drape his shawl
                        over one shoulder, set his right knee on the ground, and put the palms of
                        his hands together three times during the day and three times during the
                        night. Making all the buddhas visible, he would then speak to them in these
                        words: </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Maitreya</speaker>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Homage to all the buddhas! </l>
                            <l>Homage to the bodhisattvas,</l>
                            <l>Those sages with the divine eye—</l>
                            <l>And to the śrāvakas, too. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Homage to the mind of enlightenment,</l>
                            <l>Which reverses all negative rebirths,</l>
                            <l>Shows the path to higher rebirths,</l>
                            <l>And leads beings to the state without aging or death.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Whatever negative actions I have done</l>
                            <l>Under the influence of mind,</l>
                            <l>Here in the presence of the buddhas</l>
                            <l>I confess them.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Whatever accumulation of merit</l>
                            <l>I have produced through the three kinds of action<note place="end">
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las rnam pa
                                        gsum</foreign>, “the three [kinds of] actions” is
                                    interpreted by Dharmabhadra and Ngawang Khedrup to mean
                                    meritorious actions of body, speech, and mind, but by Padma
                                    Karpo to be meritorious actions causing rebirth as a human,
                                    meritorious actions causing rebirth as a god, and
                                    “non-transferring” actions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi g.yo ba’i las</foreign>) causing
                                    rebirth in the two higher realms (of form and no-form).
                                </note>,</l>
                            <l>May it be the seed of my omniscience</l>
                            <l>And inexhaustible enlightenment.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Whatever offerings to the buddhas </l>
                            <l>Arise in all realms throughout the ten directions,</l>
                            <l>The buddhas know and rejoice in them,</l>
                            <l>And at that I myself rejoice.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘I confess all negative actions.</l>
                            <l>I rejoice in all meritorious acts.</l>
                            <l>I pay homage to all the buddhas.</l>
                            <l>May I attain supreme awareness! <ref cRef="F.114.b"/>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘I exhort the bodhisattvas</l>
                            <l>Of all ten directions,</l>
                            <l>Who abide on the ten bodhisattva levels,</l>
                            <l>To attain supreme enlightenment.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘May they become truly enlightened buddhas,</l>
                            <l>Overcoming negative influences of every kind,</l>
                            <l>And then, to benefit living beings,</l>
                            <l>May they turn the wheel of the Dharma.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Through the sound of the great Dharma drum,</l>
                            <l>May they bring the suffering of sentient beings to an end.</l>
                            <l>For unimaginable millions of eons,</l>
                            <l>May they teach the Dharma and continue to remain in this world.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘I beg you, best of all humans,</l>
                            <l>Look upon those who are trapped in the swamp of desire,</l>
                            <l>And tightly bound by the cords of craving,</l>
                            <l>Fettered in every kind of bond.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Buddhas, do not belittle</l>
                            <l>Those whose minds are defiled,</l>
                            <l>But with loving intent toward all sentient beings,</l>
                            <l>Save them from the sea of existence.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘May I train in the footsteps</l>
                            <l>Of the perfect buddhas, those present now,</l>
                            <l>Those of the past, and of the future,</l>
                            <l>And may I engage in the conduct of the bodhisattvas.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘May I complete the six perfections</l>
                            <l>And liberate beings of the six realms.</l>
                            <l>May I realize the six supernormal powers</l>
                            <l>And reach supreme enlightenment.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Unproduced and non-arising,</l>
                            <l>Without self-nature or location,</l>
                            <l>Neither mental cognition, nor substance—</l>
                            <l>May I realize the teaching of emptiness.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Just like the Buddha, the great sage,</l>
                            <l>May I realize the teaching of non-self—</l>
                            <l>A sentient being does not exist, nor does a living being,</l>
                            <l>Nor does an individual, or a person.<note place="end">“Person” here
                                    is a translation of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gso
                                        ba</foreign>.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘May I not dwell on there being anything substantial, </l>
                            <l>A belief in a self and what I take to be mine;</l>
                            <l>But in order to make all sentient beings happy,</l>
                            <l>May I give everything away without miserliness.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Since material objects do not really exist,</l>
                            <l> May my wealth be spontaneously accomplished.</l>
                            <l>Since all material objects decay,</l>
                            <l> May I complete the perfection of generosity.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Possessing conduct that is flawless,</l>
                            <l>Conduct that is perfect,</l>
                            <l>And conduct that is without arrogance, <ref cRef="F.115.a"/>
                            </l>
                            <l>May I complete the perfection of moral conduct.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Like the elements of earth, water, fire,</l>
                            <l>And wind, not dwelling on anything,<note place="end">The commentaries
                                    differ considerably in their interpretations of these two lines,
                                    with Padma Karpo emphasizing simply the inanimate nature of the
                                    four elements, and most of the others detailing particular
                                    qualities of patience for which each of the four is a simile.
                                    Despite the syntax, most agree that “not dwelling” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi gnas pa</foreign>) refers
                                    principally to the wind element. The translation here is an
                                    attempt to remain open to more than one interpretation. </note>
                            </l>
                            <l>With patience and<note place="end">Degé and most other Kangyurs have
                                        <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa’am</foreign>
                                    here in Toh 85, but <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod
                                        pa’ang</foreign> in the versions in the Dhāraṇī section (Toh
                                    1096) and in the Tengyur (Toh 4378), which makes more sense; the
                                    Tok Palace (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang gi bris
                                        ma</title>) manuscript Kangyur has simply bzod pa</note>
                                free of anger,</l>
                            <l>May I complete the perfection of patience.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Through diligent application of diligence,</l>
                            <l>May I have constant enthusiasm without laziness,</l>
                            <l>And with strength of body and mind,</l>
                            <l>May I complete the perfection of diligence.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Through magic-like meditative concentration,</l>
                            <l>Meditative concentration of bravery,</l>
                            <l>And vajra-like meditative concentration,</l>
                            <l>May I complete the perfection of meditation.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Actualizing the three gates to liberation,</l>
                            <l>The sameness of the three times,</l>
                            <l>And the threefold knowledge,<note place="end">According to
                                    Tāranātha’s commentary, the threefold knowledge (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa gsum</foreign>)
                                    comprises 1) knowledge of the whole of the past (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngon gyi mtha’ rig
                                        pa</foreign>), 2) knowledge of the whole of the future
                                        (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyi ma’i mtha’ rig
                                        pa</foreign>), and 3) knowledge of the exhaustion of
                                    defilements (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag zad rig
                                        pa</foreign>); the other commentaries, however, take the
                                    three kinds of knowledge as knowledge of the minds, mental
                                    events, and their causes, of all sentient beings in the past,
                                    present, and future.</note>
                            </l>
                            <l>May I complete the perfection of wisdom.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘May I be praised by all the buddhas,</l>
                            <l>And blaze with light and splendor;</l>
                            <l>Through the diligence of a bodhisattva,</l>
                            <l>May my intention be fulfilled.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“ ‘Thus engaging in such conduct,</l>
                            <l>May I, who am known as Maitreya,</l>
                            <l>Complete the six perfections</l>
                            <l>And dwell on the ten bodhisattva levels.’</l>
                        </lg>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, those are the skillful means through which the bodhisattva
                        mahāsattva Maitreya, by adhering to them, through the joyous vehicle, the
                        joyous entry, and the joyous path, perfectly accomplished supreme, perfect
                        and complete enlightenment. Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya
                        was formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, he thought to himself,
                        ‘How I wish that sentient beings, having less desire, anger, and ignorance,
                        may acquire the path of the ten virtuous actions! In the future, may I
                        perfectly accomplish supreme, perfect and complete enlightenment and become
                        a Buddha.’ It was thus that he consecrated his Buddha realm. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, such a time and period will come about; then sentient beings will
                        become less desiring, angry, <ref cRef="F.115.b"/> and ignorant, and keep to
                        the path of the ten virtuous actions. After that, the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Maitreya, due to the power of his prayer, will perfectly accomplish supreme,
                        perfect and completely enlightened buddhahood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, when I formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, I made this
                        prayer: ‘When the world is beset with the five degenerations, sentient
                        beings will have great desire, anger, and ignorance. Desire, anger, and
                        ignorance will all increase. Beings will desire and crave irreligious
                        things. They will be overcome by fearsome desire, and adopt false doctrines.
                        They will despise their fathers, their mothers, their cousins, and their
                        siblings, their partners, their relatives, noble beings, abbots, spiritual
                        teachers, themselves, and others. These people will be filthy, wild, and
                        stupid. How wonderful it will be if I can perfectly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a Buddha among them!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Having lived in such a terrible epoch, Ānanda, I have kindled great
                        compassion. Today, when I enter villages, cities, towns, districts and
                        provinces, and the surroundings of royal palaces with great compassion, as
                        soon as I teach the Dharma I am slandered and reviled, harshly abused and
                        told not to create a gathering. Ānanda, it is even said that I am a
                        nihilist, or that I am an eternalist. They say that those in my retinue have
                        many desires, and that their desires are great. When I enter into houses,
                        earth is thrown at me. I am given food mixed with poison. They even have
                            <ref cRef="F.116.a"/> bonfires made for me. So it is. Although I am a
                        Buddha, I am denigrated as cohabiting with so-called ‘beautiful women’ and
                        the like. Ānanda, I kindled great compassion, and with great compassion, I
                        now teach the Dharma to such sentient beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, those are the skillful means through which the bodhisattva
                        mahāsattva Maitreya, by adhering to them, through the joyous vehicle, the
                        joyous entry, and the joyous path, perfectly accomplished supreme, perfect
                        and complete enlightenment. Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya
                        was formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, he thought to himself,
                        ‘How I wish that sentient beings, having less desire, anger, and ignorance,
                        may acquire the path of the ten virtuous actions! In the future, may I
                        perfectly accomplish supreme, perfect and complete enlightenment and become
                        a Buddha.’ It was thus that he consecrated his Buddha realm. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, such a time and period will come about; then sentient beings will
                        become less desiring, angry, [F.115.b] and ignorant, and keep to the path of
                        the ten virtuous actions. After that, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya,
                        due to the power of his prayer, will perfectly accomplish supreme, perfect
                        and completely enlightened buddhahood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Ānanda, when I formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, I made this
                        prayer: ‘When the world is beset with the five degenerations, sentient
                        beings will have great desire, anger, and ignorance. Desire, anger, and
                        ignorance will all increase. Beings will desire and crave irreligious
                        things. They will be overcome by fearsome desire, and adopt false doctrines.
                        They will despise their fathers, their mothers, their cousins, and their
                        siblings, their partners, their relatives, noble beings, abbots, spiritual
                        teachers, themselves, and others. These people will be filthy, wild, and
                        stupid. How wonderful it will be if I can perfectly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a Buddha among them!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Having lived in such a terrible epoch, Ānanda, I have kindled great
                        compassion. Today, when I enter villages, cities, towns, districts and
                        provinces, and the surroundings of royal palaces with great compassion, as
                        soon as I teach the Dharma I am slandered and reviled, harshly abused and
                        told not to create a gathering. Ānanda, it is even said that I am a
                        nihilist, or that I am an eternalist. They say that those in my retinue have
                        many desires, and that their desires are great. When I enter into houses,
                        earth is thrown at me. I am given food mixed with poison. They even have
                            <ref cRef="F.116.a"/> bonfires made for me. So it is. Although I am a
                        Buddha, I am denigrated as cohabiting with so-called ‘beautiful women’ and
                        the like. Ānanda, I kindled great compassion, and with great compassion, I
                        now teach the Dharma to such sentient beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The venerable Ānanda then said to the Blessed One, “The Blessed One who
                        teaches the Dharma to such sentient beings, converting those not previously
                        converted by the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly enlightened Buddha, has
                        taken on a great burden, and undergone hardships.” </p>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied to the venerable Ānanda, “Exactly, Ānanda. It is just
                        as you have said. Ānanda, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly
                        enlightened Buddha has tamed those not previously tamed, taken on a great
                        burden, and himself endowed with every virtuous quality, undergone hardship
                        by teaching the Dharma to such sentient beings. Why? Because this is how
                        much he was gripped by great compassion.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The venerable Ānanda then replied, “That the Blessed One should bestow such a
                        Dharma discourse, that I should hear this Dharma discourse, and hear this
                        topic from the Blessed One, the best of men, is hair-raising and amazing.
                        Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma discourse? How should it be
                        remembered?” </p>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied, “From now onward, Ānanda, you should remember this
                        Dharma discourse as ‘The Former Prayer that is Truly Noble.’ You should also
                        remember it as ‘The True Arising of the Tathāgata.’ You should also remember
                        it as ‘The Arising of the Intention of Enlightenment.’ You should also
                        remember it as ‘The Question of Maitreya.’” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>When the Blessed One had spoken, the venerable Ānanda and the bodhisattva
                        Maitreya, together with the five hundred monks <ref cRef="F.116.b"/>, and
                        the entire retinue, as well as the worlds of gods and men, demi-gods and
                        gandharvas, rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>This concludes the “Chapter of the Question of Maitreya,” the forty-first
                        chapter of the Noble Dharma Discourse, <title xml:lang="eng">The Great Heap
                            of Jewels</title>, in one hundred thousand chapters. </p>
                    <p>This text was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholars
                        Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi, together with the chief editor and translator
                        Yeshé Dé. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa
                            chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryamaitreyaparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>), Toh 85, Degé Kangyur,
                        vol. 44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 104b–116b. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa
                            chen po’i mdo, bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)</title> [Comparative Edition of
                        the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe
                        sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
                        Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009, vol. 44, pp. 289–316. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa khri
                            brgyad stong pa</title> (Aṣṭādaśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā) [Perfection of
                        Wisdom in 18,000 verses], D 11, Degé Kangyur, vol. 29 p. 1 – vol. 31 p. 414. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa’i gsang ba bsam gyis mi khyab pa
                            bstan pa</title> (<title xml:lang="So-Ltn">Tathāgatacintyaguhyanirdeśa</title>), Toh 47, Degé Kangyur vol. 39,
                        folios 100a–203a. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya mchog ldan. byams pas btab pa’i smon lam gyi
                            rnam par bshad pa byams pa’i chos la ’jug pa’i sgo</title>. In gsung
                        bum, vol. 8 (nya), pp 407-430. New Delhi: Ngawang Topgyel, (1995). (TBRC
                        W23200). </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’brug pa pad+ma dkar po. ’phags pa byams pa’i smon
                            lam gyi ’grel pa thogs med kyi dgongs pa gsal bar bstan pa</title>. In
                        gsung ’bum, vol. 7 (ja), pp. 349-376. Darjeeling: Kargyud Sungrab Nyamso
                        Khang (1973-1974). (TBRC W10736). </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Tāranātha. byams smon gyi ’grel pa.</title> In
                        gsung ’bum (blockprints from rtag brtan phun tshogs gling), vol. 13, pp
                        257-299. Leh, Ladakh: Namgyal &amp; Tsewang Taru (1982-87). (TBRC W22277). </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grags pa bshad sgrub. byams pa’i smon lam gyi rnam
                            par bzhad pa dga’ ldan du bgrod pa’i lam bzang, in co ne grags pa bshad
                            sgrub kyi gsung ’bum.</title> Beijing: Mes po’i shul bzhag series, krung
                        go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House, 2009).
                        (TBRC W1PD90129). </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngul chu d+harma b+hadra. byams pa’i smon lam gyi
                            ’grel pa’i zin bris.</title> In gsung ’bum, vol. 1. pp 495 et seq.
                        Ngulchu Chödzong: dngul chu bla brang, 2000? (TBRC W6493). </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngag dbang mkhas grub. byams pa’i smon lam gyi
                            tshig don rnam bshad.</title> In gsung ’bum, vol. 2, pp 315-360. Leh,
                        Ladakh: S.W. Tashigangpa (1972-1974). (TBRC W16912). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Matsumura, Hisashi. <title xml:lang="eng">“Marginalia to the Sanskrit
                            Fragments of Some Buddhist Texts,”</title> in Central Asiatic Journal,
                        vol. 37, no. 1/2 (1993), pp. 120-149. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 1993. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Python, Pierre. <title xml:lang="fr">Vinaya-viniścaya-upāli-paripṛcchā :
                            Enquête d’Upāli pour une exégèse de la discipline.</title> Paris:
                        Adrien-Maisonneuve, 1973. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gunaratana, Henepola. <title xml:lang="eng">The Jhānas in Theravāda
                            Buddhist Meditation</title>. Kandy, Śri Lanka: Buddhist Publication
                        Society, 1988. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te1">four great oceans</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya mtsho chen po bzhi </term>
                            <term type="definition">Four oceans believed to surround the central
                                mountain, Mt. Meru, in Indian cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te2">sphere of nothingness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ci yang med pa’i skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akiñcanyāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Third of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te3">emptiness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūnyatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditative concentration which realizes the
                                non-self of persons and phenomena; the first of the three doors of
                                liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te4">sphere of neither perception nor
                                non-perception</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du shes med ’du shes med min skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">naivasaṃjñānāsaṃjñāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Fourth of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te5">sphere of the infinity of
                                space</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ mtha yas skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ākāśānantyāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">First of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te6">sphere of the infinity of
                                consciousness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam shes mtha’ yas skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñānānantyāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Second of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te7">Eightfold Noble Path</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags lam yan lag brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryaṣṭāṇgamārga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te8">Seven Limbs of Enlightenment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub yan lag bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sapta bodhyaṃgāni</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te9">wishlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">praṇihita</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditative concentration which views nirvāṇa,
                                which is the complete pacification of the aggregates; the third of
                                the Three Doors of Liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te10">signlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan ma med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">animitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditative concentration which views the five
                                aggregates, the basis for the conception of a self, as faulty; the
                                second of the three doors of liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te11">Calm Abiding</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śamatha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditation technique to calm the mind.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te12">perfection of wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The sixth of the six perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te13">meditative absorption</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Four levels of meditation within the Form
                                Realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te14">sal tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing sA la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">A hardwood tree, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="la">Shorea robusta</foreign>, widespread on the Indian
                                subcontinent.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-te15">nyagrodha tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing nya gro dha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nyagrodha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tree, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="la">Ficus
                                    benghalensis</foreign>, native to the Indian subcontinent, that
                                can cover large areas by putting down aerial roots that become
                                subsidiary trunks.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe1">Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The cousin and close attendant monk of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe2">Giver of All Wealth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor thams cad phyin pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe3">Puṣpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Puṣpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe4">Candraprabhā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraprabhā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe5">Kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kau di nya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe6">Aśvajit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rta thul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aśvajit</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe7">Vaṣpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rlangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaṣpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe8">Mahānaman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ming chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahānaman</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe9">Bhadrika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrika</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe10">Vimala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri ma med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe11">Pūrṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe12">Gavāṃpati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ba lang bdag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gavāṃpati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe13">Mṛgaśiras</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri dags mgo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mṛgaśiras</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe14">Uruvilva Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lteng rgyas ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Uruvilva Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe15">Nadī Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu klung ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nadī Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe16">Gayā Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ga ya ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gayā Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe17">Jaṅghā-Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byin pa ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jaṅghā-Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe18">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe19">Amogharāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">don yod rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amogharāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe20">Sumati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe21">Śariputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śariputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe22">Maudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maudgalyāyana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe23">Parvatarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rgyal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Parvatarāja</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe24">Nanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nanda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe25">Upananda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upananda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe26">Rāhula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan zin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhula</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe27">Vardhamānamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros ’phel </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vardhamānamati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe28">Sumati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe29">Sthiramati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros brtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sthiramati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe30">Viśālamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros yangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viśālamati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe31">Pratibhānakūṭa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spobs pa brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratibhānakūṭa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe32">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe33">Mahāsthāmaprāpta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu chen thob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsthāmaprāpta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe34">Kusumaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kusumaśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe35">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe36">Abhijñāpuṣpasuparipūrṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par shes pa’i me tog shin tu rgyas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhijñāpuṣpasuparipūrṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe37">Anupalambhamanasikāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa med pa yid la byed pa? </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anupalambhamanasikāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe38">Prasādavat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dad ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasādavat</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe39">Ratnaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnaketu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe40">Indradeva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po’i lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indradeva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe41">Varuṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Varuṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe42">Mṛdusvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra dbyangs snyan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mṛdusvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe43">Kṣetraviśodhana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhing rnam par sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṣetraviśodhana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe44">Merukūṭa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhun po brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Merukūṭa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe45">Pratibhānasaṃpad</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spobs pa phun sum tshogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratibhānasaṃpad</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe46">Indraśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indraśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe47">Nimiṃdhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nimiṃdhara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe48">Scourer of the Hell-dwellers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can dmyal ba skems </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe49">Abandoner of Unfavorable
                                Rebirths</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan song spong </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe50">Ratnakesarin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ze ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakesarin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe51">Jyotivikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snang bas rnam par rol pa’i mngon par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jyotivikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pe52">Bhadraśuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang dag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadraśuddha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pl1">Country of the Bhargas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul bha rga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bharga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pl2">Mount Śuśumāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu srin byis pa gsod lta bu’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śuśumāragiri</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-044-005-pl3">Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhrakūtaparvata</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>