<!--Reviewed and finalized by John, placed in TEI folder 6 Jun 2016-->
<!--from the tei (production) folder 2016_08_15 -->
<?xml-model href="oxygen:/Exist$84000-AWS/db/84000/schema/84000-ODD.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Sūtra on Impermanence</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anityatāsūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="eng"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <author role="translatorMain">Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group
                    (International Buddhist Academy Division)<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng">Christian Bernert</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-072-009"/>
                <date>2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <ref>Toh 309</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol 72 (mdo sde, sa), folios 155a-155b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Zhang Yeshé Dé</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- Contents
            Summary
            Acknowledgments
            Introduction
            The Translation
            The Sūtra on Impermanence
            Notes
            Bibliography-->
    <!--            IS THIS NOTE STILL VALID DUE TO ITS LINK?  <note place="end">See, for example,
                            <title xml:lang="eng">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara</title> (Toh 155),
                        http://read.84000.co/#!ReadingRoom/UT22084-058-002/0. </note>-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>In this brief sūtra, the Buddha reminds his followers of one of the principal
                    characteristics of saṃsāric existence: the reality of impermanence. The four
                    things cherished most in this world, the Buddha says—namely good health, youth,
                    prosperity, and life—are all impermanent. He closes his teaching with a verse,
                    asking how beings, afflicted as they are by impermanence, can take delight in
                    anything desirable, and indirectly urging his disciples to practice the path of
                    liberation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>Translation by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist
                    Academy Division, Kathmandu). This sūtra was translated from the Tibetan into
                    English by Christian Bernert and edited by Vivian Paganuzzi.</p>
                <p>This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p> This sūtra highlights one of the most fundamental teachings of the
                        Buddha—recognizing the impermanence (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anityatā</foreign>) of conditioned phenomena. The fact that such
                        phenomena are impermanent (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya</foreign>) is listed as the first of the three principal
                        characteristics of existence, the other two being the suffering, or
                        unsatisfactoriness, of phenomena (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</foreign>), and their no-self, or lack of an inherent substance
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</foreign>). It is the
                        clear understanding of the reality of these facts of life that can bring
                        about a profound and essential change in a person’s worldview, marking the
                        point of entry to the path to liberation.<note place="end">See <title xml:lang="eng">The Three Basic Facts of Existence</title> (The
                            Wheel, Publication no. 186, 187) (details in bibliography).</note>
                        Impermanence is also one of the four seals of the Buddha’s teaching
                        (comprising these three characteristics of existence and a fourth principle,
                        that nirvāṇa is peace), often described as summarizing or epitomizing the
                        Buddhadharma, and more particularly as the criteria that together enable the
                        variety of Buddhist philosophical views to be distinguished from
                        non-Buddhist ones.<note place="end">See, for example, <title xml:lang="eng">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara</title> (Toh 155). </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Sūtras on impermanence</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Tibetan canon contains two sūtras with the title <title xml:lang="eng">Sūtra on Impermanence </title>(<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid
                            kyi mdo</title>), both found in the same section of the Kangyur (mdo
                        sde, Toh. 309 and 310). The sūtra translated here is the first, the shorter
                        of the two. Sūtras with equivalent titles are also found in other Buddhist
                        canons, but their contents differ substantially from the one translated
                        here. The Chinese Tripiṭaka, for instance, contains two sūtras so entitled
                        (Taishō Nos. 801 and 759), and in the Samyutta Nikāya of the Pāli canon, the
                        collection of discourses grouped by themes, there are a number of different
                        texts with the title <title xml:lang="eng">Sutta on Impermanence</title> (P.
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aniccasutta</title>).<note place="end">For
                                instance Samyutta Nikaya 22.45 and 46, and Samyutta Nikaya 36.9.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Note on the translation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The content of this sūtra is rather straightforward and its interpretation
                        does not pose any major difficulties. One particular term, however, did
                        present a problem of translation: the Tibetan <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dben pa</foreign>, which commonly translates the
                        Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viveka / vivikta
                        </foreign>and is usually related to concepts of isolation and seclusion.
                        Here it seems to refer more specifically to the act of picking something
                        out, separating it from other things and thus singling it out from them as
                        special.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleMain">The Sūtra on Impermanence</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all buddhas and
                        bodhisattvas!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling in Anāthapiṇḍada’s
                        park, in the Jeta Grove in Śrāvastī, along with a large monastic assembly.
                        The Bhagavān addressed the monks as follows:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, four things are appealing, singled out, considered valuable,
                            pleasant, and highly appreciated by everyone. What are those four? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, good health is appealing, singled out, considered valuable,
                            pleasant, and highly appreciated by everyone. Good health, however, ends
                            with sickness. Monks, sickness is neither appealing, nor is it singled
                            out, considered valuable, pleasant, or highly appreciated by anyone.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, youth is appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant,
                            and highly appreciated by everyone. Youth, however, ends with the aging
                            of the body. Monks, the aging of the body is neither appealing, nor is
                            it singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, or highly appreciated by
                            anyone.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, prosperity is appealing, singled out, considered valuable,
                            pleasant, and highly appreciated by everyone. Prosperity, however, ends
                            with its decline. Monks, the decline of prosperity is neither appealing,
                            nor is it singled out, nor considered valuable, pleasant, or highly
                            appreciated by anyone. <ref cRef="F.155.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Monks, life is appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant,
                            and highly appreciated by everyone. Life, however, ends in death. Monks,
                            death is neither appealing, nor is it singled out, considered valuable,
                            pleasant, or highly appreciated by anyone.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <p>Thus spoke the Bhagavān, the Sugata, and having spoken the Teacher added
                        these words:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <lg>
                        <l>“Good health is impermanent, </l>
                        <l>Youth does not last. </l>
                        <l>Prosperity is impermanent, </l>
                        <l>And life, too, does not last. </l>
                        <l>How can beings, afflicted as they are by impermanence,</l>
                        <l>Take delight in desirable things like these?”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>When the Bhagavān had thus spoken, the monks rejoiced and praised his words.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        This completes <title xml:lang="eng">The Sūtra on Impermanence</title>.
                    </p>
                    <p>Translated and edited by the Indian scholar Surendrabodhi and the principal
                        editor-translator, the monk Zhang Yeshé Dé. It was then also reviewed and
                        finalized in accordance with current language reforms.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anityatāsūtra</title>). Toh 309, Degé Kangyur vol. 72
                        (mdo sde, sa), folios 155a.2–155b.4. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anityatāsūtra</title>). bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
                        [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste
                        gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau
                        of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i
                        bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol.
                        72, 434-436.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nyanaponika Thera (transl.).<title xml:lang="eng"> Anicca Sutta:
                            Impermanent</title> (SN 36.9), translated from the Pali. <title xml:lang="eng">Access to Insight</title>, 30 June 2010,
                        http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/sn/sn36/sn36.009.nypo.html .
                        Retrieved on 10 May 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“The Three Basic Facts of Existence: I. Impermanence (Anicca), with a
                        preface by Nyanaponika Thera,” <title xml:lang="eng">Access to
                            Insight</title>, 2 December 2011,
                        http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/various/wheel186.html . Retrieved
                        on 10 May 2013.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te1">three principal characteristics of
                                existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkar btags gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">(Pāli tilakkhaṇa)</term>
                            <term type="definition">Impermanence, suffering, and no-self. They are
                                called the “three characteristics” in Pāli, a term that has no
                                direct equivalent in the Sanskrit or Tibetan literature; in Tibetan,
                                these three factors are usually called the “three seals of the
                                Buddha's teaching” in parallel to the “four seals of the Buddha’s
                                teaching,” q.v.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te2">impermanent</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te3">impermanence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anityatā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te4">suffering</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdug bsngal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="eng">unsatisfactoriness</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te5">no-self</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="eng">lack of an inherent
                                substance</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te6">four seals of the Buddha’s teaching</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ rtags kyi phyag rgya bzhi__,__bkar btags bzhi__,__chos kyi sdom bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturdharmoddāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">All conditioned phenomena are impermanent; all
                                defilements are suffering; all phenomena are without self; nirvāṇa
                                is peace.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-072-009-te7">singled out</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dben pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viveka, vivikta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>