<?xml-model href="../../../schema/84000-ODD.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><!-- Under review for parser status 6/5/16, first pass,-->
<!-- copied from staging 2016_08_15-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་སྐྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པ་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Teaching on the Extraordinary
                    Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the Buddha’s Powers</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhabalādhānaprātihāryavikurvāṇanirdeśa</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་སྐྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i
                    cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul pa bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Noble Sūtra of the Great Vehicle “The
                    Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining
                    the Buddha’s Powers”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryabuddhabalādhānaprātihāryavikurvāṇanirdeśanāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain">Translated by the Buddhavacana Translation Group
                    (Vienna) under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of
                    the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng">Gregory Forgues</author>
                <author role="translatorEng">Rolf Scheuermann</author>
                <!--author role="translatorEng">Khenpo Ngawang Wöser</author-->
                <author role="editorEng">Casey Kemp</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-061-006"/>
                <date>2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <ref>Toh 186</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios 143b–158a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib"/>
                    <author role="translatorTib"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>In this sūtra, the Buddha displays supernatural powers three times. First, he
                    magically transports his entire audience and retinue to Vārāṇasī. Secondly,
                    having incited Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi to use their own miraculous powers
                    to gather there all the beings who must be led to awakening, he makes the whole
                    world appear as a pure realm like Sukhāvatī. He explains that a tathāgata’s
                    various powers are like a doctor’s skills, and teaches, with Mañjuśrī’s help in
                    a series of dialogues with other protagonists, on how the tathāgatas manifest to
                    beings, displaying his supernatural powers a third time by making many other
                    buddhas appear all around him. The meaning of the Tathāgata’s miracles are
                    gradually disclosed to the audience, as well as some other essential points
                    including the merit to be gained by honoring the teachings. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>Translated by the Buddhavacana Translation Group. The translation was made by by
                    Gregory Forgues in collaboration with Rolf Scheuermann and the generous
                    assistance of Khenpo Ngawang Wöser. English text edited by Casey Kemp. Special
                    thanks to Professor Tom Tillemans for his comments and advice.</p>
                <p>This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Setting</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The sūtra is set at first on the banks of the Nairañjanā River, where the
                        Buddha is dwelling together with a retinue of bodhisattvas including
                        Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi, Maitreya, and Mañjuśrī, as well as great hearers
                        like Subhūti, Śāripūtra, and Maudgalyayāna. After Śakra and Brahmā pay their
                        respects, the Tathāgata magically transports himself together with his
                        entire assembly to a grove in Vārāṇasī, where he manifests his supernatural
                        powers.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Story </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Buddha, upon entering into the state of state of concentration known as
                            <distinct><!--type="concentration"-->the garlands of the buddhas
                        </distinct>, asks Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi to summon miraculously all
                        degenerate beings of the Sahā world system who must be led to awakening.
                        Entering into the same state of concentration, Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi
                        manifest light rays and inspirational verses to invite those beings to the
                        mango grove. Once they arrive, the Tathāgata displays his supernatural
                        powers by exerting his sovereign power over the whole world, turning it into
                        a place similar to the pure realm of Sukhāvatī. With Mañjuśrī’s help, he
                        teaches on how the tathāgatas manifest to beings in a series of dialogues
                        with other protagonists. He explains that a tathāgata is like a doctor who
                        knows the various diseases of beings and the methods to cure them. The
                        Buddha finally displays his supernatural powers a third time by making many
                        other buddhas appear all around him. The sūtra ends with a condensed summary
                        of Buddhadharma.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">The Main Points of the Subject Matter</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>From a doctrinal perspective, the sūtra explores important Mahāyāna topics in
                        relation with the notion of miracles (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihārya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cho
                            ’phrul</foreign>), supernatural powers (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhi</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul</foreign>), and extraordinary
                        transformation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvaṇa</foreign>,
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par ’phrul</foreign>):
                            <emph>The necessity for miracles</emph>. At the beginning of the text,
                        it is stated that sentient beings who could fall into negative forms of
                        existence should be converted to the path in order to lead them to
                        unsurpassable awakening. This can only occur, though, through the display of
                        miracles. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <emph>The description of miracles</emph>. In this sūtra, the miracles of the
                        Buddha are presented in three different ways: as magical transformations, as
                        the ability to know another’s mind, and as the capacity to destroy
                        defilements by expounding the Dharma. First the Buddha performs supernatural
                        actions that transform the immediate physical surroundings. Then he explains
                        that beings should be helped according to their dispositions, inclinations,
                        and capacities. Since the Tathāgata is able to know beings’ minds through
                        his supernatural powers, he is able to assist them through various skillful
                        means (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign>) corresponding to their
                        circumstances. Vasubandhu explains this sequence in great detail in the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title>: the Buddha first
                        ravishes the minds of beings he wishes to set on the path through the
                        display of his extraordinary powers. Knowing their dispositions,
                        inclinations, and capacities, he then imparts methods that will ultimately
                        lead them to the unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening. The use of such
                        miracles by the Buddha as skillful means is a recurring theme of Mahāyāna
                        sūtras, as can be seen, for example, in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra</title> (Lamotte 2003: 233) where there is a
                        passage that mirrors the storyline of the present sūtra.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <emph>The “magical show” as an analogy for the nature of reality</emph>. The
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhabalādhānaprātihāryavikurvāṇanirdeśa</title> makes the important
                        point that conditioned phenomena are like a “show” or an illusion, as
                        clearly explained by Mañjuśrī to the gods. Just like a reflection in a
                        mirror, the Tathāgata neither comes nor goes. Things neither arise nor
                        cease. Yet the Tathāgata appears in the world for the sake of beings. For
                        him, however, there is no birth, no old age, and no death. The sūtra
                        explains that since all conditioned phenomena are like illusions, the
                        extraordinary activities of a tathāgata, such as teaching and leading beings
                        to awakening, are not limited by time and space. His teaching remains even
                        if he manifested the extinction of suffering eons ago. As an object of
                        veneration, he is a means to reach awakening by accumulating merit. His
                        purpose and meaning are not constrained by notions of his being present or
                        absent. The same idea occurs in a sūtra found in the Ratnakūṭa, <title xml:lang="eng">The Prophecy for the Magician Bhadra</title> (Toh. 65),
                        in which the Tathāgata displays similar miracles (Chang 1983: 4–13) and in
                        which it is stated that the Buddha can perform magic because he knows that
                        all phenomena are illusory. Action (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karma</foreign>) is explained as being the great conjurer that
                        magically creates beings and material objects. Thus, the basis of the
                        Tathāgata’s supernatural powers is considered to be his realization that all
                        phenomena are like magic and illusions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <emph>The nature of the cycle of rebirths (saṃsāra) and karma</emph>. In the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhabalādhānaprātihāryavikurvāṇanirdeśa</title>, the Buddha explains
                        that there is no birth, old age, and death. However, one’s state of life is
                        dependent on the perception conditioned by the body, since beings are
                        fixated on the physical basis of their existence. These perceptions trigger
                        actions. On the basis of these actions, beings will experience suffering
                        again and again throughout all their future rebirths. This endless cycle of
                        arisings and cessations is what is called <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra</foreign>. The scales of a balance are used as
                        a metaphor in the text to illustrate this process, and it is worth noting
                        that this simile is also found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmasamuccaya</title> in the same context (Rahula 2001: 94). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <emph>Skillful means and practices</emph>. The sūtra puts forward various
                        methods for venerating the tathāgatas—making offerings, chanting their
                        names, supporting the Dharma, propagating the teachings, and making the
                        Dharma available in any possible way. Of all these methods, those concerning
                        the protection of the Dharma are deemed supreme. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Source Text and Various Versions</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The source text is extant in Tibetan, Chinese, and (partially) Sanskrit. The
                        Tibetan text is found in the various editions of the Kangyur with no major
                        variations. A glimpse of what might have been the source text for the
                        Tibetan translation of the sūtra is afforded by some Sanskrit fragments in
                        the collection of Gilgit manuscripts. The Gilgit manuscripts are among the
                        oldest manuscripts in the world, dating back to the 5th and 6th centuries
                        A.D., and include famous works from the Buddhist canon such as the <title xml:lang="eng"> Sūtra</title>. The language of these manuscripts is a
                        form of Sanskrit with Prakrit vocabulary and inflections. The Gilgit
                        fragments of this sūtra, although far from representing the whole text, show
                        no major variations from their Tibetan counterparts. It is, however, not
                        possible at this stage to establish whether this specific Sanskrit version
                        of the text was the basis for the Tibetan translations. </p>
                    <p>There is unfortunately no colophon to this sūtra, and therefore no direct
                        mention by name of the Indian and Tibetan translators. We were unable to
                        find any reference to this sūtra elsewhere in the Tibetan canon. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Regarding the relationship between this sūtra and others, it is worth noting
                        that the text belongs to a corpus of sūtras containing passages in which
                        miracles play a significant role: one Vinaya text, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title> (Toh 6); two
                        Prajñāpāramitāsūtras, the <title xml:lang="eng">Prajñāpāramitā in 25,000
                            lines</title> (Toh 9) and <title xml:lang="eng">Prajñāpāramitā in 10,000
                            lines</title> (Toh 11); the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title> (Toh 44); six sūtras from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatācintyaguhyanirdeśa</title> (Toh 47), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvapiṭaka</title> (Toh 56), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadramāyākāravyākaraṇa</title> (Toh 65), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāpratihāryanirdeśa</title> (Toh 66), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyamahāsiṃhanāda</title> (Toh 67), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Acintyabuddhaviśayanirdeśa</title> (Toh 79); and twenty-eight sūtras
                        from the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title> (Toh 94), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṃghāṭisūtradharmaparyāya</title> (Toh 102), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇāpuṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 112), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmapuṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarvadharmaguṇavyūharāja</title> (Toh 114), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakaraṇḍa</title> (Toh 117), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samādhirāja</title> (Toh 127), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Praśāntaviniścayaprātihāryasamādhi</title> (Toh 129),
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgamasamādhi</title> (Toh 132), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Caturdārakasamādhi</title> (Toh 136), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsamnipātaratnaketudhāraṇī</title> (Toh 138),
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatamahākaruṇānirdeśa</title> (Toh 147),
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgaramatiparipṛcchā</title> (Toh 152), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anavataptanāgarājaparipṛcchā</title> (Toh 156), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Drumakiṃnararājaparipṛcchā</title> (Toh 157), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vikurvāṇarājaparipṛcchā</title> (Toh 167), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāyānopadeśa</title> (Toh 169), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākṣayamatinirdeśa</title> (Toh 175), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalakīrtinirdeśa</title> (Toh 176), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhabalavardhanaprātihāryavikurvāṇanirdeśa</title>
                        (this text, Toh 186), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahābherīhārakaparivarta</title> (Toh 222), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśatparivarta</title> (Toh 223), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhasaṅgīti</title> (Toh 228), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmegha</title> (Toh 232), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramārthadharmavijaya</title> (Toh 246), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmasmṛtyupasthāna</title> (Toh 287), <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdzangs blun</title> (Toh 341), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumāgadhāvadāna</title> (Toh 346). </p>
                    <p>In addition, the pure realm of Sukhāvatī is mentioned in the text, as are
                        some names of tathāgatas and of a specific samādhi also found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title>. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Translation Issues and Academic Research</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>To the best of our knowledge, no complete English translation of this sūtra
                        was available prior to the one published here. Schopen, however, edited some
                        Sanskrit fragments of the sūtra, compared them to the Tibetan text, and
                        provided an English translation on the basis of the Sanskrit and Tibetan
                        versions. </p>
                    <p>The many compounds found in the text remain, unsurprisingly, one of the main
                        issues for translators. Some Tibetan expressions in which terms appear in a
                        different order are apparently used for the same Sanskrit compound, for
                        instance, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bsod nams las skyes pa’i
                            dge ba’i rtsa ba</foreign> (145b.2) instead of <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i rtsa ba las skyes pa’i bsod nams</foreign>
                        (150b.7). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Another good illustration of the difficulty of translating compounds is the
                        title of the sūtra itself, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhabalādhānaprātihāryavikurvāṇa</title>, which Schopen does not
                        translate in his study of the Sanskrit text. Although the Sanskrit term
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balādhāna</foreign> is translated
                        in the Mahāvyutpatti as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs skyed
                            pa</foreign>, different transliterations are found in the various
                        Kangyur editions. For example, the Degé Kangyur reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balavadhana</foreign>, the Stog Palace
                        reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balādhana</foreign>, the
                        Narthang reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">baladhana</foreign>,
                        and so forth. The Pedurma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe sdur ma</title>,
                        comparative edition, see bibliography) settles for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balavardhana</foreign>. In the present
                        case, we chose to follow Schopen, who opts for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balādhāna</foreign> (1978: 319). Edgerton, in his <title xml:lang="eng">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary</title>,
                        offers a detailed explanation of this term, which he understands as “the
                        attainment of (usually some particular) power,” such as the powers of a
                        tathāgata (1953: 398a). As for the rest of the compound, we have translated
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign> as “miracle”
                        and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvāṇa</foreign> as
                        “extraordinary transformation.” In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra</title> (Lamotte 2003: 233), <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihāryabala</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vikurvāṇabala</foreign> are often used as
                        synonyms. Lamotte reads them as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmadhāraya</foreign> compounds (in the way of adjective+noun)
                        respectively meaning “wondrous powers” and “prodigious powers.” Burnouf, on
                        his part, understands <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṛddhiprātihārya</foreign> as “supernatural transformation” (2010: 189).
                        La Vallée Poussin translates <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign> as “magical powers” in v. VII.47–48 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title> (and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="longTitle">bhāṣya</title>).<note place="end">The English
                            translations of these terms are found in the English translations of
                            Lamotte’s, Burnouf’s, and La Vallée Poussin’s respective works. </note>
                        In this context, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign>
                        is used by a buddha to convert beings through the manifestation of
                        miraculous powers, the ability to know others’ minds, and the capacity to
                        teach, all of which correspond very much to the subject matter of our sūtra.
                        In this context, the third <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign> is deemed to be superior since it cannot be
                        attained by means of magic formulae (La Vallée Poussin 1988–90: 1166–68 and
                        1209–1210). For these reasons, we have not read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihāryavikurvāṇa</foreign> as a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvandva</foreign> in this context, as we
                        were originally tempted to do. It is probably a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmadhāraya</foreign> (noun+noun) and possibly a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tatpuruṣa</foreign>. In the Tibetan
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul
                            pa</foreign>, the two terms stand in apposition, indicating rather a
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmadhāraya</foreign>. The
                        complete title of the sūtra can therefore be translated as “The Teaching on
                        the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the
                        Buddha’s Powers,” and indeed the message of the sūtra is that the ultimate
                        miracle is to attain the state of buddhahood. Supernatural powers are only a
                        means to lead beings to awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Another translation issue concerns the mention in the sūtra of a grove
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shing a mra srung ba’i tshal /
                            a mra srung ba mo’i tshal</foreign>) located in Vāraṇasī. Although there
                        is no extant Sanskrit fragment for this passage, Schopen translated the
                        phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">a mra srung ba mo’i
                            tshal</foreign> from the Tibetan as “the grove of Āmrapālī” (see Schopen
                        1978: 323 fragment [1288]), taking it as a reference to the grove offered to
                        the Buddha by the courtesan Āmrapāli in which several events and teachings
                        recorded in the canonical texts took place. This translation is problematic
                        here, however, because Āmrapālī’s grove was located in Vaiśālī and not
                        Vāraṇasī. There are several reasons for thinking that these phrases do not
                        refer to Āmrapālī’s grove. In the narratives of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya</title> texts—the only instances in the Kangyur in which
                        Āmrapālī is a protagonist in her own right as opposed to mentions of her
                        grove—her name is rendered in Tibetan as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra skyong ma</foreign>, while the phrase a <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mra srung ba</foreign>, which is often
                        taken as an alternative rendering, is in fact only used in the sūtra section
                        of the Kangyur, and only within the phrase a <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign>, i.e. referring to a grove.
                        There are, it is true, several sūtras explicitly located in Vaiśālī in which
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign>
                        can be reasonably taken as referring to Āmrapālī’s grove. In this text,
                        however, we are faced not only with the anomalous location, but also with
                        the variant phrases <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shing a mra srung
                            ba’i tshal</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra
                            srung ba mo’i tshal</foreign>, both of which occur only here and nowhere
                        else in the entire Kangyur. A literal translation of the syntactic
                        construction in this text, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shing a
                            mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign> (F.143.b) would be “grove of the
                        caretaker of mango trees,” and our understanding is that the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba (āmrapāla /
                            āmrapālī)</foreign> is simply a generic name with this meaning, not a
                        proper noun. In a word, the translation of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign> as “Āmrapālī’s grove” is
                        technically wrong, although it is semantically correct when the grove is
                        located in Vaiśālī. Other possible hypotheses to explain the anomaly would
                        be that at some point in the transmission of the text a geographical or
                        nominal inaccuracy has been introduced; or else that the translocation of
                        Āmrapālī’s grove to Vāraṇasī is intended to be understood as part of the
                        Buddha’s miraculous display. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon">The Noble Sūtra of the Great Vehicle</head>
                <head type="titleMain">The Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the
                    Miracle of Attaining the Buddha’s Powers</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <ref cRef="F.143.b"/>
                        <!--modularPassage type=openingHomage-->Homage to the Omniscient One
                        One!<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <p><!--modularPassage type=thusSetting Retinue-->Thus did I hear at one time.
                        The Blessed One was dwelling on the banks of the great Nairañjanā River,
                        together with seven thousand bodhisattvas.<!--/modularPassage--> Among them
                        were the Noble Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi, Maitreya, and Mañjuśrī, and all
                        the great śrāvakas like Subhūti, Śāripūtra, and Maudgalyayāna. He was
                        circumambulated by Śakra, Brahmā, and all the protectors of the world, as
                        well as all the kings, ministers, brahmins, and householders, and was <ref cRef="F.144.a"/> placed in front of the assembly. After being presented
                        with offerings of almsfood, he pleased his surrounding retinue with a
                        teaching on Dharma, and encouraged, uplifted, and complimented them. By
                        means of his great supernatural power, the Tathāgata and his surrounding
                        retinue were then transported to the city of Vārāṇasī, where they stayed in
                        the grove of the caretaker of mango trees.<note place="end">The Tibetan
                            reads here <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shing a mra srung
                                ba’i tshal</foreign>. This issue is discussed in detail at the end
                            of the Introduction. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>At that time the earth trembled greatly, and a vast lion throne made from the
                        seven kinds of precious substances appeared. Covering about ten miles in
                        height and five miles in breadth, it was well adorned,<note place="end">Pedurma, Lhasa, Narthang, Stog Palace, and Urga: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">legs par spras pa</foreign>. Degé:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">legs par smras
                            pa</foreign>.</note> delightful, and pleasing to the mind. It was tied
                        with hanging silk tassels, clothed with thousands of divine garments,
                        covered with myriad garlands of divine flowers, endowed with a divine
                        fragrance, and colorful. The lion throne had arisen from the Tathāgata’s
                        previously developed roots of virtue. As soon as they saw it, all beings
                        would immediately reach the stage of accepting that phenomena are not
                        produced. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p> Then, the Blessed One sat down on this lion throne, settled into the state
                        of concentration known as <distinct>the garlands of buddhas</distinct>, and
                        addressed the bodhisattvas Noble Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi as follows. </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>the Blessed One</speaker>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Avalokiteśvara, go forth. Together with Vajrapāṇi, use your great
                            supernatural powers and state of concentration to assemble around me the
                            beings of this Sahā world system and of the other world systems of the
                            ten directions whom you should tame and who are degenerate, have no
                            faith, practice negative deeds, are obscured because of various types of
                            affliction, have no consideration for their mothers or fathers, do not
                            respect ascetics or brahmins for what they are, and have no faith in the
                            Three Jewels.” </p>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <p>“Avalokiteśvara, go forth. Together with Vajrapāṇi, use your great
                            supernatural powers and state of concentration to assemble around me the
                            beings of this Sahā world system and of the other world systems of the
                            ten directions whom you should tame and who are degenerate, have no
                            faith, practice negative deeds, are obscured because of various types of
                            affliction, have no consideration for their mothers or fathers, do not
                            respect ascetics or brahmins for what they are, and have no faith in the
                            Three Jewels.”</p>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <ref cRef="F.144.b"/> On hearing these words from the Tathāgata, the
                        bodhisattvas Noble Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi settled into the state of
                        concentration known as <distinct>watching over and exhorting all
                            beings</distinct>. Through the power of their state of concentration,
                        this great earth was tremendously shaken in six ways.<note place="end">“This
                            great earth teetered, tottered, and tremored in six different ways: it
                            quivered, quavered, and quaked; it shifted, shuddered, and shook. The
                            west rose up and the east sank down. [The east rose up and the west sank
                            down.] The south rose up and the north sank down. The north rose up and
                            the south sank down. The middle rose up and the ends sank down. The ends
                            rose up and the middle sank down.” (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prātihāryasūtra</title>, translated in Rotman 2008: 174).</note>
                        Thousands of light rays shone forth from the bodies of Avalokiteśvara and
                        Vajrapāṇi, and as they shone they completely illuminated the world systems
                        of the great trichiliocosm. They illuminated everything from the world of
                        Brahmā on down—that is, the worlds endowed with form and pervaded by form.
                        From these light rays also came these verses of exhortation: </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Thousands of light rays</speaker>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Be attentive and without afflictions.</l>
                            <l>Do not fall under the power of distraction!</l>
                            <l>While everywhere is the suffering of birth, old age, and death,</l>
                            <l>Rare is the appearance of the teaching of the Sugata.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Those of unwholesome livelihood have no fear,</l>
                            <l>Even though they are bound to circle </l>
                            <l>In saṃsāra’s ocean for countless eons,</l>
                            <l>Always ensnared by afflictions.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Gain, desires, and women are impermanent.</l>
                            <l>They always possess the nature of an illusory song and dance.</l>
                            <l>Even if one experiences eons of bliss,</l>
                            <l>One will eventually undergo suffering.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Behold how tricky things are!</l>
                            <l>One’s mother in this life may be one’s wife in another,</l>
                            <l>And in yet another life fools may eat her flesh,</l>
                            <l>And in their ignorance enjoy it.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“No doubt, human beings take birth in the ocean of saṃsāra’s
                                suffering,</l>
                            <l>Yet they are not afraid. </l>
                            <l>You who desire to honor the Sugata for having explained the noble
                                Dharma to human beings,</l>
                            <l>Go forth!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Once you have understood the one who can guide the untamed,</l>
                            <l>You will attain the state of concentration, the cultivation of peace. </l>
                            <l>Thus, all you human beings in the ocean of saṃsāra,</l>
                            <l>Be afraid and long for liberation! <ref cRef="F.145.a"/>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l> “All you humans, honor this noble one! <note place="end">Stog
                                    Palace: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rnams ky
                                        ni</foreign>. Degé: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rnams kyis ni</foreign>.</note>
                            </l>
                            <l>Do not take the lives of others,</l>
                            <l>And likewise do not take others’ possessions that have not been
                                offered.</l>
                            <l>Do not violate other people’s wives.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Always pay homage to the Buddhadharma!</l>
                            <l>Give up pride, arrogance, and harsh speech,</l>
                            <l> And then set out for the grove of the caretaker of mango trees</l>
                            <l>In the city called Vārāṇasī!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Upon arriving, behold the supreme person.</l>
                            <l>Vast and pleasing is his array:</l>
                            <l>The saṅgha of monks who always have supernatural powers,</l>
                            <l>And the bodhisattvas who possess even greater ones.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“He is named Avalokiteśvara</l>
                            <l>Who continuously sends forth light rays</l>
                            <l>So that the ignorant know</l>
                            <l>And the myriad beings are liberated.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Those who are proud, arrogant, and haughty</l>
                            <l>And those who do not venerate the Buddhadharma,</l>
                            <l>The protector, the supreme Vajrapāṇi, never ceases to illuminate
                                them</l>
                            <l>And leads them to understanding.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Their bodies are vast with great supernatural powers.</l>
                            <l>Eons and eons would not suffice to describe them.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“There, in the grove of the caretaker of mango trees,</l>
                            <l>Bring perfume, garlands, fine clothes, and ornaments to honor the
                                Sugata.</l>
                            <l>Venerate this guide of humankind,</l>
                            <l>For rare is a buddha.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Beings have suffered for myriads of eons</l>
                            <l>And will forever do so due to desire.</l>
                            <l>May the wise always long for liberation</l>
                            <l>And venerate the supreme person, the Buddha!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Sons, daughters, relatives,</l>
                            <l>Parents, wives, friends— </l>
                            <l>All are illusory and pointless;</l>
                            <l>They will always be reborn in different ways.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“So, too, gold and silver are like flashes of lightning.</l>
                            <l>None show any essence.</l>
                            <l>To reach the state of awakening,</l>
                            <l>Venerate the guide of humankind."</l>
                        </lg>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>As these inspirational verses arose one after another from the light rays,
                            <ref cRef="F.145.b"/> they filled the world systems of the great
                        trichiliocosm with sound, inspiring all beings. Those who formerly had wrong
                        views were converted to right views. Those who were afflicted with pride,
                        vanity, arrogance, and pretense were freed from pride, vanity, and
                        arrogance. Those who indulged in lust without restraint were freed from
                        lust. All those who engaged in killing, stealing, sexual misconduct on
                        account of desire, or the eight unwholesome factors were set on the noble
                        eightfold path in all their actions, words, and thoughts. Each and every one
                        of them completely abandoned excitement, joking, pleasure, amusement,
                        desire, anger, envy, and attachment. They felt determined to contemplate,
                        follow, and serve the Tathāgata. They all wished to hear the Dharma. All the
                        gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, mahoragas,
                        humans, non-humans, kings of the nāgas, royal lords of the citadels,
                        vassals, universal monarchs, monks, nuns, and male and female lay vow holder
                        carried divine flowers, garlands, salves, aromatic powders, garments,
                        umbrellas, royal banners, cymbals, and bundles of silk scarves in order to
                        venerate the Tathāgata. Once they reached the place where he resided, the
                        grove of the caretaker of mango trees in the great city of Vārāṇasī, they
                        worshipped him and his surrounding retinue with the roots of virtue that
                        arose from their own merit. A rain of flowers, a great fragrant rain, fell. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then, <ref cRef="F.146.a"/> at that moment, the Blessed One exerted his
                        sovereign power on<note place="end">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byin gyi rlabs te</foreign>
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhyatiṣṭha</foreign>, see
                            Schopen 1978: 322 fragment [1288]). We have translated <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byin gyi rlabs</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhāna</foreign>) in this text as
                            ‘sovereign power.’ Conze used the expression ‘sustaining power.’ The
                            term is often translated as ‘blessings.’ However, as explained in Eckel
                            1994: 90–93, Gómez 2011: 539, 541, and Fiordalis 2012: 104, 118,
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhāna</foreign> conveys
                            the notions of control (of one’s environment as a result of meditative
                            absorption), authority, or protection (see <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title> VII.51, cf. Poussin 1925: 119ff). As can be
                            seen in the present text, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhāna</foreign> is also used to convey the idea of
                            transformation through exerting one’s control over objects, people, and
                            places. It seems to us that ‘sovereign power’ covers all these shades of
                            meaning as well as the various usages of the Sanskrit term. For example,
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satyādhiṣṭhāna</foreign> ‘the
                            sovereign power of truth,’ <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhānādhisthita</foreign> ‘empowered by the sovereign power (of
                            the Tathāgata)’—which in tantric initiation may also refer to being
                            empowered as a sovereign. </note> Jambudvīpa and the grove of the
                        caretaker of mango trees so that it extended over several trillions of
                        yojanas. The ground became as smooth as the palm of a hand, divinely
                        pleasing to the mind, colorful, and fragrant. It was ornamented with
                        heavenly flower trees, fruit trees, fragrant trees, jewel trees,
                        wish-fulfilling trees, and trees bearing garments. It supported heavenly
                        lion thrones with hanging garlands of jewels, cloth, and flowers, and was
                        suffused with the sound of divine bells. Thus, just like the world system
                        known as Sukhāvatī, it was ravishing, fulfilling, pleasing, and delightful.
                        It was blessed, being filled by everyone, from bodhisattvas, śrāvakas,
                        pratyekabuddhas, gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras,
                        and mahoragas, to monks, nuns, male and female lay vow holders, kings,
                        ministers, brahmins, and kings, ministers, brahmins, and householders.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then, the bodhisattvas Noble Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi emerged from their
                        state of concentration and went to where the Blessed One was staying. They
                        approached, circumambulated him three times, and said to him, “O Blessed
                        One, the Tathāgata’s skillful means and methods that bring beings to
                        spiritual maturity are many. O Sugata, they are many indeed. O Blessed One,
                        the bodhisattva mahāsattvas, the great śrāvakas, gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                        gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, <ref cRef="F.146.b"/> kinnaras, mahoragas,
                        kings, ministers, brahmins, householders, monks, nuns, and male and female
                        lay vow holders have gathered here in great numbers through the strength of
                        the Tathāgata’s majesty and supernatural powers.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied, “O sons of a good family, this is excellent, most
                        excellent. O sons of the Victorious One, it is indeed so. Many are the
                        Tathāgata’s skillful means and methods that bring beings to spiritual
                        maturity. He teaches the Dharma knowing their intentions, the way to convert
                        them, and their roots of virtue, as well as their behavior according to
                        their various dispositions. Some beings are to be converted by bodhisattvas.
                        Some are to be converted by śrāvakas. Some are to be converted by
                        pratyekabuddhas. Some are to be converted by gods. Some are to be converted
                        by Śakra. Some are to be converted by Brahmā. Some are to be converted by
                        nāgas. Some are to be converted by great supernatural powers. Some are to be
                        converted by kings. Some are to be converted by states of concentration.
                        Some are to be converted by listening to the Dharma. Some are to be
                        converted by miracles. Some are to be converted by the Tathāgata’s complete
                        nirvāṇa. Some are to be converted by relics. Some to be converted strive for
                        the roots of virtue that arise from commissioning stūpas, monasteries,
                        promenades, and groves. Some to be converted strive for the roots of virtue
                        that arise from commissioning statues, images, and representations of gold,
                        silver, and brass. Some to be converted strive<note place="end">In the
                            following sentences, we have chosen to follow the Sanskrit construction.
                            We have thus translated <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">kecid...kuśalamūlotsukā vaineyāḥ</foreign> as “some to be converted
                            strive for the roots of virtue...” instead of the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kha cig...dge ba’i rtsa ba la spro ba
                                bskyed pas ’dul</foreign>, literally, “some are to be converted
                            through striving for the roots of virtue...”</note> for the roots of
                        virtue that arise from worshipping and venerating the Saṅgha of monks. Some
                        to be converted strive for the roots of virtue that arise from copying
                            sūtras,<note place="end">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dri ba</foreign> in the sense of
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yi ger ’dri ba</foreign>. See
                            Schopen 2005: 32ff.</note> having sūtras copied, or reciting sūtras.
                        Some to be converted strive for the roots of virtue that arise from offering
                        lamps, incense, flowers, perfume, garlands, salves, jewel necklaces, and so
                        forth. <ref cRef="F.147.a"/> They do not partake of a Dharma versed in the
                        ultimate nor of a Dharma concerned with nirvāṇa. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O sons of the Victorious One, there is indeed nothing whatsoever that the
                        tathāgatas do not know, see, hear, or fully comprehend. They know what has
                        happened. They know the future. They know the past. They know the present.
                        They know the activities of all beings. They know their conduct. They know
                        their dispositions. They know their birth. They know their existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O sons of the Victorious One, it is as follows. Consider the analogy of a
                        well-trained doctor who is very skilled in the the eight branches of
                        Āyurveda and expert in all conditions, having extensively studied the use of
                        medicinal substances and instruments, knows the condition of the sick beings
                        whose bodies are tormented by various ailments. He knows the phases and the
                        degrees. He knows the cure. He knows the diseases related to the airs, bile,
                        phlegm, or a combination of the three, those related to blood, indigestion,
                        tumors, edema, heart disease, leprosy, skin eruption, abscesses, and boils,
                        as well as poisoning, inflammation, and so on. Possessing knowledge of all
                        these things, he cures the diseases of all beings and liberates them from
                        the fear of diverse ailments through various medicinal substances,
                        vomitives, purgatives, powders, sternutatory treatments, bleeding, ghee,
                        boiled oil, and tonics.<note place="end">The Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">smin par bya ba</foreign>, which
                            literally means “that which raises, that which ripens.” The Sanskrit
                            equivalent is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bālacūrṇa</foreign>
                            (see Schopen 1978: 326 §1291). However, an alternative and possibly
                            better reading would be the Āyurvedic tonic called <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balācūrṇa</foreign>, a powder made
                            with herbs such as <foreign xml:lang="lat" type="term">sida
                                cordifolia</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“In the same way, O noble sons of the Victorious One, the Tathāgata possesses
                        eight branches of Āyurveda: the various states of concentration, the bases
                        of supernatural powers, the powers, the assurance s, and divine sight and
                            hearing.<note place="end">See glossary for lists of these qualities.
                            Divine sight and hearing are qualities that are part of the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhijñās</foreign> (“superior
                            knowledge”).</note>
                        <ref cRef="F.147.b"/> He is well versed in the various conditions of beings,
                        their intentions, and their conduct. Thus he seeks to free from taking
                        rebirth in hell or as animals, hungry ghosts, or in the world of Yama all
                        those beings who are tormented by the diseases of desire, hatred, and
                        bewilderment and by the sicknesses of the fundamental and secondary
                        defilements, as well as those obscured by pride, vanity, and arrogance or by
                        attachment, suffering, fear, and anger. To this end, by using various
                        skillful means, various practices, various states of concentration, and
                        supernatural powers, he brings beings to all stages of liberation up to and
                        including their unsurpassable, perfect awakening, and thus leads them to the
                        extinction of their suffering in the sphere of remainderless <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">parinirvāṇa</foreign>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“He liberates them from the eight unwholesome factors and sets each of them
                        on the eightfold noble path. O sons of a noble family, it is as follows. The
                        disc of the moon skillfully manifests as hidden, or as a half-disc, or
                        waning, or waxing, or as a full disc for beings—the latter are to be
                        converted according to the roots of virtue making up their conditions. It
                        dispels all obscurity and darkness, and refreshes all the grass, forests,
                        medicinal herbs, and crops. Likewise, O sons of the Victorious One, the
                        Tathāgata understands beings who are obscured by various kinds of suffering,
                        as well as the conduct of beings who are to be converted in keeping with
                        their various conditions. He manifests as being in the state of parinirvāṇa,
                        as being born, as a universal monarch, and also as someone joyful who is
                        entertained by amusements and pleasures such as women’s laughter, play,
                        perfume, and garlands. <ref cRef="F.148.a"/> He also manifests as someone
                        who renounces the household life, goes forth to live as a renunciant, and
                        practices asceticism, and eventually as someone who, having tamed Māra and
                        turned the wheel of Dharma, pleases beings by bringing down the rain of the
                        great cloud of Dharma. The tathāgatas have attained parinirvāṇa. Yet, they
                        liberate all beings through various practices such as zealously venerating
                        relics, having stūpas, monasteries, and images constructed, giving up the
                        household life for the sake of going forth as a renunciant, and venerating
                        the Saṅgha of monks, as well as copying, reading, and reciting the noble
                        Dharma. They also liberate beings through skillful means such as maintaining
                        the training, the way of life, the monastic vows, fasting,<note place="end">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsnyan gnas</foreign> (Tib.) or
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upavāsa</foreign> (Skt.) is the fast day
                            during the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Poṣadha</foreign>
                            (Pāli <foreign xml:lang="pli" type="term">uposatha</foreign>), which
                            includes the recitation of the Prātimokṣasūtra, the confession of
                            faults, and the restoration of vows (e.g., the eight vows for lay
                            followers). </note> and the lay pledges. They liberate these beings from
                        rebirths as hell beings, animals, and beings born in Yama’s world, and from
                        existences deprived of the eight freedoms, as well as from negative rebirths
                        and negative forms of existence, and so forth, including comforting these
                        beings by having them listen to the Dharma and bringing them to
                        unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>At that point, some dim-witted gods thought, “The tathāgatas of earlier
                        times, who were arhats and fully awakened buddhas, accomplished the deeds of
                        a tathāgata. That is to say, after extending their own lifespan through
                        their blessings, they liberated all beings from birth, old age, sickness,
                        death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and trouble. Likewise,
                        this tathāgata, although he has not as yet accomplished all the deeds of a
                        tathāgata, is also extolling and teaching nirvāṇa. And he is displaying <ref cRef="F.148.b"/> supernatural powers and miracles of extraordinary
                        transformations after having assembled a great retinue. So does this
                        tathāgata also seek parinirvāṇa right away?” With this thought, they were
                        depressed and fell silent.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The youthful Mañjuśrī then clairvoyantly understood what those gods were
                        thinking and said to them, “O gods, do not think like that, do not say such
                        things. Do not be depressed. Many are the skillful means of the tathāgatas.
                        They teach the Dharma to beings of diverse inclinations by means of their
                        sovereign power, the power of their roots of virtue, which consists of
                        various methods, insights, and states of concentration. O gods, since I have
                        seen the supernatural powers and miracles of extraordinary transformations
                        that are the skillful means of the tathāgatas of the past, I know. So surely
                        the Tathāgata will indeed wish to expound and spread the king of sūtras of
                        the great vehicle called <title xml:lang="eng">The Teaching on the
                            Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the
                            Buddha’s Powers</title>. Moreover, O gods, the tathāgatas do not enter
                        parinirvāṇa because there is no parinirvāṇa of the tathāgatas, nor are their
                        lives ever exhausted. The tathāgatas remain for immeasurable millions of
                        eons, for utterly inexpressible eons. But by their skillful means they
                        display their parinirvāṇa to beings as well as the disappearance of the
                        noble Dharma. Just as the Tathāgata sees the various beings of an impure
                        nature who are to be converted by means of parinirvāṇa or by relics, who
                        have no faith in the Tathāgata, and who are irreverent toward the master, so
                        in each such case the Tathāgata displays his parinirvāṇa. But in fact, the
                        Tathāgata neither comes nor goes. When the roots of virtue of beings have
                        fully matured, <ref cRef="F.149.a"/> and they long to look upon the
                        Tathāgata, are worthy of veneration, and long to listen to the Dharma just
                        as they long for the disc of the moon, at that time, the Tathāgata appears
                        in the world for the benefit and happiness of many beings such as gods and
                        humans, and for the sake of manifesting and propagating the Three Jewels to
                            them.<note place="end">Translated on the basis of the Tibetan. The
                            Sanskrit is based on a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yāvad</foreign> construction: “The Tathāgata appears in the world,
                            for the benefit of many beings, for the happiness of many beings and so
                            on, up to manifesting and propagating the Three Jewels to men and
                            gods.”</note> But in fact, the Tathāgata is not born, nor does he age or
                        die. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O sons of a noble family, it is as follows. As an analogy, although many
                        forms might appear and disappear in a well-polished mirror, one does not see
                        that the reflected image actually comes into the mirror or leaves it.<note place="end">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzugs
                                nyan</foreign> / Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratibimba</foreign>. The images appearing in the mirror are
                            nothing but reflections. </note> O gods, you should also look upon the
                        body of the Tathāgata in this way. </p>
                    <p>“O sons of a noble family, it is as follows. As an analogy, a well-trained
                        conjurer displays various cities, archways, parks, vehicles, physical forms
                        of a universal monarch, amusements, and entertainments. Even if he makes
                        these illusions cease, they do not move anywhere, nor do they come or go.
                        You should regard the appearance of the tathāgatas and their parinirvāṇa in
                        the same way. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Moreover, O gods, the tathāgatas—because of their former vows, although a
                        thousand years, an eon, or ten million eons may have elapsed since their
                        parinirvāṇa, and on account of the fact that sentient beings worship them,
                        venerate them, construct relic stūpas, create images, recite their names,
                        and preserve and venerate the holy Dharma—liberate beings from all the
                        hells, animal births, the world of Yama, downfalls into inopportune
                        existences, unfortunate destinies, bad rebirths, and all suffering, even
                        though these tathāgatas might belong to different world systems, <ref cRef="F.149.b"/> until beings gradually attain the unsurpassable, truly
                        perfect enlightenment.<note place="end">This passage was translated from the
                            Sanskrit fragments. As Schopen points out, the Tibetan cannot be
                            followed here since the syntax of the sentence is problematic: “by
                            introducing <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems can</foreign>
                            here as the logical subject of the sentence, [the Tibetan] has
                            completely changed the meaning of the passage” (1978: 333). The Degé
                            edition of the text reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">/yang
                                lha’i bu dag sngon gyi smon lam gyis de bzhin gshegs pa mya ngan las
                                ’das nas lo stod lon pa’am/ mya ngan las ’das nas bskal par lon
                                pa’am/ mya ngan las ’das nas bskal pa bye bar lon yang sems can
                                rnams kyis mchod par bya ba dang / bkur stir bya ba dang / ring
                                bsrel gyi mchod rten byed du gzhug pa dang / sku gzugs byed du gzhug
                                pa dang / mtshan nas brjod pa dang / dam pa’i chos ’dzin pa dang /
                                mchod pa byed pa’i sems can ’jig rten gyi khams sna tshogs na gnas
                                pa rnams thar par mdzad de sems can dmyal ba dang / dud ’gro'i skye
                                gnas dang / gshin rje’i ’jig rten dang / mi khom pa dang / ngan song
                                dang / ngan ’gro log par ltung ba thams cad dang / sdug <ref cRef="F.149.b"/> bsngal thams cad las yongs su thar par mdzad
                                nas rim gyis bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa’i byang chub kyi
                                bar du mngon par rdzogs par ’tshang rgya bar ’gyur na/</foreign>
                            Unfortunately, the other Tibetan editions we consulted are not helpful
                            here. Schopen suggests reading the long Sanskrit compound °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saddharmedharaṇapūjanā</foreign>
                            (1978: 332 §1296) as a dative: °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūjanān nānā-</foreign>. This emendation is justified by the fact
                            that the loss of a final dental followed by the same consonant is
                            frequent in the Gilgit manuscripts (1978: 336, n9). We have chosen to
                            follow Schopen’s suggestion. However, it should be added that another
                            problem is involved with Schopen’s reading: the verb <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mokṣayanti</foreign> has no object in
                            the emended Sanskrit sentence. Schopen therefore also has to add the
                            logical object satvān to the sentence on top of his emendation of the
                            compound °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saddharmedharaṇapūjanā</foreign>. An alternative reading based on
                            the principle of lectio difficilior would be to accept Schopen’s
                            emendation °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saddharmedharaṇapūjanān</foreign> but to read it as a bahuvrīhi
                            (accusative plural) instead of a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tatpuruṣa</foreign> (dative singular). The preceding <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satvānām</foreign> could be read in
                            this case as a partitive genitive: “those who have veneration, etc.
                            (i.e., °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūjanān</foreign> =
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bahuvrīhi</foreign> acc.
                            plu.) among sentient beings (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satvānām</foreign> = partitive genitive ).” The complete sentence
                            would read: “Moreover, O gods, although a thousand years, an eon, or ten
                            million eons may have elapsed since the tathāgatas attained parinirvāṇa,
                            on account of their former vows, they liberate from all the hells,
                            animal births, the world of Yama, downfalls into inopportune existences,
                            unfortunate destinies, and bad rebirths those who among beings worship
                            them, venerate them, construct relic stūpas, create images, recite their
                            names, and preserve and venerate the holy Dharma...”</note> Thus, what
                        need is there to mention those who worship the tathāgatas in person by
                        offering them flowers, incense, perfume, garlands, salves, clothes, and
                        aromatic powders? O gods, even though one thousand years, an eon, or even
                        ten million eons may have elapsed since the Bhagavān Buddha entered
                        parinirvāṇa, if some beings throw a flower in the sky, after calling the
                        Tathāgata by his name seven times and saying ‘Homage to the Buddha,’ they
                        will all bring an end to their suffering. But, let alone throwing a flower
                        in the sky, if someone, whoever they might be, faithfully emulating the
                        Tathāgata, strives to maintain even a single precept in order to honor the
                        Tathāgata, or strives to focus on worshipping the Tathāgata even for a
                        single day, or a single night, or a single moment, this person will put an
                        end to suffering and gradually, fully, and completely awaken to
                        unsurpassable, truly perfect enlightenment. If even those who, in order to
                        honor the Tathāgata, laugh, have fun, joke like fools, play games, or make a
                        stūpa from sand, will all put an end to suffering and fully and completely
                        awaken to unsurpassable, truly perfect enlightenment, what need is there to
                        mention those who have built relic stūpas or relic images and, understanding
                        that compassion toward all beings is the most important thing, think ‘I
                        shall liberate all beings from suffering’? And what need is there to mention
                        those who, having produced the thought directed toward unsurpassable, truly
                        perfect awakening, <ref cRef="F.150.a"/> make offerings of divine flowers
                        and incense, garlands, salves, aromatic powders, cymbals, umbrellas, and
                        royal banners? Those who have thus made offerings to all the tathāgatas will
                        be free from birth, old age, sickness, and death, as well as from misery,
                        lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and afflictions. And as long as they
                        have not completely and fully awakened to unsurpassable, truly perfect
                        awakening, they will be reborn in pleasant forms of existence. O gods, thus
                        can one discern the aspiration of the tathāgatas of the past and is in
                        perfect agreement with it.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Then, those gods thought, “Oh, this youthful Mañjuśrī is endowed with great
                        insight. If the tathāgatas possess supreme skillful means, what does it mean
                        when Mañjuśrī says that the tathāgatas remain in the world systems and bring
                        beings to spiritual maturity through various skillful means, even though ten
                        billion eons have passed many times over since the tathāgatas attained
                        nirvāṇa?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The youthful Mañjuśrī, having clairvoyantly understood what those gods were
                        thinking, said, “O gods, excellent! Excellent! Just wait a moment. These
                        thoughts arising in your mind, as well as your earlier question, are also
                        the sovereign power of the Tathāgata.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>At this, the Blessed One displayed his supernatural powers and the tathāgatas
                        Śikhin (Crown Ornament Holder), Viśvabhū (Protector of All), Krakucchanda
                        (Destroyer of Saṃsāra), Kanakumūni (Golden Sage), Vipāśyin (Discerning One),
                        Akṣobhya (Unmovable One), and Amitābha (Infinite Light) appeared in his
                        surrounding retinue, sitting on lion thrones surrounded by the saṅgha of
                        śrāvakas and <ref cRef="F.150.b"/> bodhisattvas, and taught the Dharma to an
                        ocean-like retinue. They too displayed those same types of supernatural
                        powers by manifesting many tathāgatas sitting on their lion thrones,
                        expounding the Dharma throughout the world systems of the east, south, west,
                        and north. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The retinue of all those gathered and the gods rejoiced, jubilated, and were
                        pleased. Having themselves increased the power of the roots of virtue
                        arising from their merit, they worshipped the tathāgatas with flowers,
                        incense, perfume, garlands, salves, garments, and ornaments, and
                        circumambulated them three times, proclaiming the following verses:</p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>The retinue of all those gathered and the gods</speaker>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“How wonderful is this gnosis!</l>
                            <l>For this, one should practice the state of concentration and
                                insight!</l>
                            <l>Just like lights illuminating the world, </l>
                            <l>This great Hero will remain</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“For the benefit of beings</l>
                            <l>For many eons after his nirvāṇa.</l>
                            <l>Surrounded by bodhisattvas,</l>
                            <l>He is seated on a lion throne.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Seeing the Buddha is excellent.</l>
                            <l>Listening to the Dharma is excellent.</l>
                            <l>Likewise, observing a spiritual friend</l>
                            <l>And listening to him is also excellent.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“All the precepts of the body</l>
                            <l>That preserve the training are excellent.</l>
                            <l>Those who have diligently perfected them</l>
                            <l>Will all achieve awakening.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Those who are skillful in means and insight</l>
                            <l>Will liberate beings in this world.</l>
                            <l>Like the disc of the moon,</l>
                            <l>Like a conjurer,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“The Tathāgata shows himself</l>
                            <l>To come and go.</l>
                            <l>Because they have stūpas,</l>
                            <l>Drawings, and images made</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“And they honor and worship him,</l>
                            <l>Those who remember his name</l>
                            <l>And live for the sake of awakening</l>
                            <l>Will all attain liberation.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Since they pay homage to the Tathāgata, <ref cRef="F.151.a"/>
                            </l>
                            <l>Listen to the noble Dharma,</l>
                            <l>And worship and retain it accordingly,</l>
                            <l>They will be free from all suffering.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>As the Tathāgata imparted this instruction on the sovereign power and the
                        miracle of the extraordinary transformation of a tathāgata, sixty-four
                        thousand beings reached the stage where they accepted that phenomena are not
                            produced.<note place="end">See Sasaki 1986: “[<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anutpattikadharmakṣānti</foreign>] represents the fact
                            that emptiness or the absolute experience is beyond the thinkable, and
                            therefore in the failure of the intellect, designation is impossible.
                            One can only refer to being unborn (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anutpattika</foreign>) in the absolute sense. The
                            inclination or willingness to make this absolute statement is called
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>... Buddhist
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>, however, is
                            a willing acceptance of the unborn” (138–139).</note> Twenty thousand
                        beings completely purified the eye of Dharma that sees all phenomena. Five
                        thousand gods remained without grasping, their minds freed from defilements.
                        They were led to the stage of a non-returner. Seven hundred monks, nuns, and
                        male and female lay vow holders attained various states of
                        concentration.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>King Prasenajit said to the youthful Mañjuśrī, “O son of the Victorious One,
                        as for your answers to the questions asked for the benefit of all beings,
                        what you said was excellent, it was excellent indeed. Yet, I still have a
                        few doubts. Therefore, please expound upon and answer my questions about
                        beings applying their minds to what they have heard and thus becoming free
                        from the suffering of saṃsāra, passing into fortunate forms of existence,
                        and never falling back from the unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Mañjuśrī replied, “O great king, it is excellent that you have developed your
                        previous roots of merit and that your confidence has increased through the
                        sovereign power of the Tathāgata. Whatever you wish to know, ask and I shall
                        explain it to you.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The king said, “O son of the Victorious One, just by hearing the names of the
                        tathāgatas and honoring and serving them, beings who perform negative
                        actions will be liberated from rebirths as hell beings and animals, as well
                        as from Yama’s world, and will pass into pleasant forms of existence. Who
                        are they? In which world system do they abide? How should we honor
                        them?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Mañjuśrī <ref cRef="F.151.b"/> replied, “O son of a noble family, listen, I
                        shall elucidate the reason why these beings will not pass into negative
                        forms of existence. I shall state the names of the blessed ones, the
                        tathāgatas, who will liberate them from rebirths in negative forms of
                        existence, from rebirths as hell beings and animals, and from Yama’s world,
                        and I shall state how they are to be worshipped and venerated in their
                        respective world systems. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“In the world system called Vaiḍūrya Light abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat,
                        the truly perfect Buddha called Bhaiṣajyaguru Vaidūryaprabharāja (Teacher of
                        Medicine, King<note place="end">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyal po</foreign> is missing in
                            the text.</note> of Vaiḍūrya Light), who watches over beings as well as
                        teaches the Dharma. In the world system called Śikhin (Crown Ornament
                        Holder) abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called
                        Śikhin (Crown Ornament Holder). In the world system called Vimalā (
                        Stainless) abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called
                        Stainless Arising. In the world system called Peace abides the Tathāgata,
                        the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called Established in Peace. In the
                        world system called Sukhāvatī (Endowed with Happiness) abides the Tathāgata,
                        the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called Amitābha (Infinite Light). In the
                        world system called Excellence abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly
                        perfect Buddha called Born. In the world system called Vajra abides the
                        Tathāgata called Indestructible Vajra. In the world system called Aśoka
                        (Without Suffering) abides the Tathāgata called Vigataśoka (Free from
                        Suffering). In the world system called Fearless abides the Tathāgata called
                        Pacifier of All Fears. In the world system called Endowed with Realization
                        and Intelligence abides the Tathāgata called Purifier of All Rebirths. In
                        the world system called Free from Negative Forms of Existence abides the
                        Tathāgata called <ref cRef="F.152.a"/> Pacifier of All Negative Forms of
                        Existence. In the world system called Vimalā (Stainless) abides the
                        Tathāgata called He Whose Intelligence Has Been Completely Purified. In the
                        world system called Possessed of Power abides the Tathāgata called Powerful
                        Intelligence. By calling them by their names, one will become the lord of
                        the gods. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“In the world system called Moon abides the Tathāgata called Stainless Full
                        Moon. By calling him by his name and worshipping him, one will be completely
                        liberated from all defilements. In the world system called Excellent
                        Attainment abides the Tathāgata called Pacifier of All Negative Forms of
                        Existence. By calling him by his name and worshipping him, one will be
                        liberated from negative forms of existence. In the world system called
                        Perfect Light abides the Tathāgata called he Who Looks at All Beings with
                        Love. By calling him by his name and worshipping him, all worldly beings
                        will be completely delighted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O son of a noble family, in a word, even if a sextillion years or a hundred
                        eons have passed since the tathāgatas Ānandaśrī, Candanaśrī, Hero,
                        Subjugator of All Demon Forces, Śikhin, Viśvabhū, Krakucchanda, Kanakumūni,
                        and Kāśyapa have manifested nirvāṇa, O great king, all beings will be
                        liberated from negative rebirths and negative forms of existence by calling
                        the names of these buddhas; by having relic stūpas, drawings, and
                        representations made; by worshipping and honoring them with lamps, incense,
                        flowers, and perfume; and by maintaining the training, way of life,
                        austerities, discipline, <ref cRef="F.152.b"/> and fasting. </p>
                    <p>“Karmic obscurations that remain for eons, such as those stemming from the
                        five actions with immediate results,<note place="end">The five actions with
                            immediate results are: killing one’s mother, killing one’s father,
                            killing an arhat, intentionally wounding a buddha, and creating a schism
                            in the Saṅgha.</note> will be purified. One will pass to pleasant forms
                        of existence and not to negative ones, and one will gradually, fully, and
                        completely awaken to the unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Suppose that sons or daughters of noble family with a feeble recollection of
                        faith and bodhicitta commissions drawings or clay statues of those
                        tathāgatas. Suppose they do so to liberate friends and relatives, and for
                        the sake of beings who engage in negative actions, abandon the noble Dharma,
                        denigrate the noble ones, commit the five actions with immediate results,
                        take a life, steal the wealth of the Three Jewels, go to the Avīci hell, or
                        take birth in the three negative forms of existence. And suppose that once
                        they have commissioned the drawings or statues, they focus principally on
                        generating compassion toward all these beings and adopts the noble eightfold
                        path. And then suppose they worship the tathāgatas three times in the night
                        and three times in the day with flowers, incense, perfume, garlands, salves,
                        lamps, cymbals, royal banners, and flags from the eighth day of the waxing
                        moon until the fifteenth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Now, in order to liberate beings, the buddhas, the blessed ones know with
                        their tathāgatas’ gnosis, hear with their divine ear, and see with their
                        divine eye; so when sons or daughters of noble family dedicates their merit
                        so that such beings will pass to pleasant forms of existence and accomplish
                        wholesome deeds instead of negative ones, <ref cRef="F.153.a"/> in order to
                        liberate the beings born in negative forms of existence, they should
                        supplicate the tathāgatas. They should dedicate merit in this way: ‘May
                        negative actions be attenuated through confessing and acknowledging faults!
                        May the names of the tathāgatas be heard! May beings be liberated from all
                        negative forms of existence! Until fully and perfectly awakened to the
                        unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening, may one’s conduct be in
                        accordance with that of Mañjuśrī himself!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Moreover, if one copies the different teachings of the Dharma or commissions
                        this activity, keeps them in mind, recites them, and worships them, then due
                        to the power of the aspiration of the past tathāgatas, the names of the
                        buddhas will reach the ears of the beings born in Avīci hell and in the
                        three negative forms of existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“In addition, through the power of these different methods of the Dharma, all
                        negative actions will be attenuated. Through the power of the tathāgatas’
                        majesty and their various Dharma Dharma discourses, one will be aware of
                        wholesome and unwholesome actions. Thus one will subsequently not commit
                        negative actions. One will then be liberated from the various kinds of
                        suffering and pass to pleasant rebirths. Until one reaches unsurpassable,
                        complete, and perfect awakening, the state of truly perfect awakening, one’s
                        actions will be conducive to it. </p>
                    <p>“Thus, these Dharma discourses are endowed with many positive properties.
                        They are like the great maṇi jewel. Just like the great maṇi jewel, the
                        wish-fulfilling jewel, they accomplish all wishes. All negative actions are
                        subjugated. All gates to the negative forms of existence are closed. All
                        gates to the pleasant forms of existence and the buddhas’ realms are opened. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“So, O son of a noble family, owing to the Tathāgatas’ various skillful
                        means, aspirations, extraordinary transformations, sovereign power, and
                        states of concentration, <ref cRef="F.153.b"/> one will pass to pleasant
                        forms of existence and be liberated from all negative ones by continuously
                        listening to and worshipping those who have remained in the various world
                        systems, even if a hundred eons have passed since the tathāgatas’ nirvāṇa.
                        Therefore, what need is there to mention the importance of keeping in mind
                        the Dharma, reading it, copying it or commissioning this action, or
                        accurately teaching it in a detailed way to others? Suppose a son or
                        daughter of a noble family comes to possess this excellent quality. Except
                        for the tathāgatas, no one could easily express the excellent quality of
                        that being’s accumulation of merit and of their roots of virtue. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O great king, you should thus rely on this excellent quality and keep in
                        mind the various Dharma discourses. You should read them. You should explain
                        them. You should worship them. You should make your faith in the Three
                        Jewels integral to you. You should always worship and venerate the
                        tathāgatas and correctly grasp their teachings. Being repulsed by saṃsāra,
                        you should be vigilant and focus your thoughts on its momentariness.
                        Moreover, O great king, by pursuing desires, one will remain in a state of
                        suffering for sextillions of eons. That is, one will experience the
                        suffering of arising and cessation, the suffering of being in the womb, the
                        suffering of rebirth as a hell being or an animal, or the suffering of the
                        world of Yama, the suffering of poverty, and the suffering of being cut,
                        bruised, beaten, struck, and burnt. Therefore, you should proceed to abandon
                        all conditioned phenomena. O great king, you should give priority to
                        compassion and long for the Dharma and liberation.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>King Prasenajit, together with his entire retinue, said to Mañjuśrī, “O
                        Mañjuśrī, this is excellent, most excellent! By bringing down the rain of
                        the Dharma, <ref cRef="F.154.a"/> you have made us content and happy. As we
                        have set out upon the state of awakening, you have made us vigilant.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>An eager bodhisattva then asked the Blessed One, “O Blessed One, suppose
                        someone adopts the various teachings of the Dharma, reads them, teaches them
                        in detail to others, copies them or commissions their copying, and honors
                        those who copy, adopt, and recite the teachings with flowers, incense,
                        perfume, garlands, salves, garments, and ornaments. How much would the merit
                        of this person increase, O Blessed One?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied, “If a son or a daughter of a noble family, a king, a
                        minister, a monk, a nun, a male lay vow holder, or a female lay vow holder
                        keeps in mind the various teachings of the Dharma with faith in the
                        Tathāgata, worships them, copies them or commissions their copying, and
                        teaches them correctly, he or she will attain the eight great qualities.
                        What are they? None of the diseases or harm in the world will affect him or
                        her at all. All yakṣas, bhūtas, and piśācas who rob people of their radiance
                        will abide in loving-kindness. No harmful influences from kṛtyās, kākhordas,
                        spell-casters, or vetālas will injure his or her body. Having pleased all
                        the kings, ministers, brahmins, householders, monks, nuns, and male and
                        female lay vow holders, he or she will accomplish all aims. All the gods
                        will congregate. He or she will pass to pleasant forms of existence. He or
                        she will be accepted by Vajrapāṇi. He or she will be born wherever he or she
                        might wish and will remember the succession of former lives. In this way a
                        son or daughter of noble family and others will <ref cRef="F.154.b"/> attain
                        the eight great qualities. Thus, for one hundred thousand years, he or she
                        will venerate these tathāgatas with the divine and manifest offerings meant
                        for a tathāgata. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Suppose someone were to fill Jambudvīpa with tathāgatas’ relic stūpas made
                        of the seven precious substances, and then venerate, revere, and worship
                        them for one hundred thousand years with divine garlands, salves, flowers,
                        lamps, precious umbrellas, cymbals, royal banners, and flags; compared to
                        such a person, someone who keeps in mind the various teachings of the Dharma
                        with faith in the Tathāgata and who reads them, worships them, copies them
                        or commissions their copying, and teaches them correctly to others will have
                        a vastly greater increase in merit. O son of a noble family, suppose someone
                        were to set the beings of Jambudvīpa on the noble eightfold path and, after
                        having done so, venerated and worshipped the Tathāgata for a hundred
                        thousand divine years with all the necessities of life there might be;
                        compared to such a person, someone who listens to just one four-line stanza
                        drawn from the various teachings of the Dharma, keeps it in mind, copies it
                        or commissions it to be copied, and promulgates it to others will have a
                        vastly greater increase in merit.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>When the Blessed One had explained in detail the significance of the various
                        teachings of the Dharma, he then spoke the following verses: </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>the Blessed One</speaker>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Abiding in one trillion other fields,</l>
                            <l>Ten million skillful buddhas</l>
                            <l>Care for beings</l>
                            <l>And liberate them from negative forms of existence.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“After you have performed actions of generosity</l>
                            <l>By engaging in ceaseless activity,</l>
                            <l>You should worship the tathāgatas by longing for the Dharma</l>
                            <l>In order to liberate those who have gone to negative forms of
                                existence.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Produce drawings, stūpas, and various representations,</l>
                            <l>Have statues made,</l>
                            <l>Some of gold or silver, some of metal or clay,</l>
                            <l>And worship them with various offerings. <ref cRef="F.155.a"/>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Worship the tathāgatas with flowers, garlands, salves,</l>
                            <l>Lamps, cymbals, perfume, and incense.</l>
                            <l>With superior insight, dedicate merit as well.</l>
                            <l>Explain the teachings of the sūtras, and abide by them.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“The majesty of the Tathāgata and of the collection of sūtras</l>
                            <l>Will liberate beings from negative actions.</l>
                            <l>They will take rebirth in pure abodes</l>
                            <l>Until they reach the unsurpassable awakening.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“They will remember their former actions, and having done so,</l>
                            <l>Those who understand will not commit negative actions again.</l>
                            <l>By expounding the bodhisattvas’ collection of sūtras for the sake of
                                    humans,<note place="end">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byang chub sems
                                        dpa’</foreign> (Stog Palace 347a.5) instead of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byang chub sems dpas</foreign>
                                    (Degé 155a.2).</note>
                            </l>
                            <l>They will obtain great merit.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“They will be protected by the gods.</l>
                            <l>In their bodies no disease will occur.</l>
                            <l>Nowhere in their kingdoms will there be strife,</l>
                            <l>And in their homes, villages, and cities there will be peace.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                        <lg>
                            <l>“Whoever holds at all times this collection of sutrās</l>
                            <l>Holds at all times the treasury of the buddhas.</l>
                            <l>Whoever worships and venerates it, has it copied, and makes it
                                heard,</l>
                            <l>He, without doing anything else,</l>
                            <l>Will perfectly worship the Buddha,</l>
                            <l>And will quickly attain supreme awakening.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The eager bodhisattva mahāsattva asked the Blessed One, “O Blessed One, I
                        have some qualms about this. Having come into possession of a kingdom with
                        this body, will one again experience suffering? Or will there not be any
                        sorrow when one circles in saṃsāra? Or alternatively, as one will experience
                        again birth, old age, sickness, death, misery, despair, lamentation,
                        suffering, and unhappiness, how will one be born, die, live, and gain
                        happiness? How will one experience suffering?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One answered the eager bodhisattva mahāsattva, “O you who are
                        eager, you should consider that these experiences are conditioned by karma.
                        Now, O son of a noble family, <ref cRef="F.155.b"/> there is no birth, no
                        death, no life in this world. O son of a noble family, although there is no
                        old age and death here, one’s state of life is always dependent on the body
                            consciousness.<note place="end">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tsho ba’i khams ni rtag tu lus
                                kyis par shes pa la gnas so</foreign> (Degé, 155b.1) does not make
                            sense. We followed the alternative reading found in most other editions:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tsho ba’i khams ni rtag tu
                                lus kyi rnam par shes pa la gnas so</foreign>.</note> Furthermore,
                        when one transmigrates to various births due to karmic conditions and karmic
                        circumstances, one will experience happiness and suffering. One has the
                        notion of happiness as happiness and suffering as suffering. One gives rise
                        to the notion that non-happiness is not happiness and that non-suffering is
                        not suffering. Nonetheless, until one possesses the qualities of nirvāṇa in
                        the realm of nirvāṇa without a remainder, one will still be subject to
                        sorrow. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O son of a noble family, it is as follows. As an analogy, consider someone
                        who puts on new clothes. Having put them on, this person performs all sorts
                        of actions and experiences happiness and suffering. Later, at another time,
                        this person is finally told that these clothes, being old and moth-eaten,
                        are dirty, upon which he realizes that they should be thrown away, and thus
                        he gets rid of them. Once he is rid of them, he again looks for brand new
                        clothes to wear. When he has put them on, he performs various actions and
                        experiences happiness and suffering. Until this person has put on genuine
                        clothes that are durable and everlasting, indestructible and unbreakable,
                        then though many eons pass, one after another, he will either have to wear
                        such temporary clothes or throw them away. He does not think about this nor
                        reflect upon it; he is under the influence of the body. Likewise, O son of a
                        noble family, at a certain time, due to one’s state of life, one’s body
                        perishes and is seen to be on the point of collapse. At that time, one
                        discards this body and looks for another that is new and young. Taking it on
                        and performing actions with it, one will experience happiness and suffering.
                        Just as clothes arisen from one’s own merit are soft, hard, or rough, so too
                        one adopts the body that one takes on according to one’s state of life. Just
                        as one is born according to one’s roots of virtue, namely, one’s karmic
                        conditions, one will be born as a god, a king, <ref cRef="F.156.a"/> a hell
                        being, an animal, or a being from the world of Yama. Although this body is
                        also influenced by one’s state of life and is given up according to one’s
                        state of life, one does not think about this, nor reflect upon it. O son of
                        a noble family, you should look upon the body just as you look upon these
                        clothes. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O son of a noble family, it is like a snake that, when the time has come on
                        account of karmic conditions, sheds its skin, and then comes and goes in
                        keeping with its physical shape. Although the snake will experience
                        happiness and suffering, it does not think about its skin nor reflect upon
                        it. You should look upon your state of life just as you look upon this
                        snake. </p>
                    <p>“O son of a noble family, it is like a tree that, after it has developed its
                        leaves and foliage, will then, with time, evolve so that finally they wither
                        and fall. And then yet later again, with time, it will grow buds, branches,
                        foliage, flowers, and fruit. O son of a noble family, it is in this way that
                        you should look upon arising and cessation due to karmic conditions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Now, O son of a noble family, some time in the future beings will experience
                        more greed, attachment, anger, envy, and pride. As they cause the scales and
                        weights of karma to move,<note place="end">This metaphor is probably used
                            here to explain the dynamics of cause and effect in relation to karma.
                            Asaṅga uses the same metaphor to explain rebirth (see <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmasamuccaya</title> II.1 trans. in Rahula
                            2001: 94), and it is found in similar contexts in the Tibetan
                            commentarial literature. </note> their behavior will follow upon
                        pleasure and attachment, so that they will commit more negative actions
                        based upon or caused by their attachment. Committing more negative actions,
                        they will experience suffering. They who construe impermanent things as
                        permanent and the impure as pure will not venerate the Buddha, the Dharma,
                        and the Saṅgha. These infantile people will not seek out a spiritual friend.
                        Instead, they will mock and ridicule those who teach them the Dharma, rather
                        than having faith or trust in them. Such beings will perform negative
                        actions. They will adopt the body that they take on and which they will
                        experience in keeping with karmic conditions and according to their
                        particular state of life. <ref cRef="F.156.b"/> They will then give rise to
                        notions of suffering and pleasure. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“O son of a noble family, this is the answer of the Tathāgata. This body
                        should be regarded as karmically conditioned. For this body also there is no
                        death, there is no life; happiness and suffering will not be experienced but
                        they will arise and cease according to karmic causes and conditions. The
                        tathāgatas have undergone sextillions of hardships for the sake of beings.
                        Having completely given up all their possessions, they become perfectly
                        awakened within unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening, and
                        establish all beings, too, in great nirvāṇa.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>At that point, the Tathāgata’s sovereign power caused the whole earth to
                        tremble. The assembled retinue said to the Tathāgata, “Excellent!” King
                        Prasenajit and the others, by means of many, great, more and more powerful
                        supernatural powers, made an offering to the Tathāgata of five hundred
                        divine garments. Trembling, they circumambulated the Tathāgata three times.
                        In the presence of all the tathāgatas, each of them confessed that the
                        faults consisting of all their negative actions had indeed been committed,
                        and they promised to adopt the training. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>At the same time, the assembled retinue spoke these words: </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>the assembled retinue</speaker>
                        <p>“O Tathāgata, we pay homage to those who have turned away from all
                            births, freed all beings from suffering, and attained liberation. Homage
                            to them! O Blessed One, in the future, we will not take any delight in
                            the experiences of suffering in saṃsāra. O Blessed One, we pray that you
                            liberate us from birth, old age, disease, death, misery, despair,
                            lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and distress.” </p>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One replied, “O sons of a noble family, with roots of virtue that
                        focus upon diligent application, may you acquire the superior intention
                        directed at the Three Jewels. Know all conditioned phenomena to be
                        impermanent and like illusions. <ref cRef="F.157.a"/> Be filled with joy at
                        upholding the holy Dharma. May you worship, revere, and venerate it more and
                        more. Know it as supreme compassion for all beings. Consider the one who
                        expounds the Dharma as a tathāgata. Consider virtuous friends as gurus. Keep
                        in mind, cultivate, and spread the various Dharma discourses. O sons of a
                        noble family, you will be liberated from all sufferings, all births, old
                        age, disease, death, misery, unhappiness, and great distress. You will be
                        liberated from the noose of saṃsāra. Practice the roots of virtue, that is,
                        the noble eightfold path. May you turn away from the state of not being
                        vigilant. Sons of noble family, once beings adopt even a single training of
                        the Tathāgata for only a short while, they will be liberated from all
                        suffering, experience pleasant rebirths, and will not experience negative
                        forms of existence. That being so, what need is there to mention those who,
                        after abandoning jokes, amusement, pleasure, and games, through their
                        sublime devotion to the Tathāgata perform rituals to him, live with superior
                        intentions, and practice the restoration and purification of their vows with
                        the eight-branched fasting ritual? What need is there to mention that all
                        those who practice these sorts of conduct will not be born in the three
                        negative forms of existence, but will pass to pleasant ones, and that,
                        having experienced the happiness of gods and humans, their suffering will
                        come to an end so that gradually they will fully and completely awaken to
                        unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Whosoever has the body of a woman tainted by the fundamental and secondary
                        defilements, if they genuinely take refuge in the Three Jewels and adopt the
                        training, whether for one day, half a day, or just a moment, <ref cRef="F.157.b"/> they will all dispel that condition of being a woman,
                        suffering, unhappiness, and afflictions. Having put an end to suffering,
                        they will go to pleasant forms of existence until they become fully and
                        perfectly awakened buddhas within unsurpassable, complete, and perfect
                        awakening. O sons of a noble family, the infantile do not recognize that one
                        who genuinely takes up the pledges and the training commitments of body,
                        speech, and mind is endowed with many qualities and great roots of virtue.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p><!--modularPassage type=auspiciousSigns-->At that moment, a great noise
                        resounded in the sky. All the retinue marveled, upon which a great rain of
                        flowers and perfume fell.<!--/modularPassage-->
                        <!--modularPassage type=multipleResult-->One hundred thousand beings were
                        all liberated from suffering and established in unsurpassable, complete, and
                        perfect awakening—the spiritual level from which there can be no relapse.
                        Moreover, ten million beings focused upon taking refuge in the Buddha,
                        Dharma, and Saṅgha, and generated bodhicitta for the first
                        time.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The tathāgatas, too, all disappeared. Then, Vajrapāṇi and the others, all the
                        vajra holders, Śakra, Brahmā, the protectors of the world, and the four
                        kings spoke these words to the Blessed One: </p>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Vajrapāṇi and the others, all the vajra holders, Śakra, Brahmā, the
                            protectors of the world, and the four kings</speaker>
                        <p>“Thanks to the Tathāgata, we have respite. We have heard the Dharma
                            discourses and the names of the tathāgatas. To the Blessed One, we have
                            dedicated our countries, cities, and temples as well as our bodies and
                            lives so that the Dharma will be taught, copied, recited, worshipped,
                            and proclaimed. We will preserve it. We will protect it. We will
                            accomplish all its purposes. We will ensure that wealth and grains are
                            well provided. We will ensure that the Blessed One will be venerated
                            everywhere. We will ensure that people are free from all diseases. We
                            will ensure that we give mindfulness, power, and inspiration.” </p>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The Blessed One <ref cRef="F.158.a"/> declared, “Excellent. This is
                        excellent!” And he told them, “At all costs, make sure in this way that
                        these teachings of the Dharma, which are the pledge of the Tathāgata, will
                        not quickly disappear.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p><!--modularPassage type=concludingPraise-->When the Blessed One had spoken in
                        this way, all the bodhisattva mahāsattvas, such as Noble Avalokiteśvara,
                        Vajrapāṇi, and others, as well as the great śrāvakas and the entire retinue,
                        as well as the world of the gods, human beings, asuras, and gandharvas,
                        rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <p> Here ends the noble Mahāyāna sūtra entitled <title xml:lang="eng">The
                            Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of
                            Attaining the Buddha’s Powers</title>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho
                            ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo.</title> Toh 186, Degé Kangyur vol. 61, folios 143b4–158a4.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho
                            ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title>. Toh 186, Narthang Kangyur vol. 61, folios
                        228a3–251b6.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho
                            ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title>. Toh 186, sTog Kangyur vol. 54, folios 332a1–351b1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho
                            ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo.
                            bka’ ’gyur</title> (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur],
                        krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The
                        Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center).
                        108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China
                        Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 61, pp. 387–420.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Sanskrit Fragments</head>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory. “The Five Leaves of the
                        Buddhabalādhānaprātihāryavikurvāna-nirdeśa-sūtra Found at Gilgit.” <title xml:lang="eng" level="j">Journal of Indian Philosophy</title>, vol. 5
                        (no. 4), 1978. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Dutt, Nalinaksha. “Buddhabalādhānaprātihārya-vikurvānanirdeśa-sūtra,” in
                            <title xml:lang="eng" level="s">Gilgit Manuscripts</title>, vol. IV,
                        173-183. Calcutta, 1959; reprinted Delhi: Sri Satguru Publications, 1984.
                        [Note: an edition of the same fragments as in Schopen (1978) but with
                        numerous passages reconstructed from the Tibetan and inserted without
                        annotation.] </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl>Burnouf, Eugène. <title xml:lang="eng">Introduction to the History of
                            Indian Buddhism</title>. Chicago &amp; London: University of Chicago
                        Press, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chang, Garma C.C. (ed.). <title xml:lang="eng">A Treasury of Mahāyāna
                            Sūtras: Selections from the Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title>. New York:
                        Pennsylvania State University, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cleary, Thomas. <title xml:lang="eng">The Flower Ornament Scripture: A
                            Translation of the Avatamsaka Sutra</title>. Boston &amp; London:
                        Shambhala, 1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="eng">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar
                            and Dictionary</title>. Vol. 2: Dictionary. New Haven: Yale University
                        Press, 1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl>La Vallée Poussin (trs.), Louis de. <title xml:lang="eng">Abhidharmakośabhāṣya of Vasubandhu</title>. Berkeley: Asian Humanities
                        Press, 1988–90.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lamotte, Etienne (trs.). <title xml:lang="eng">Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra: The
                            Concentration of Heroic Progress</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass,
                        2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rotman, Andy (trs.). <title xml:lang="eng">Divine Stories:
                            Divyāvadāna</title>, Part 1. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rahula, Walpola. <title xml:lang="eng">Abhidharmasamuccaya: The Compendium
                            of Higher Teaching (philosophy) by Asanga</title>. Fremont: Asian
                        Humanities Press, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sasaki, Genjun. Linguistic Approach to Buddhist Thought. Delhi: Motilal
                        Banarsidass, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory. <title xml:lang="eng">Figments and Fragments of Māhāyana
                            Buddhism in India: More Collected Papers</title>. Honolulu: University
                        of Hawaii Press, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vaidya, P.L. (ed.). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>. Buddhist
                        Sanskrit Texts No. 20. Darbhanga: Mithila Institute, 1959.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te1">attainment of the Buddha’s
                                powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs skyed pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">balādhāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te2">Blessed One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavān, bhagavat</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te3">karmic circumstances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi gzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karmavastu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te4">saṅgha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ’dun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṅgha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Community.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te5">eon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bskal pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te6">Dharma discourse</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi rnam grangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmaparyāya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te7">nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan las ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Extinction of suffering.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te8">assurance</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’jigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four kinds of assurance of a Tathāgata
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturvaiśāraya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi
                                    ’jigs pa bzhi</foreign>) are: 1) assurance concerning complete
                                awakening (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhisambodhivaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad mkhyen pa la mi ’jigs pa</foreign>);
                                2) assurance concerning the destruction of the impurities (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsravakṣayavaiśāradya</foreign>,
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa zad pa mkhyen pa
                                    la mi ’jigs pa</foreign>); 3) assurance concerning harmful
                                things (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">antarāyikadharmavaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bar du gcod pa’i chos la mi ’jigs
                                pa</foreign>); 4) assurance concerning the path that leads to
                                emancipation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nairyāṇikapratipadvaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thob par ’gyur bar nges par ’byung ba’i lam la
                                    mi ’jigs pa</foreign>). (See Rahula 2001: 230, in which they are
                                called “perfect self-confidence”).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te9">female lay vow holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāsikā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te10">great trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te11">Mahāyāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Great vehicle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te12">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Hearer.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te13">insight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te14">extraordinary transformation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par ’phrul pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvāṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te15">male lay vow holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāsaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te16">miracle</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cho ’phrul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihārya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te17">monk</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge’ slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te18">nun</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge’ slong ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣuṇī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te19">Omniscient One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad mkhyen pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvajñā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te20">bases of supernatural powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipādā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four bases of supernatural powers (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa
                                    bzh</foreign>i) are: 1) concentration through will (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">chanda</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dun pa</foreign>); 2)
                                concentration through vigor (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson
                                    ’grus</foreign>); 3) concentration through the mind (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">citta</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam pa</foreign>); 4)
                                concentration through investigation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mīmāṃsā</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpyod pa</foreign>). See Rahula 2001:
                                163.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te21">power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ten powers (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bcu</foreign>) of the Tathāgata are 1)
                                the power of knowledge of what is possible and what is not possible
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sthānāsthānajñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnas dang gnas ma yin pa mkhyen pa’i
                                    stobs</foreign>); 2) the power of knowledge of the individual
                                results of actions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karmasvakajñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi rnam smin mkhyen pa’i
                                stobs</foreign>); 3) the power of knowledge of different practices
                                leading to various destinies (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvatragāminīpratipajjñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad du ’gro ba’i lam mkhyen pa’i
                                    stobs</foreign>); 4) the power of knowledge of the different
                                dispositions and tendencies of different beings (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anekadhātunānādhātujñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams sna tshogs mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>);
                                5) the power of knowledge of the different aspirations of beings
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nānādhimuktijñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mos pa sna tshogs mkhyen pa’i
                                stobs</foreign>); 6) the power of knowledge of the different degrees
                                of development of the faculties and inclinations of beings (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriyaparāparyajñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po mchog dang mchog ma yin pa mkhyen
                                    pa’i stobs</foreign>); 7) the power of knowledge of the
                                absorptions, deliverances, concentrations, and attainments (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyānavimokṣasamādhisamāpattijñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan dang rnam thar dang ting
                                    nge ’dzin dang snyoms par ’jug pa thams cad mkhyen pa’i
                                    stobs</foreign>); 8) the power of knowledge of previous lives
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūrvanivāsajñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngon gyi gnas rjes su dran pa mkhyen pa’i
                                    stobs</foreign>); 9) the power of knowledge of the deaths and
                                births of beings according to their actions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cyutyupapādajñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho bo dang skye ba mkhyen
                                    pa’i stobs</foreign>); and 10) the power of knowledge of the
                                destruction of the impurities (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsravakṣayajñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa zad pa mkhyen pa’i
                                    stobs</foreign>). (Rahula 2001: 229–230, n118).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te22">gnosis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te23">sextillion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye ba khrag khrig brgya stong </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te24">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Solitary awakened one.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te25">state of concentration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te26">supernatural powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The supernatural powers of a śrāvaka correspond
                                to the first <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhijnā</foreign>: “Being one he becomes many, being many he
                                becomes one; he becomes visible, invisible; goes through walls,
                                ramparts and mountains without being impeded, just as through air;
                                he immerses himself in the earth and emerges from it as if in water;
                                he goes on water without breaking through it, as if on [solid]
                                earth; he travels through the air crosslegged like a winged bird; he
                                takes in his hands and touches the moon and the sun, those two
                                wonderful, mighty beings, and with his body he extends his power as
                                far as the Brahma world” (Lamotte 2003: 20). The great supernatural
                                powers (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāṛddhi</foreign>)
                                of bodhisattvas are: “causing trembling, blazing, illuminating,
                                rendering invisible, transforming, coming and going across
                                obstacles, reducing or enlarging worlds, inserting any matter into
                                one’s own body, assuming the aspects of those one frequents,
                                appearing and disappearing, submitting everyone to one’s will,
                                dominating the supernormal power of others, giving intellectual
                                clarity to those who lack it, giving mindfulness, bestowing
                                happiness, and finally, emitting beneficial rays.” (Lamotte 2003:
                                30).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te27">to be converted</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaineya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te28">yojana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpag tsad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te29">garlands of the buddhas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas phal po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhāvataṃsaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Here, the name of a particular state of
                                concentration (but also the title of a composite Mahāyāna sūtra or
                                “family” of sūtras, Toh 44).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te30">sovereign power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byin gyi rlabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhiṣṭhāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te31">the eight branches of
                                Āyurveda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe’i rig pa yan lag brgyad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭāṅgāyurveda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The eight branches are: 1) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śalya</foreign> (surgery), 2) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śālākya</foreign> (treatment of
                                diseases of the head and neck), 3) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">agada</foreign> (treatment of poisoning),4)
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumāra bharaṇa</foreign>
                                (pediatrics), 5) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāya
                                    cikitsā</foreign> (treatment of internal diseases), 6) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta kriyā</foreign> (treatment
                                of diseases caused by spirits), 7) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vāji karaṇa</foreign> (aphrodisiacs), and 8)
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rasāyana</foreign>
                                (rejuvenation).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-te32">boiled oil</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’bru mar bskol ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">taila</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Āyurvedic medicine, taila can be used both
                                internally and externally. It is produced by boiling herbs in edible
                                oil, such as sesame seed oil.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe1">Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’khrugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akṣobhya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe2">Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag tu med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">amitābha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe3">Aśoka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aśoka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe4">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāvalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe5">Established in Peace</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu zhi bar bkod pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe6">Hero</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe7">Kanakumūni</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser thub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kanakumūni</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe8">Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāśyapa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe9">Krakucchanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">log par dang sal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krakucchanda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe10">Lotus Born</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad mo ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">padmasaṃbhava</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe11">Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maitreya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe12">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mañjuśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe13">Maudgalyayāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maudgalyayāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe14">Pacifier of All Fears</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs pa thams cad rab tu zhi bar mdzad pa
                            </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe15">Pacifier of All Negative Forms of
                                Existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan song thams cad zhi bar mdzad pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe16">Powerful Intelligence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po’i blo gros </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe17">Purifier of All Rebirths</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’gro ba thams cad yongs su byong ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe18">Śāripūtra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāripūtra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe19">Śikhin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug phud can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śikhin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe20">Ānandaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ānandaśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe21">Candanaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsan dan gyi dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">candanaśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe22">Stainless Arising</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med par ’byung ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe23">Stainless Full Moon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba rgyas pa dri ma med pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe24">Subhūti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">subhūti</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe25">Subjugator of All Demon
                                Forces</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud thams cad kyi stobs rab tu ’joms pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe26">Bhaiṣajyaguru
                                Vaidūryaprabharāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi bla bai du rya’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhaiṣajyaguru vaidūryaprabharāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Teacher of Medicine, King of Vaiḍūrya
                                Light.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe27">the One Who Looks at All Beings with
                                Love</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can thams cad sdug par thong ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe28">the One Whose Intelligence Has Been
                                Completely Purified</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros rnam dag pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe29">Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag na rdo rje, phyag na rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajrapāṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe30">Vigataśoka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan bral ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vigataśoka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe31">Vipāśyin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par gzigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vipāśyin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe32">Viśvabhū</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad skyob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viśvabhū</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe33">Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yama</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pe34">Prasenajit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsal rgyal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prasenajit</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl1">Endowed with Realization and
                                Intelligence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtogs pa dang blo gros su ldan pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl2">Excellent Attainment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khyad par thob pa </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl3">Fearless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirbhaya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl5">Free from Negative Forms of
                                Existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan ’gro dang bral ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl6">Vaiḍūrya Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bai du rya snang ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl7">Lotus Excellence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad mo’i bla ma </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl8">Moon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl9">Peace</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl10">Perfect Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs par snang ba </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl11">Possessed of Power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl12">Sahā world system</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed kyi ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sahālokadhātu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl13">Stainless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimalā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl14">Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Endowed with happiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl15">Vārāṇasī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bA rA na sI </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vārāṇasī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-061-006-pl16">grove of the caretaker of mango
                                trees</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a mra srung ba’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmrapālīvana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A phrase usually translated as Āmrapālī’s grove,
                                referring to the grove in Vaiśālī donated to the Buddha by the
                                courtesan Āmrapālī (“Protected by a Mango Tree”), but here possibly
                                to be interpreted as a generic term, as the narrative locates it in
                                Vārāṇasī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>