<!--  Edited and finalized by John, placed in TEI folder 22 June 2016 --><!-- copied from tei production folder 2016_08_15-->
<?xml-model href="oxygen:/Exist$84000-AWS/db/84000/schema/84000-ODD.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཆོས་བདུན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="eng">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven
                    Qualities</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara­paripṛcchā­sapta­dharmaka</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཆོས་བདུན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis
                    zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="eng"> The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Inquiry of
                    Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryāvalokiteśvara­paripṛcchā­sapta­dharmaka­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain">Translated by the University of Calgary Buddhist
                    Studies team<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the
                    Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng">James B. Apple</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1 <date>2014 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <lb/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-057-009"/>
                <date>2014</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <ref>Toh 150</ref>, <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 57 (mdo sde, pa), folios 331a
                        – 331b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Dīpaṃkaraśrījñāna</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Gewai Lodrö</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!--Contents											
		Summary												
	             Acknowledgments
		Introduction
		The Translation
		 The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities
		Notes
		Bibliography-->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>The sūtra is introduced with the Buddha residing on Vulture Peak Mountain in
                    Rājagṛha, together with a great monastic assembly of 1,250 monks and a multitude
                    of bodhisattva mahāsattvas. The Buddha is approached and asked by the
                    bodhisattva mahāsattva Avalokiteśvara about the qualities that should be
                    cultivated by a bodhisattva who has just generated the altruistic mind set on
                    attaining awakening. The Buddha briefly expounds seven qualities that should be
                    practiced by such a bodhisattva, emphasizing mental purity and cognitive
                    detachment from conceptuality. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                <p>Translation by the University of Calgary Buddhist Studies team. This sūtra was
                    introduced and translated by James B. Apple.</p>
                <p>This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <title xml:lang="eng">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara‌ on the Seven
                        Qualities</title>
                        <note place="end">Within the title, DGoHeJLQ have 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug</foreign>; FSZ have 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug</foreign>. Go has the 
                        title <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gyis zhus pa / 
                        byang chub sems dpa’i slab pa bdun pa</foreign> (“The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara: 
                        the Seven Points of a Bodhisattva’s Training”).</note>
                        is a brief sūtra describing seven qualities that should be
                        cultivated by a bodhisattva immediately upon generating the altruistic mind
                        set on attaining awakening. The mind of awakening is the intention or
                        resolution to attain full and complete buddhahood for the benefit of oneself
                        and all sentient beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The structure of the sūtra is in three parts: the opening formula that gives
                        the time, place, and Buddha’s retinue when the discourse was taught; the
                        prescription of seven dharmas to be cultivated; and a formulaic
                        conclusion.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p> The Buddha delivers his teaching in response to the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Avalokiteśvara’s inquiry. What is unusual in the formulaic inquiry phrases
                        of this sūtra is that Avalokiteśvara places his right knee in the center of
                        a lotus flower; in most sūtras that follow such a pattern, the questioner
                        places his knee on the ground. This implicitly demonstrates the reverence in
                        which Avalokiteśvara was held by the compilers or transmitters of this
                        sūtra. The Buddha prescribes seven qualities or dharmas that one should
                        cultivate after producing the mind of awakening. They emphasize mental
                        purity and cognitive detachment from conceptuality. These prescriptions are
                        straightforward and easy to understand according to the overview of the
                        sūtra by Pekar Sangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad dkar bzang po</foreign>, see bibliography).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <title xml:id="eng">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven
                            Qualities</title> was initially translated from an Indian language, most
                        likely Sanskrit, into Tibetan by Atiśa Dīpaṃkara­śrī­jñāna (982-1054) and the
                        Tibetan monk Gewai Lodrö.</p>
                    <p>The translation took place in all probability at the monastery of Tholing in
                        West Tibet, where the rulers of Ngari (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnga’ ris</foreign>) first officially welcomed Atiśa
                        and where Gewai Lodrö was active.<note place="end">See Chattopadhyaya 1967:
                            325.</note> Gewai Lodrö collaborated with the great Kaśmīri scholar
                        Subhūtiśrī(śānti) in Tholing before working with Atiśa. Atiśa and Gewai
                        Lodrö worked together on several translations found in editions of the
                        Tengyur, including the verses of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­patha­pradīpa</title> (<ref>Toh 3947</ref>) and the <bibl>
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cittotpāda­saṃvara­vidhikrama</title> (<ref>Toh
                                3969</ref>)</bibl>, and two texts found in most Kangyurs, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍi­samaya­sūtra</title> (<ref>Toh 299</ref>) and the
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaika­vīra­mahā­tantra­rāja</title> (<ref>Toh
                            544</ref>, <ref>Degé 541</ref>).<note place="end">See Dharmachakra Translation Group 2016.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p> Atiśa makes explicit reference to this sūtra in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­mārga­pradīpa­pañjikā</title>, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cittotpāda­saṃvara­vidhikrama</title>, and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­karaṇḍodghāṭa­nāma­madhyamakopadeśa</title> (<ref>Toh 3930, English
                        translation Apple 2010: 142-43</ref>). In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­mārga­pradīpa­pañjikā</title> this sūtra is mentioned in the
                        sections discussing the mind of awakening (Sherburne 2000: 101), the
                        monastic life (Sherburne 2000: 127), and the supersensory knowledges
                        (Sherburne 2000: 209). The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cittotpāda­saṃvara­vidhikrama</title> also advocates the practice of this
                        sūtra’s prescriptions for a bodhisattva who wishes to attain supersensory
                        knowledge quickly (Sherburne 2000: 540-541).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>The present translation from Tibetan is based upon a critical edition of ten
                        Kangyur exemplars. A detailed philological analysis of the extant editions
                        of this sūtra indicates that the oldest copies of this sūtra are preserved
                        among Western Kangyur collections such as the Gondhla Collection, Hemis
                        Kangyur, and Phudrak (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phug brag</foreign>)
                        Kangyur.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to the Bhagavān
                        Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="thusDid">-->Thus have I heard at one time. The
                        Bhagavān was dwelling in Rājagṛha<note place="end">GoLSZ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab na</foreign>; DFHeJQ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab</foreign>
                        </note> on the Vulture
                        Peak mountain<note place="end">FGoLSZ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod
                                kyi phung po</foreign>; DHeJQ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod
                                phung po</foreign>
                        </note> together with a great monastic assembly of
                        1,250 monks and a multitude of bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas.<!--</modularPassage>--> At that time, the bodhisattva
                        mahāsattva Noble Avalokiteśvara rose from his seat, arranged his upper robe
                        on one shoulder, and placed his right knee in the center of a lotus flower. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>Joining his hands in devotion toward the Bhagavān, he asked him, “Bhagavān, in how many qualities should a bodhisattva train, just after
                            generating the altruistic mind set on attaining awakening?”<note place="end"> FGoHeLSZ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub tu
                                    sems</foreign>; DJQ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi
                                    sems</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Bhagavān replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Noble Avalokiteśvara’s
                        inquiry with the following words.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>“Kulaputra, bodhisattvas should train in seven qualities just after
                            generating the altruistic mind set on attaining awakening.<note place="end"> DFGoHeLSZ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub tu sems
                                    bskyed</foreign>; JQ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems
                                    bskyed</foreign>
                        </note> What are the seven? They are as follows. </p>
                    <list>
                        <item>“(1) One should not have sexual enjoyment even in thought, not to
                                mention joining together the two sexual organs. <ref cRef="F.331.b"/>
                        </item>
                        <item>“(2) One should not take up with a non-virtuous friend even in
                                dreams.</item>
                        <item>“(3) With a mind free like a bird, one should be completely
                                without grasping.</item>
                        <item>“(4) With mastery in skill and wisdom, one should be without pride
                                and reified conceptions of ‘I.’ </item>
                        <item>“(5) One should abandon conceptions of existence and non-existence
                                and be firm in the emancipation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimokṣa</foreign>) of emptiness.</item>
                        <item>“(6) One should not take delight in saṃsāra through an inauthentic
                                conceptual understanding, saṃsāra being like a magical illusion or
                                dream.</item>
                        <item>“(7) And one should refrain from deprecating the law of cause and
                                effect. </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>“Kulaputra, a bodhisattva who has just generated the altruistic mind set
                            on attaining awakening<note place="end">DFGoJQ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub tu sems bskyed</foreign>; HeLSZ
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems bskyed</foreign>
                        </note> should
                            train in these seven qualities.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="finalPraise">-->When the Bhagavān had spoken, the
                        bodhisattva Noble Avalokiteśvara, along with the monks and bodhisattvas,
                        rejoiced and praised highly what had been proclaimed by the 
                        Bhagavān.<!--</modularPassage>-->
                        <note place="end">Go omits <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags 
                            pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug dang / dge slong de dag dang byang chub sems dpa’
                                de dag yi rangs te/ bcom ldan ’das kyis gsungs pa la mngon par bstod
                                do</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <milestone unit="chunk"/>
                    <p>This completes the Noble Mahāyāna sūtra, <title xml:lang="eng">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on
                        the Seven Qualities</title>.<note place="end">DFHeJLQSZ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos bdun pa</foreign>; Go <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang sems
                                dpa’i / slab pa bdun pa</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Translated and edited by the Indian master Dīpaṃkara­śrī­jñāna and the
                        translator monk Gewai Lodrö.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head>Abbreviations</head>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>MsK</abbr>
                        <expan>Manuscript Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>PK</abbr>
                        <expan>Printed Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé (sde dge) PK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>F</abbr>
                        <expan>Phug brag MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>Go</abbr>
                        <expan>Gondhla Collection MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>He</abbr>
                        <expan>Hemis MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>Lithang PK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>L</abbr>
                        <expan>London MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>Q</abbr>
                        <expan>Peking Qianlong PK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <abbr>Z</abbr>
                        <expan>Shey Palace MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Tibetan Kangyur Editions</head>
                    <bibl>
                        (rKTs = University of Vienna Resources for Kanjur and Tibetan Studies, 
                            www.istb.univie.ac.at/kanjur/xml3/xml/. For other abbreviations, see Notes.)</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa
                            chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo
                            (Āryāvalokiteśvara­pari­pṛcchā­sapta­dharmaka­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra)</title>. Toh
                        150, rKTs-K150, D 150, Degé Kangyur (PK) vol. 57 (mdo sde, pa), folios
                        331a-331b. http://tbrc.org/link?RID=W22084 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa
                            chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150,
                        He48.6, Hemis Kangyur (He) (MsK), mdo sde, nga, folios 296b-299b. Digital
                        scans from rKTs. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa
                            chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, J94,
                        Lithang (li thang) Kangyur (J) (PK), vol. 52 (mdo sde, pa), folios
                        278a-279a. http://tbrc.org/link?RID=W4CZ7445 </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa
                            chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, Q
                        817, Peking Qianlong (Q) (PK), vol. 33 (mdo sna tshogs, nu), folios
                        293b-294b (p 36 in bound edition). </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa
                            chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo.</title> bka’ ’gyur (dpe
                        bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib
                        ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation
                        Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung
                        go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
                        2006-2009, vol. 57, pp. 875-878.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gyis zhus pa
                            / byang chub sems dpa'i slab pa bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title>. Go16,04, Gondhla Collection (Go) (MsK), vol. 16 (ka),
                        folios 49a-49b. Digital scans from rKTs. See also Tauscher (2008)
                        below.</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus
                            pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po'i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150,
                        L154, London Kangyur (L) (MsK), vol. 52 (mdo sde, za), folios 8b-9a. Digital
                        scans from rKTs. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus
                            pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150,
                        C790, Phug brag Kangyur (F) (MsK), vol. 80 (mdo sde, la), folios 371b-372b.
                        Institute for Advanced Studies of World Religions. 1990. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus
                            pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po'i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150,
                        Z242, Shey Palace Manuscript Kangyur (Z) (MsK), vol.69 (mdo, za), folios
                        7a-8a. Digital scans from rKTs. </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus
                            pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150,
                        S211, Stok Palace Manuscript Kangyur (stog pho brang bris ma) (S)
                        (MsK), vol. 73 (mdo sde, za) folios 7b-8b. TBRC W22083. 109 vols. leh:
                        smanrtsis shesrig dpemzod, 1975-1980. http://tbrc.org/link?RID=W22083
                    </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Other references</head>
                    <bibl>Apple, James B. 2010. “Atiśa’s Open Basket of Jewels: A Middle Way Vision
                        in Late Phase Indian Vajrayāna.” <title level="j">The Indian International
                            Journal of Buddhist Studies 11</title>: 117-198.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chattopadhyaya, Alaka. 1967. <title xml:lang="eng">Atīśa and Tibet Life
                            and Works of Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna in relation to the History and Religion
                            of Tibet.</title>(Reprinted) New Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1999,
                        2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dharmachakra Translation Group. 2016. <title xml:lang="eng">The Tantra of Siddhaika­vīra.</title> Toh 544, in Tantra / Tantra Collection / Action tantras. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pad dkar bzang po (author), mi nyag mgon po (editor). “ ’phags pa spyan
                        ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa’i chos bdun pa’i mdo.” In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde spyi’i rnam bzhag</title>, p. 426. Beijing: mi
                        rigs dpe skrun khang (Minorities Publishing House), 2006. TBRC W1PD76588.
                        http://tbrc.org/link?RID=O2DB70299|O2DB702992DB70539$W1PD76588 </bibl>
                    <bibl>Sherburne, Richard. 2000. <title xml:lang="eng">The Complete Works of
                            Atīśa Śrī Dīpaṁkara Jñāna, Jo-bo-rje: The Lamp for the Path and
                            Commentary, together with the newly translated Twenty-Five Key Texts
                            (Tibetan and English Texts)</title>. New Delhi: Aditya Prakashan.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tauscher, Helmut. 2008. <title xml:lang="eng">Catalogue of the Gondhla
                            proto-Kanjur</title>. Vienna: Arbeitskreis für Tibetische und
                        Buddhistische Studien Universität Wien.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-te1">generating the altruistic mind set on
                                attaining awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems bskyed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicittotpāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The altruistic resolve to achieve complete and
                                perfect Buddhahood for the sake of oneself and all sentient
                                beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-te2">the opening formula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gleng gzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nidāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-pe1">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva who first appears in the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī­vyūha</title> sūtra (Toh 115) and then in a number of other Mahāyāna sūtras
                                such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sad­dharma­puṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113). Avalokiteśvara develops into a great
                                bodhisattva who embodies compassion with multiple forms in Indian,
                                Chinese, and Tibetan Buddhism.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-pe2">Atiśa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a ti sha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atiśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Atiśa Dīpaṃkara­śrī­jñāna (982–1054 C.E.), often
                                referred to in Tibetan as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">jo bo</foreign>, “(The) Lord,” was a renowned figure
                                in the history of Tibetan Buddhism famous for coming to Tibet and
                                revitalizing Buddhism there during the early eleventh
                                century.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-pe3">Gewai Lodrö</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">-</term>
                            <term type="definition">Ma Gewai Lodrö (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma dge ba’i blo gros</foreign>), a Tibetan
                                lotsāva, was an important disciple of Rinchen Zangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen bzang
                                po</foreign>, 958-1055) who translated several texts with Atiśa and worked
                                with the Kaśmīri master Subhūti­śri­bhadra to translate a number of
                                pramāṇa texts.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-pe4">Subhūtiśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">-</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūtiśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Subhūtiśrī(śānti) was a paṇḍita from Kaśmīr
                                invited to Western Tibet during the reign of the king <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Lha lde</foreign> who
                                translated a number of Prajñāpāramitā texts, sūtras, and works of
                                pramāṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss>
                            <term xml:id="UT22084-057-009-pl1">Tholing</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tho ling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">-</term>
                            <term type="definition">The important West Tibetan monastery founded in
                                996 C.E. by King Yeshé Ö (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes 'od</foreign>) and the translator Rinchen Zangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen bzang
                                po</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>